Schafer: I need to get accustomed
to money being around.
That's the thing.
This is for the therapy,
the physical therapy
of getting me used to actually
not being afraid of money.
Offscreen voice: Richard Branson
does the same thing.
Schafer: Ah! You guys, what is
this stuff that's all over me?
Offscreen voice: Beautiful.
Schafer: I can't apply it to myself..
Offscreen voice: Oh my God.
Schafer: I can't self-terminate.
Offscreen voice: Help me apply money.
Schafer: I can't self-monetize.
Schafer: So this is a more recent,
uh point-and-click adventure game.
I have to show you someone else's,
because I haven't made
one in a long time.
I used to make them back in the '90s.
This is Machinarium.
You role play this little
robot and you click around.
And these kind of games,
you walk the character around
by clicking on the ground somewhere
and pull on this handle here.
And then I can make this mine
cart come through the room.
Shahani: I'm sorry. What's that?
Schafer: I pulled this handle,
oh, that's right.
This doesn't work until I do this.
That's what a lot of adventure
game playing is like.
You're like, oh, this doesn't,
why doesn't this work?
Oh, I need this gear first.
I need to get the gear on the sprocket.
And so they're, they
move at a slower pace.
And some people really like that.
But it also means they're not
exactly as attention-getting
and as visceral and maybe as a
big block buster action game.
And it led us to this point
now where it's really hard
to get one of these games
made these days,
or at least get funding
for it from a publisher.
Shahani: Before getting into all that,
what put you on the map?
Like, just describe the game
that got you into game famous.
Schafer: Game famous.
You know, we just, each
game we made in the '90s,
we got a little more recognition for it.
And we were always pretty savvy
about getting our names on the box,
you know, so we're, hey.
You know, you have to kind of act
like you're famous before you're famous.
That sounds funny.
I learned that from an interview with
David Lee Roth about Van Halen.
Like we always acted
like we were hot shit.
We had a big hit, Full Throttle,
it's called Full Throttle and
it sold a million copies
and that was really big for
those PC graphic adventures.
And then I made a game
called Grim Fandango
and that won Game of
the Year with Game Spot
and that was the big
thing that helped a lot.
Grim Fandango is set in the
Land of the Dead, yeah.
And it was, it sold
about half a million units
and it was seen as not
being commercially successful.
And it was one of the reasons
that adventure games died.
I mean, I heard a friend of mine,
who worked in another game company,
saying we tried to get
an adventure game made
and they said, well look, you know,
Grim Fandango didn't do that well.
So obviously, you know, it was
a good game, it won Game of the Year.
And if Game of the Year can't sell,
you know, as many copies as it
needs to, then maybe that genre's dead.
So I feel some responsibility to make
a good game and make it do well.
Rice: He's been excited about it.
I mean, he's wanted to return to
adventure games for a while
and it's just been a matter of not
knowing how to make that happen.
Schafer: But fans are always saying
they would want, they want one,
but a publisher would say, we
can't make money doing those.
So something like Kickstarter shows up,
which is this crowd sourcing website,
where everybody can back a project.
You pitch your project and you get
backers and then if you meet your goals,
you get the money and
you build your project.
Doing an adventure game is interesting,
because it's the only, like the
only way you could do that,
letting the fans like, kind of put
their money where their mouth is.
Is it that? Wait a second.
Did I get that backwards? Yeah.
Host: No, you're right. Yeah.
Some loud mouth fan, no,
I don't want to buy Trenched,
but what about an adventure game?
Schafer: Exactly.
Shahani: Explain your
Kickstarter campaign.
What have you just done?
Schafer: Yeah. What have we done?
Schafer: Oh, sorry.
I didn't see you there.
You caught me indulging in one
of my many impressive hobbies.
I'm Tim Schafer.
Schafer: And so we put a pitch video
up where we said we want to make a game.
And the idea was, what if we made
one of these adventure games
that most publishers don't
want to fund these days?
And one of my favorite types of
games to make is adventure games.
But these days, it seems
like adventure games
are almost a bit of a lost art form.
They exist in our dreams and
our memories and in Germany.
Schafer: Maybe that would
get people excited about
getting a chance to do something
that couldn't be funded any other way.
Schafer: It's perfect.
We got the perfect team here
at Double Fine to make it.
We got the inventor of the
genre here, Ron Gilbert.
Oh, look! There he is right now.
Maybe he'll help us.
He'll help us.
Gilbert: You know, we've always
talked about wanting to do,
you know, more classic adventure stuff.
And so doing the
Kickstarter thing, it's like,
yeah, that sounds, I mean, that
sounds really like an interesting idea.
I think we were both very
skeptical about the amount of money.
Schafer: So, we are asking for
this much to make the game
and this much to film it.
And that may seem like a lot of money,
but it's really not that much for
a game budget these days.
It's pretty small, actually.
Schafer: And I just never thought
you could get the kind of money
that would actually pay for
a whole game budget.
Schafer: Hello, potential backers.
I could do all three options.
Thank you for donating well
over the amount we asked for.
That's so great.
We have too much money now.
Damn you!
Why haven't anyone given us any money?
I'm so sad.
That doesn't seem believable.
Yeah, we're not going to use that one.
Or just moderately, hello.
Thank you for dedicating
the appropriate amount of...
Schafer: Because the previous
projects in Kickstarter had only been,
I don't know what the
maximum was before then,
but it looked like
they're like forty grand.
You know, I mean, we're used to making
projects that were like, you know, Brütal.
Like 20 million dollars and these
smaller games, like two million.
It was like, no way you can get
two million from Kickstarter.
Could you?
Schafer: I hope this works out,
because it is kind of,
that enough people got together,
are they going to actually make
a game like this happen?
A game like, that we
haven't really been able to
make happen for business reasons
for like, many, many years.
Gilbert: Or we'll just prove
all those publishers right.
Schafer: Or we'll just
prove them all right.
Schafer: No, I mean
nothing I had done before
prepared me for what it's
like to work with publishers.
Rice: When you're
working with a publisher,
a lot of times they get
involved with design decisions.
And you have to make compromises.
Gilbert: You know, if
a publisher is out there,
from the outside kind of poking
in and making you do things.
You know, that's where I think
things can kind of come off the rails.
Schafer: And the way it felt,
I don't know if this makes any sense,
but my head, like the creative process
of making a game was like,
you look at a field of
floating, multi-colored dots,
drifting slowly to the ground.
And eventually when they hit the ground,
they're going to make like
a painting on the floor.
But you've got to kind of like move
them around, give them the right and see.
And then as they fall, you start
to see where you need more color
and you move them around and
slowly they settle and you just add a sound.
And then you're done.
So it'd be like, Tim, what do
you do with that green dot?
Phew, I can't tell you.
You're like, ok, that dot?
Can we just nail that down here.
Can we just say what that's going to be?
And you're like, no.
So let's just say where all the
red dots are going to be, ok.
Could you just nail
all the red dots down?
Like, no!
How about if we just start on this edge
and we just take all the dots,
like this and just nail all those dots.
No!
Rice: Yeah. The games
industry as a whole, I think,
is in a really weird
spot where it's like we're,
like the film industry used
to be way back in the day.
Where the publishers are
running mostly everything.
That's kind of how it
was for a long time
and it's only now that
people are starting to like
seek out the creators of the games.
That people who are making the game
and try to actually support those
people and lift them up a bit.
Young Man: Because Tim Schafer
has consistently put out quality games.
Man: Games that have very
large and dedicated followings.
Man: People would probably pay
him just to spit on their screen.
Young Man: And we do appreciate that.
We show our appreciation
by doing what we've done.
By giving them the funding
for this game in eight hours.
Rice: The whole like past month
has been like a complete blur.
It's gone so quick.
But, yeah, we were in Vegas
for DICE the day that we launched.
Schafer: And we'd had a hard
month, because we had a game cancel.
The whole team, we're
trying to figure out
whether we could swing
having this team stay on
or do we have to let go of twelve
people to keep the company afloat?
We've never laid off
anyone for money before.
So we were, and even besides
the financial concerns, it was just such a,
it doesn't feel like you're winning
when you have a game canceled.
You feel like it's a big,
you know, you've lost.
Schafer: I'm about to launch
our first Kickstarter project.
Rice: It kind of just all came together
right when we were out there
and we had a bit of time before
a meeting and we're like,
we could launch this today.
Schafer: Yeah, I did have to like
decide, well, we'll launch our Kickstarter.
That, for time, we're
like I guess $200,000.
We could make something for $200,000.
And I had to accept it, I might
only get $200,000, right?
And then when I was nervous
about it, so I upped it to three, right.
And so it was like, yeah, we
can make something for $300,000.
Because we could.
You know, we'd been talking
about iPhone games recently
and it's like three people for six
months or something like that.
Yeah, we could make something
with three people and six months.
It would look like a flash game or
it'd look like an iPhone game,
but it would technically be a game.
By all scientific definitions.
Schafer: I'm nervous.
Launch.
Review, i'll have to review it.
Rice: Oh, man.
That was such a letdown!
Schafer: OK. No, no,
that's just fine print.
It's just that I never
read these things.
Should I do it?
Rice: Yeah, do it.
Schafer: It couldn't hurt, right?
Rice: It could, but
we're not going to let it.
Schafer: Whoo!
Rice: I remember like as soon as we
hit it up and we refresh, it was like at $30.
We're like, holy crap!
There's already $30.
Schafer: I think I'm going to look at
how much, I don't care about money.
I'm not going to look. I'm going
to look, just one second.
Rice: What are we at?
OK, so we posted this, what?
Two hours ago, right?
Schafer: Two hours ago.
We launched our Kickstarter
project two hours ago.
$106,000 in 56.
A hundred and six,
I can't count so high.
It's such a high number, that's crazy.
It's too much money.
Rice: Yeah. So when we hit a million,
that was definitely like,
that was the day after.
One day after we launched, right?
Rice: What are we at?
Schafer: I want to just say I love
you guys and not for the money.
Offscreen: 999,700!
Muir: Oh my god, they're
counting down to a refresh.
F5!
Muir: Oh my God! It's so exciting.
Rice: What's the number?
Offscreen: Refresh! Refresh!
Min: The internet has crashed.
No!
Rice: And what? No!
Schafer: Where's my phone?
Muir: The Internet's crashed.
[Offscreen Yelling]
[Distortion]
I think they all died. They're dying!
Are you guys ok? What happened?
Oh, they're being
crushed. It's horrible.
Muir: Oh, no! No!
What happened?
[Distortion]
Muir: It's a million dollars!
Rice: Is it?
Muir: That's what a
million dollars sounds like.
Offscreen: What do you mean it crashed?
Offscreen: Kickstarter crashed.
Muir: Kickstarter crashed!
Schafer: No.
[Offscreen yelling]
Rice: Yeah, that was definitely
one of the high points,
where it was like, holy crap
-- This is a huge thing.
Muir: Whoo! A million in 24 hours.
Tim Schafer, you just made
a million dollars in 24 hours!
What do you, what are you doing?
Schafer: Yeah! I got to make a game.
Newscaster: Over the last few
days, Tim Schafer from Double Fine
took crowd funding site,
Kickstarter to fund his next game.
Schafer: It feels like a happening.
You know what I mean?
Like it feels like an event.
Newscaster: They're raising money
at a clip of a thousand dollars per minute.
It's incredible.
Host: One question that is
on everybody's mind.
You get the million dollars.
Did you immediately withdraw it all?
Put it into a vault and then dive
into it like Scrooge McDuck style?
Schafer: Then during
Kickstarter, it made it,
I don't know what it was,
but it made everyone just take
that big basket of money
and shake it out over our heads.
It really was like the end
of "It's a Wonderful Life".
[Music]
Offscreen: So excited.
Offscreen: Thumbs up?
Man: Thumbs up, yes.
That was pretty amazing.
I told you, adventure
games are not dead!
The thing that I noticed was that
it was just such a morale
boost to the whole team.
And you know, I think it just
felt like a lot of goodwill
and love coming towards the company
and everyone got super excited about it.
And because it was like
this feeling of like,
we knew those people were
there, we knew they were.
But, because sometimes they don't
show up when you make a game.
You know, you make
a game, you release it,
you know, like I thought it was
going to sell a lot and it didn't.
You're like, where are all
those people that it feels like,
there's all this goodwill out there.
Man #1: It's two million.
Man #2: One of us has to stop shaving.
Man #2: He has to shave my
scrotum if it gets to two million.
Man #1: Only if he
agrees to do it on camera.
Offscreen: Congratulations.
Schafer: It had been a long
time since we had experience
where it felt like we were the winners.
We were at DICE and I
was walking through DICE,
feeling like a winner,
which is really kind of like,
not that I feel like a loser,
but usually feel like the
alternative, alternative to money.
I mean i'm proud of all our games
and I wouldn't switch them
with anyone else's games,
but usually walking in
a convention like that,
you're talking to the, you know,
the people who made Uncharted
and they're, they're really
nice and you're like, ah.
Congratulations on the game.
Did really well for you.
And like, you don't often feel like,
you feel like they're like the family
member who's like still living at home.
You know, like yeah.
They're all really nice
to us, but you know,
we haven't, it's different when
you make a bunch of money.
Schafer: And we raised 1.7
million dollars on Kickstarter.
[Applause]
Schafer: Is that auto refreshing?
Everyone: Yes.
Schafer: We were in the hotel room
and I was listening on
the Skype, on the iPad
and you just remember
like, click, click,
aha, aha, then all of a sudden, whooo!
Schafer: Distortion sound
as everyone lost their shit.
And right now we're at
almost 2.5 million dollars.
and we have six more days to go.
Rice, Offscreen: Everything
moved really quickly
and I actually didn't
really have a chance
to like let everything sit in
until yesterday, when it finished.
And I was like, finally it like hit
me and it was like, holy crap.
We did something really crazy here.
Schafer: 2 minutes!
[Crowd shouting and cheering]
So like we cleared in advance
I'm going to shake this up and
I'm going to spray it all over your head.
Why is that...
Ron!
My God, that's terrible for your teeth.
Offscreen: Two minutes!
Two minutes.
[Pop]
Offscreen: Premature! Premature!
Gilbert: There's still
a part of my skeptical
pessimistic brain that says, well,
you can never do this again.
That this was really kind of this
one time perfect storm thing.
But I don't know. I mean, maybe not.
[Music]
[Cheering]
I've been so happy about that
ever since Kickstarter started,
just thinking about how, I
still have to answer to people.
Like people funded the game, you know.
But they're exactly the
people I want to answer to.
Those are the people
I'm making dots for, right?
And all those things
like, and so it's like,
it's just this really liberating,
freeing thing to just
think that I'm just going to
have to worry about how good
the game is, almost nothing else.
[Music]
Schafer: I love you guys!
It has been an amazing
experience. So much love.
We know there's not, it's not
all about us and Double Fine,
but about you, the fans and
what you guys want to say
and do with your money and choose to do.
And make things happen for yourself.
I mean, I don't want to
make a huge speech here,
because I'll be all choked up.
Gilbert: Too late.
Schafer: But I just, I don't
want to say this is the end of the,
you know, the whole game
industry as we know it.
It's not, it's not.
And it's not, again it's not
like we're total replacement
of all publishers and publishing games.
There's still going to be,
there still might be a few games
made by publishers after today.
Just a couple games.
But it does mean if you've ever been
told that your part of a niche market,
if you've ever like,
when you're a kid and you had
your favorite TV show cancelled
or you hear about your favorite band
being dropped by their label
for not selling enough
and you've just been like why
does a big company get to choose
what music I listen to
or what movies I watch
or what TV shows I watch
or what game I get to play,
now you know that they
can't do that anymore.
You can choose. So thanks everybody.
[Cheering]
Thank you to the team!
Everybody!
Thanks to my parents
for backing the project
and everybody else's parents
who backed the project.
Does anybody else want to thank anybody?
Kipnis: Thank you Tim!
Thank you!
Thanks everyone and now we dance.
[Cheering]
Ron's dancing!
[Music]