Cambell: Hello?
Schafer: Hello!
Cambell: It's open.
Oh, god.
How many flights
of these stairs are there?
[Heavy breathing]
[Coughs]
[Gasping]
So out of shape.
Gonna die.
[Deep breaths]
[Knocking]
[Wheezing]
Cambell: Hi, dude.
Schafer: Hi.
Scott Campbell.
Cambell: You made it up the stairs.
Schafer: Do you wanna work
on our adventure game?
Cambell: Yes.
Schafer: Okay.
[Music]
Schafer: Ah, you wanna come
to the stand up?
Crook: Come and do our stand up.
We're gonna have it right here.
Cambell: You guys stand up
for the whole thing?
Schafer: Come to our stand up.
Cambell: Okay.
I kind of have to use the...
you know...
Schafer: Nope.
Cambell: ...you-know-what first.
Oh yeah?
We were doing stand ups
when you were here.
Kipnis: Ah, Scott, holy shit.
Hey!
Cambell: Hey!
Kipnis: Hey!
Cambell: How are you?
Is this how you guys always do it,
just standing in the middle?
Schafer: You stand in the middle and
then you close your eyes and you lean
and we pass the body around.
Rice: Good, how's it goin'?
Cambell: Good, man.
Schafer: You know Brandon?
Dillon: No, we haven't met before.
Schafer: Brandon, Scott Campbell.
Cambell: Hey man.
Skillman: Oh man, we're being filmed.
Man, this is so awkward,
but it's nice to see you.
McGarry: Oh, it's on camera.
What's up, buddy?
Good to see you.
Hackett: That's all we do
around here is hug.
Cambell: Hey, buddy.
Hug sounds good, man.
Muir: I never met Peter Chan
in person.
McGarry: I never met him either.
Crook: Really?
[Murmuring]
Schafer: Bap-bee-dee-bap-bup-ba-da,
buh-bum, ba-da-dum-dum-dum.
Ya-da-za-ha.
Let's see, are we all here?
Everyone here?
Hello, hello, everybody.
Hi, thanks for coming.
Uh, please join me in welcoming
some special guests
we have here today.
We have from--some out-of-towners.
We have Mr. Peter Chan
over here, Peter Chan.
Hello.
[applause]
Uh, we have Mr. Scott Campbell.
Where's Scott Campbell?
There's Scott Campbell!
Yay, Scott Campbell.
[Applause]
And we have, uh,
Nathan "Bagel" Stapley.
There he is.
[Applause]
Anyone else coming in
from out of town?
Is anyone here? Great.
Um, we are doing, um, uh,
an art jam for Reds.
Reds is the code name
for our Double Fine Adventure.
This last week, we did one of my
favorite things, which was the art jam,
which we got all our artists
from across the country
here in this room
sitting around one table
just drawing and talking and
pitching ideas back and forth.
And we had Peter Chan
who has been working with me
since "Monkey Island 2."
We have Scott Campbell, who's here
since the beginning of Double Fine.
And Nathan "Bagel" Stapley,
who, um,
whose art is gonna be featured
front and center
in the Double Fine Adventure,
and who has also been here since
the beginning of Double Fine.
It's good to see you guys,
I haven't seen, you know,
a lot of you in the office for a while,
so it's awesome to have you here.
Um, people who don't know who
these guys are, ask somebody.
[Laughter]
Cambell: You know, I'm excited.
It's like a total reunion.
The last time we were all together
was, um, beginning of "Brütal Legend."
Peter was--Peter's been on, I think,
every one of his projects.
Chan: Here that, uh, hired me.
Right here.
Gilbert: I hired more people in
this industry than you know.
Chan: Tim and everyone was going,
"We would like you
to come back
and help us out on this."
And that was the friendliest
you've seen Ron right there, fellas.
To collaborate with, uh,
these guys Ron and Tim again
is, you know, is like the good old days,
you know?
So I didn't want
to pass that up.
Schafer: Art is obviously really
critical to graphic adventures.
It's part of the defining thing of like, "Let's have
an adventure game, but let's add not just text to it.
Let's actually show the world."
And seeing beautiful worlds
laid out in front of you
that inspire your imagination.
Your desire to explore them
is such an important thing,
'cause they don't have,
um, you know,
an RPG's progression drive,
you know, or an addictive hook
like collectables or
something like that usually.
It's just the--the thing that pulls you
forward and keeps you going is the--
the extent to which we've ignited
your desire to explore.
So I was gonna go over the state
of the game like storywise
and what design there
is on the game,
and then talk about, uh,
art jam, too, a little bit,
'cause this is a little-- this is a
little earlier than I think we did--
Like, when Peter--by the time
Peter visited on "Brütal,"
we already had a bunch of art
that we then kind of bundled up
and made the factions
and stuff like that.
This is, I think, a little
earlier in the process.
I was hoping to--
I asked Greg to kind of
get you guys here as soon as possible
to help generate ideas while I'm designing the game,
'cause, um, the game could go
so many different areas.
And I have this idea about the boy and the girl,
but, you know, there's the spaceship,
but there could be
anything on the spaceship,
and there's this pastoral world,
but it could be any level of--
it could have anything in it right now,
and I think a lot of these, I think coming up
with just visual ideas for cool places to go
are just as valid a place to start as anything.
Petty: This one is, we're at such
an early state on, uh, Reds,
that, um, you know, Tim--
Tim's only really identified
a few very specific things for us.
Schafer: Right now, the
green cards are characters--
these are the characters so far--
and the yellow cards
are just story points.
Um, I'm gonna be adding locations here
and, um, puzzles
in different colors.
I mean, I told them a lot
about what we have.
That's really as far as the game has gone
because, um, I've been doing a lot of business stuff,
which is annoying.
Yeah, so I'm way behind on the design and the
puzzles, but we did hire a business guy.
Rice: So that's good.
Schafer: Which means I won't have
to work on Hausen anymore.
But luckily,
we just hired a business guy
to come in and take care
of that stuff.
Trying to get Brad's
new project signed,
and, uh, there were a lot
of meetings at E3 and stuff.
Um, you know,
there's a few more details
that only make sense to me,
but, uh, um,
I mostly gave those guys
the heads up about where--
where everything is right now, yeah.
Uh, it's a story
about a boy and a girl,
and they both have two different
parallel stories going on,
and the player can jump back
and forth between them.
And the girl is,
um, a young girl
who's been chosen for this big honor
that she finds out is actually being sacrificed
to a horrible monster
in order to save her town.
And her story is about
choosing to break out
of that arrangement
and endanger her town
and hopefully fight the monster
and save her town.
And then the boy is a, um--
has grown up alone on a spaceship,
a giant,
kind of organic spaceship
that takes care of his every needs
and creates entertainment for him
and takes care of his food
and his health and everything,
but he's all by himself
out in space.
And it's about him
actually finding out, um,
how to take control of that ship
and get access to
new secret areas
and find out that he has
the ability to actually, uh,
have a higher purpose
than just hanging out
in this ship being entertained,
but he can actually
go on rescue missions
and save helpless creatures
around the galaxy.
Chan: Like all the other
adventure games,
I think he had more landmarks
already established.
More tent poles, right?
And, um, and then my job
was to connect between them.
And this time around,
yeah, there's less tent poles,
and so it's our job to go in
and try to figure out
what the other places
are right now.
Basically, all we're doing
is giving him
enough of inspiration for him
to run with it.
Once he sees an image
and his imagination starts,
you know, uh, walking around
in our drawings,
he can then start
to expand on that.
That's how it
always works with Tim.
Petty: On a creative
direction standpoint, you know,
Tim--I think Tim fishes a lot, you know?
And, um, he kind of
gets these elements
and then he makes unusual
but cohesive connections
between those elements,
you know?
And I think that this will help
that process for him.
Other people maybe have-- have in
mind a very specific mythology,
and I think Tim's different
in different games.
Like, I think "Brütal Legend,"
you know, he had a very, like,
"It's a roadie in this
heavy metal fantasy world,
and it's based on the look
of album covers,"
and Frazetta--some
of the very early stuff.
A little more--a little more
specific than some of this,
but I think in the end, he just
takes different ways to get there
depending on what he feels
the game needs
or what the theme of the game
is really about.
Schafer: But, um, it's still
in the phase where just,
like, everything is like, "Yes, and that
could be cool and this could be cool
and this could be cool," and just like,
coming up with tons of art.
That's my goal.
All right?
Petty: There's these big gaps
in the first two acts past the intro,
and that's where I think
we can help Tim the most.
[Music]
Schafer: It is--I'm joking,
but it is like a dream team.
I mean, these are the best artists I know,
and they're all here together.
[Music]
Cambell: Man, these
are a little dry, dude.
Chan: Who makes this?
Petty: Copic.
These are Japanese markers
and they're the best, because first,
they got a square shape so
they don't roll on your table.
Right, and they got nice--
nice medium-sized tip,
a very nice chisel tip.
And they--and they
really can lay it down,
so all you do to refill it is you
just pull this sucker off like that.
And you can buy just
tip replacements, too.
-Yeah.
-Oh yeah.
It's like, uh, I met some--
I met Chris.
Cambell: Like a steak--it's like a meat--
it's like a bacon steak root.
-Very nice.
-One down.
Bagel: Yam.
-Who else?
Chan: So she starts exploring.
When she reaches, like, pathways
which are made of twigs, all right?
Schafer: Mm-hm.
Chan: So there are some paths.
Once she's on it,
she won't sink anymore,
so that--that automatically
guides her through.
Schafer: Textural.
Chan: Now--awesome.
Petty: When he wasn't looking,
or when they needed to operate the ship,
they started to like fold back,
and they have all these like,
um, like A.M. clock radio innards,
and the arms come out
and they start doing stuff
and he turns around and they're
like back as a little bunny.
Cambell: So, like, these people
would be cruisin' around
on like combs and brushes, dude,
and they'd be combing the land like farming.
So it'd be like farming style, but
they'd be farming the trees and shit.
Schafer: Are they pulling out lice
to eat or anything?
Cambell: No, it'd just be really pretty.
That's the thing, they can be farming,
harvesting all the bugs and shit,
and then they could put it
in their little harvester,
but also making really
cool shapes from the stuff
that they create like that,
you know what I mean?
Chan: So, that's what we've got.
Bagel: Yeah, I think we're getting closer to--
I think we're just trying to figure out
like a language because-- since
these things are gonna be 2D painting,
I think we really
just have to figure out
the language of both worlds.
And I think we're like getting...
I think all these drawings,
once we put them all up tomorrow
and see what Tim says,
it'll even be just that next
level of direction, you know?
Cambell: But he just gets worried
when you throw away your drawings.
I don't know if you saw that today,
but we had some--some run-ins
with some of the artists
throwing away their work
'cause they don't think
it's good enough.
Schafer: Don't let me bother you,
I'm just looking at what you're drawing.
Those are pretty.
Where'd that squid go?
Bagel: Squid?
Petty: You were
painting a squid earlier.
Bagel: Oh yeah, I threw it out,
I threw it away.
Schafer: You threw it out?
Petty: Oh!
Schafer: You son of a--
Petty: We all liked it.
Cambell: Why'd you
throw that away, dude?
Bagel: Son of a monkey.
Which one?
Petty: Get a whole sheet.
Schafer: Oh my God, and you tore it in half?
Bagel: I can make another one.
Bagel: We'll make another one.
Cambell: Dude, that whole fuckin' page.
Bagel: You guys liked it?
Schafer: Yeah, we paid for that,
we paid for that.
You pretty much just stole from
the backers by tearing that up.
Bagel: Yeah.
Cambell: Why'd you rip that up?
-You crazy, man?
Bagel: I know.
Cambell: That was the best shit, man.
Bagel: Now, uh--
I didn't think
it was that great.
Yeah, he picked it out
of the trash, my drawing.
And then he told me
to do it over again.
Cambell: He'll probably Frankenstein
that one and that'll be the...
Bagel: Oh, speak of the devil.
Cambell: ...the biggest idea.
Schafer: You guys
talking about something?
That's cool.
Weird porcupine guys.
Bagel: It's like moving, uh, on land.
Schafer: That's awesome.
Chan: I have a lot of faith in Tim,
and all we have to do
is plant a few seeds
and he'll start running with it, right?
Cambell: Yeah, planting seeds.
Yeah, you don't know what seeds
will turn into rad stuff, man.
[Music]
Cambell: So it's just a list of possible room
ideas and experiences, you know?
Just kind of--like,
some of them are just words.
They may make us think about
some interesting things, you know?
Like wild jungle.
It's fun for people.
A sunny beach, candy room,
garden zone for, like,
the tender side of boys.
[Laughing]
Maybe those seeds
will grow into amazing things
and then we'll realize that those
amazing things are actually terrible.
So we'll just cover them up with a sheet
and then move on to the next thing.
Who knows?
You know, fireball, soccer,
playin' with fireballs are
really fun, probably, for boys.
Laser zone--anything
can be made into lasers,
so you can eat sandwiches of lasers,
you could just shoot 'em,
ride 'em, dodge 'em. You know.
I'll just do drawings
and try to get people pumped.
It's my--That'll be my role.
So this is like, just,
could be waterfalls
and different things of goop,
and it could be falling down,
or this could be barf, you know?
And it could be like animal,
or, you know, creatures
made of barf kind of unhappy
or happy, you know?
Like, and they can be
barfing new creatures.
It could just be barf zone,
you know what I mean?
Schafer: Was there a period in your life
where you had a barf thing?
Cambell: People love barf, dude.
Schafer: Oh, no, they don't.
Cambell: At this point, everything
is disposable and stuff, so.
That's the thing
about creative processes, like,
you wanna go down
every road fully
to realize that road is wrong.
You can't just go down a
little bit and be, "Ooh, uh..."
You gotta really
test that water fully
before you can realize
that's a terrible road.
And then you go down
the next road.
Rice: This is a list of locations
from our backers on the forums.
Petty: You know, some of the stuff,
we're just incorporating backer--
uh, backer ideas,
which was cool.
You know, but they don't really know
anything about the story,
which is kind of
cool at this phase, right,
that they don't really have to,
that maybe some of those things
will wind up working in ways.
Rice: I went through
the first ten pages so far.
Schafer: Oh my God,
how many pages are there?
Rice: I know, there's 38
or something like that.
Um, we're still in girl world.
Sand castle world?
That's a new one.
Bagel: Sand castles.
Rice: Sand castle world.
Boy world.
A haunted lighthouse
on the moon.
Schafer: What?
Bagel: I didn't see that moon comin'.
Rice: Um, this dude says,
"Inside of a computer."
This dude says, "An entire city
made of blanket forts."
That was something.
Cambell: Yeah.
Rice: MS-DOS world, where
everything's made from words.
Schafer: That's a text adventure,
that's called a text adventure.
Rice: "It is a place where you play
connect-the-dots to build the location."
Cambell: Fuckin' creative people, dude.
Rice: Yeah.
Cambell: It's okay if we use that shit?
I mean, dude, we're gonna get...
Schafer: Yeah.
Cambell: ...sued.
Seriously, man, fuck, like, I'm
so excited to see these lists.
I feel like--I feel like
it's cheating, kind of.
Bagel: It's like, uh, they're stoked.
Like, if somebody gets their idea made,
like, that'd be awesome.
Cambell: And there's all these sequels based
on that one idea that someone said,
then they're gonna start being like, "Hm,
maybe I should have held onto that idea."
Schafer: The hair trees,
wanna mention that.
I love all these guys and that
whole story, like, whatever--
I don't even know
what it is yet, but like,
the idea of going into this, like, grass-covered
thing that comes to life.
And this behavior is
really cool, it's just like,
there's something
lazy about it that I like.
Cambell: We've just been trying to get
as much stuff as we can.
All right, with the big--I just think it's
a round hunchback of forest right here.
Schafer: It's kind of like those, uh, you know,
those places in New Mexico or...
Cambell: We're not getting too into the
mechanics of how the ship creates things
or how the monster land looks
or how the city looks,
but just kind of overall things
that might spark stuff for him right now.
So we'll just do more
of that tomorrow.
[Music]
Chan: I just, uh, did a lot
of drawing on my own,
you know, self-taught.
I would draw--when I was little,
I would draw on paper,
and then,
if I didn't like something,
I would crumple it up
and throw it away.
And I remember my father
said to me, um, "Now, if you--
if you just slide your drawings
into the garbage can,
and without crumpling it--
without crumpling it up,
you would fit more drawings
in the, um, garbage bin,"
not knowing that he was
going through it later, um,
and pulling out the ones he liked,
because, um, after he passed away,
I found a folder
that was labeled, uh, "Peter,"
and I found my old
Star Wars drawings.
Uh, if he didn't do that,
I wouldn't have any drawings,
because I don't--
I don't really keep my--my stuff around.
[Music]
As you can see, uh,
I tucked in the woods here,
and this is where I get
my inspiration, is, uh, nature.
Um, so, as you know, uh,
you're on San Juan Island,
and, uh, this is my little studio
away from my home,
and this is where I create, uh,
drawings for games and films.
I'm, uh, in here
eight hours a day,
and what's nice is on
a beautiful day like today,
I--I, uh, I like to draw
outside when I can.
When I'm having
a creative block,
that's the time to go out,
you know, go on walks and hikes,
and that's important
to be creative, too.
I need to create that space
to think.
I love it, can't go back.
This fits and feels really,
really good for my creative self
and for my emotional self
and everything else.
It's really good.
"Grim" actually
was my last adventure game,
and it was the--
and it was done here on the island.
It was my first job
away from Lucas.
This was my goin' away present,
uh, from Lucas, as you can see.
Never forget where you started,
where you come from,
and that's something
really important to me.
'Cause that's why, um, I have, like,
some Star Wars stuff in here.
It's important that I have
a few of those things around
because that's what inspired me.
That's what got me started.
That's why this piece here,
by Ralph McQuarrie,
is so important to me,
'Cause he's the man that, um,
inspired me to do
what I'm doing now.
When I was ten, I didn't know
that there was such thing as,
a, you know, concept designer,
someone that actually
designs something
for you to live in
for those couple hours,
if it was a movie, or--or now,
hours playing video games.
I mean, it's a--an opportunity to escape
and live in that world.
This is where I draw, mostly.
I do everything standing up,
and I still draw on paper,
as you can see.
Down here is, uh,
all the bad ideas right here.
See, these are the workups.
From this came this one,
where it's--
as you can see, is a total mess,
and, uh, I try to come up with, uh, some funny ideas,
and then from there,
becomes this one up here.
And then eventually, I use
all those drawings, um,
to start my fire in the morning.
It's a good lesson
on letting go.
[Music]
I'm gonna show you guys something.
These are my family photo albums
of when Tim and Pete Tscale
came to visit,
and, uh, used to do work jams
on the island with me
at the, uh, farmhouse.
That's, uh, me in my
upstairs loft studio out of--
in the farmhouse.
And those are all the storyboards
for "Grim Fandango."
And here's me drawing.
I don't remember, but Tim swears
that I was drawing so fast
I was shooting
the little ball tips out.
Is he gonna kill me?
I gotta show you this.
I'm not gonna show you
the second one,
'cause I know he'll kill me
for sure,
but I'm gonna give you this one
because he looks so good in it.
Tim chopping wood.
And I'm not gonna show you
the second one.
That's a before,
and then this one's after.
"Grim" is my favorite,
um, adventure game
that I've ever worked on.
But who knows, this could be
the next favorite game.
When I start a project,
I start collecting my books.
It's important to go
and do your research,
do it the old-fashioned way first.
And I learn more by going to
the library and reading up on it
instead of just looking
for a pretty picture off the internet.
And so for us to create
our own village,
I think it's important
that we, um,
try to find that happy balance
between what we're familiar
with as fairytale--
the signature shape
is, like, mushrooms,
for, like, Alice in Wonderland--
and you balance it
with something foreign,
something that
we're not familiar with.
In Japanese architecture,
you can kind of see
there's mushrooms in it
without even thinking about it.
There are these great mushroom shapes
that are happening,
and so I thought
I'd mix that up with,
um, Scandinavian,
like country homes,
and that brings in some
of the really cute stuff
that's happening, see,
with the thatched roofing.
Here you can kind of see
that my wood-burning stove
that I put
in the background here
looks like
one of these lanterns.
It has, like, the mushroom top.
And so, I'm just figuring
that out right now,
and then eventually have to pitch this
to, um, Tim and Lee,
and hopefully sell them
the ideas that I have.
Um, yeah, I can't wait.
And then what's nice, though,
is that I'm able to shut that door
at the end of the day and walk
across the lawn and go home,
and I leave, uh,
this game in the studio
and it doesn't follow me--
follow me home,
because my life at home
is important.
And, uh, and actually, you know,
we should get out of here
and spend some time outside.
That's where some
of the better ideas come from.
[Music]
Cambell: My name's Scott Campbell and
I live here in New York City.
We are in my apartment,
which also is my studio.
I'm an illustrator
and I've worked at Double Fine, uh--
I think I was employee
number six in 2001,
and I was art director
on "Psychonauts"
and "Brütal Legend."
Production designer for "Brütal Legend,"
my official title.
When I was working
at the studio, like,
I liked to go into his office
and just kind of show him,
like, uh, the paintings
and drawings and stuff,
and I would be able
to gauge from his--
his reaction
whether or not it was good.
That's what I miss
living here in New York.
One thing I know
that Tim likes, though--
he likes drawings
when they're in cool poses.
Even if the designs aren't
very good, he just likes poses.
So if there's a dude that
I really like the design of,
I'll put him in the coolest pose
and hope that he digs it.
It was one of my
favorite poses is putting his--
putting your feet up
on something.
Always sell Tim on this pose.
I haven't talked to Tim
since the very beginning,
so I don't know how
it's evolved, you know?
Just when Tim first pitched
the game to Bagel and I,
he came here to New York.
We had some, uh,
some sangria and some tacos
and we talked about it
and he gave us the pitch.
And so after that,
you know, Bagel--Bagel and I
just kind of started
just gathering our friends
and just trying out drawing
the main two characters
and some basic
environment ideas.
Pre-production is like
when you get started
and you start dream--
dream the dreams, you know?
It can be anything you want and stuff,
and you're just kind of gathering inspiration.
Gathering reference is like--
it's like my favorite part,
so I'm constantly taking
stuff from the internet,
like gathering images and stuff.
It's just like if ever I hit--
if ever I see something cool,
I'll just kind of take it
and put it in a folder for later.
Just like kind of the effects
or the colors,
I don't know what it would inspire,
but it just makes me feel pretty good.
I just think
that's an odd scene.
This is a nice soft picture of a lady
that makes me feel pretty good.
I don't know what these
are gonna inspire at all, you guys.
I--I do all the drawings
like kind of this
just on pieces of paper
like this.
I just draw on Xerox paper
and stuff, and I, like,
I just scan 'em in
and kind of make 'em
look better later,
pretty much, so.
It's easy for me to kind of
like chill out in the morning
in a café and do drawings like that,
and then kind of like
worry about, you know,
just so I could kind of--
any way that I kind of relax
and kind of loosen up
and stuff like that,
and I find that if I'm not near
a computer, I'm most relaxed.
This is my little drawing zone.
See, I print out a lot of my--
a lot of my reference
and kind of mood boards.
So I have this up and I'm
constantly kind of changing it out.
You know, update it, and with new things,
make me feel different ways, so.
So here are some paintings.
So I painted these girls from--
these are from the game,
and so I just print out--
print them out,
and then just kind of trace 'em
onto the paper,
and then start--start
water coloring like that.
This could be the girl,
you guys.
This could be the--
this could be the--the drawing.
So let's see what
happens together, shall we?
I'm gonna give her
this little dress here.
I'm not exactly sure
what that's made of.
Noodle arms. Well, it doesn't
really look like noodle arms.
Okay, there she is.
That's one version.
Maybe she has a little buddy,
her magical buddy.
We'll see.
There you go.
This is, uh, concept art.
That's--that's how it works.
That's how magic works.
Oh, here's a painting that Bagel did
of Obama a long time ago.
Bagel and I
are really tight bros.
I moved here,
um, about four years ago,
and he moved here
like a month after.
He stayed with our other friend,
and then he would just work out of my house
'cause we were still workin'
for Double Fine out of my house.
And then he just was always over here,
so he just found a place over here.
Yeah, he's super close.
I mean, we can just
walk there right now even.
[Offscreen] Okay, and
then we cut to us over there.
Okay, cool.
Cambell: That's his window up there.
Bagel!
Hey, bro.
Bagel: Hey, buddy!
It's a little tight,
sorry, guys.
I was gonna try to clean
all this stuff up, but I didn't.
Cambell: That's okay, man.
Bagel: This is my bedroom here
and my studio where I paint
and where I sleep.
There's my bed,
there's my bathroom.
It's pretty amazing.
Um, it's clean.
And this is my kitchen.
This is my view, the projects.
And this is like
this butcher paper that I had
that I imagined I was gonna,
like, draw all over,
but that's about as far
as I've gotten.
But if I ever want to draw
on the wall, I could do it.
Painting, I do it--I usually
just stick a canvas on the wall.
You could see, like,
all these paint marks
like underneath that map.
I just like tack up a canvas on the wall
and start paintin' on it, usually.
Yeah, no easel.
So I'm just in the
sketching phase kind of now,
and I do that all right here
on the computer.
I have, like, one show a year
that's kind of like my sketch.
I just work--do work stuff
and then have, like, a solo show.
That's the--how it's been goin'
the last, like, three years,
so I just have like one big show
to worry about a year.
Some stuff I had in the show last year.
18 Dads, it's a bunch of dads.
This is just random pieces of paper.
This is like how I
organize myself, I guess.
These are just studies,
like color studies, like N.C. Wyeth
and, uh, that's the
illustrator that I like.
Just weird doodles.
First kind of color sketch
of that thing, yeah.
Tim hadn't even really talked
about the idea that he had yet.
I would just kind of throw
things at him every week,
and sometimes he would say
that he liked little things
or he would just grab
onto something
and then I would take it,
or, you know,
just kind of push things
or try other things out.
And so, um, I worked out
this kind of story
about this weird lumberjack
and a bear.
Like he washes up
on this mysterious island,
and it's like a magical island
in some huge lake
in the Pacific Northwest.
This is kind of where
the prototype started.
Yeah, I had an idea
that this, like, caveman
got unfrozen with this dinosaur
and they ended up, like,
in the--what was it,
like, Virginia?
The mountains of Virginia
and stuff?
And it--it was gonna be all like,
uh, bluegrass soundtrack,
fish-out-of-water style,
and then they would, like,
all play music together
or something,
but I don't think
that's gonna happen.
This is where that
lumberjack dude is right now.
He's gonna be a puppet,
so we're, like,
separating all of his limbs.
I gotta cut him all up.
You know, break him up into kind of joints,
but really simple puppet-style, so, you know,
at the knees, at the elbows,
and puppetize him
for Ray to start
animating this week.
You know, in between
these rotating poses,
he can, you know,
supposedly make him look
like he's going back and forth.
So I gotta like paint
what's gonna be behind the arms,
but he's gonna move it around,
so you gotta see what's behind here.
Uh, this game is gonna be
so totally different and new,
so who knows, you know?
It's gonna be exciting
when we start getting into like,
uh, the real deal.
I'm lookin' forward to that,
it's gonna be awesome.
Schafer: I've always loved
Bagel's paintings.
He's, um, when he does his
fine art shows and galleries,
he does these crazy works
that are somewhat surreal,
you know, playing with scale
and playing with a mix of cartoony and, like, realism.
He can do realistic stuff really well,
mixes it with cartoony stuff
and otherworldly type landscapes,
and I think--I wanna do a whole game
that'll look like those landscapes
and with those strange characters.
Bagel: Check it out.
Franzke: It takes a while to actually
be responsive, for some reason.
Bagel: No way!
Man, that looks so cool on the iPad.
Rice: Isn't that awesome?
Schafer: Did you see that?
Bagel: Is it like a touch and then
he walks toward your finger?
Rice: Just touch down.
You have to be
in the foreground.
Schafer: We can't go in the back
with all the layers yet?
Oliver: Not right now, not this version.
Rice: But you can walk around.
Bagel: It's insane.
Schafer: It makes me so happy
'cause it's on an iPad and it looks pretty.
In the end, all the art will go through Nathan,
as he paints the final stuff.
So it's all gonna look like his style,
so it'll all be unified.
You're just gonna see his take
on the other artists' ideas and drawings.
This'll be more than any
game we've done before,
like, uh, in the end, you know,
a game where Bagel
really gets to shine.
Bagel: Yeah, I mean, I guess, I mean, and
theoretically, he should be darker, like, you know?
I think he's too light right now.
Like, he should blend--the colors, I think,
should blend more with the environment.
But, um, that's--that--
it's just not in yet.
It's, uh...
Lee's gonna do some
effects and aftereffects,
I think, that lights
the character's texture,
so he would be a lot more blue
and dark in this one.
Nice.
Killer.
I feel pretty awesome
about it, I think.
I feel great about everything.
Uh, yeah, I think--it's--I'm,
like, interested to see
how it's gonna go, you know?
Like I hope those guys don't
hate my paintings of their paintings.
You know, it's awesome
'cause they're just gonna be
in a sweet painting world.
Like, that's--
that gets me pumped
that people are gonna be able to, like,
explore my paintings, you know?
Rice: That's hilarious.
Bagel: That's amazing, though, dude.
Rice: Oh, man, that's super good.
Crook: So I'm actually scaling the arms a little bit
so that it feels like they go--
Yeah, they get a little bit
of perspective.
And the feet.
Rice: Yeah.
Bagel: That totally, uh,
that totally works.
Petty: It's weird, it's a hybrid process
'cause it's like you're doing a 2D painting,
but then we do have to get it
on a 3D geometry,
so it has some
of the cleanup work
as if it were a real 3D--
like a full 3D model.
Bagel: It depends on how complicated we're gonna get
with all the parallaxing and, you know,
I have never had to
worry about memory issues
in painting and restrictions, you know,
technical restrictions or
anything like that, so, yeah,
I mean, it's really, like, gonna
be a crazy learning process
at the same time, you know?
Yeah, putting it all together and makin' it
into a working, functional, moving world is, like,
I haven't really done that before,
so this is a whole--a whole new world.
If I were to say, like, "Ah, here's this--
here's, like, him the most lit he's gonna be."
Uh, you know, "Here's
him dark as he's gonna be,"
and then, like, you're--okay--
Petty: But I think it solves
a different problem, right?
We're talking about-- like, I think the general
color gradients, I think, look good.
I think the rim lighting
is a different thing.
That's not about lighting
as much as it is, like,
when there's an intense
light source around.
It's about just putting a little bit on there
to, like, tie him into the scene.
I think, I mean, you read the comments at the forum,
and like everyone found it very appealing.
It really helped the tie-in.
Bagel: Yeah?
Schafer: Yeah, Bagel is not, um,
really, you know, technical.
He likes to paint.
He likes to paint on, you know,
canvas and paper, and, uh, um,
and that's why it's really invaluable to have someone
like Lee Petty on the team who can bridge that gap.
He's a fine artist himself,
he can draw, he can paint,
but he also knows how to use,
um, incredibly advanced,
you know, techniques
and 3D rendering, and, you know,
just making games that, you know,
a lot of programmers, you know,
he can match programmers sometimes
with the knowledge of, um...
He's got a lot of knowledge.
That's what I'm trying to say.
So it's great to have someone like Lee
around who can bridge that gap.
Petty: That's why I was saying earlier,
don't paint the character dark
because you can never get lighter.
We want to generally paint him pretty light
like this 'cause then he can get darker.
Schafer: If you can span
both worlds, it's really essential,
'cause you can work with a great artist,
but then if that doesn't really translate into the game,
you can be, um,
it's just a waste.
Chan: Yeah, I'm--I'm curious
as much as you are,
and I have faith
that it'll work.
I mean, Tim--see, that's
the thing is like, Tim says,
"This is what I--I want to
showcase Bagel's style."
Perfect.
I think that's a great idea.
And so I trust him.
If that's what he wants, then--
then there's something there.
Bagel: Ooh!
Petty: All right, Ray.
Crook: Go back to your jam.
Petty: All right.
Bagel: Jam out.
Crook: All right, guys.
[Music]
Schafer: You know, very early on,
I sometimes have
these stress nightmares
about the game not existing yet.
I used to have
these nightmares about levels
in "Psychonauts" that didn't exist yet,
and like, I was floating in the undesigned world
and couldn't grab
onto anything.
It's just like,
it's the stress of things
that you haven't
really pulled together yet.
And these are like little
life preservers and the--
floating in the ocean,
like, you grab onto them like,
"Ah, ah, now I can breathe
and, like, look around
and see what else I can pull together
to make a raft out of," you know?
That's a metaphor.
I like how it's like lighthouse
with the haunted house on top of it.
Petty: Yeah, it's basic--
Chan: I can go home now?
Schafer: What?
Petty: Peter Chan.
Bagel: Thank you.
Schafer: Peter Chan, yeah, Peter Chan.
Oh, Bagel's posting!
Bagel, Bagel.
Chan: Bagel!
Bagel: Yeah.
Chan: Yeah.
Bagel: Jump in there.
Schafer: Bagel.
Okay.
Bagel: Floating island maybe that--
Schafer: What's on the floating island?
What are all these guys
jumping off?
Penguins?
Bagel: Maybe they're loomin' outside the bushes.
Cambell: You should scan those in.
Schafer: Crazy imagination.
Bagel: Yep, crazy imagination.
Schafer: Bradbury early folklore--
Mars folklore.
Ooh, I like Mars folklore.
Bagel: Mars folklore.
Yeah, okay, bros,
I'm out of here.
Schafer: Aw!
Cambell: What?
Schafer: Aw, why?
Thank you for comin'.
Cambell: See you, buddy.
Bagel: All right.
Bye, bros.
-All right, buddies.
[Offscreen] Bye, Bagel!
Chan: Well, I came over
to say goodbye.
Schafer: Next time, we come up to you.
Chan: Yeah.
Schafer: It's gonna be awesome.
Oh, Jesus.
Chan: I know.
[Laughter]
[Music]
Schafer: These are just some, uh, see,
Scott is doing some
crazy people, which I like.
And Lee did some crazy monsters,
which I love those, too.
This guy's too young,
that's wrong.
I love that one.
Those are freaking me out.
Um, I don't know what that is.
The Jedi robe.
I don't know
about the Jedi robe.
Some monsters.
That is a really scary monster.
I think his little--ugh--
little things up front.
And Bagel did this one
and it's like a mountain
that looks like a wig.
It's like wig mountain.
And that's like a ship, I think.
And these are waves floating.
Little mushroom guy,
which I love.
I love these paintings.
They're so tiny.
Sacrificial altars.
Here's another vision
of the girl's village,
really happy and
cheerful looking, which I like.
This is crazy.
It's like a, um...
I don't know what that is.
God's eye,
we just had that idea today.
That one's gonna work, I think.
This is such a great stage
in the project
'cause everything's been,
like, in my head
and the people's heads
and in my notebook,
and now it's just exploded out
on the wall for everyone to see.
Everyone.
[Music]