[Music]
Petty: So I can double-check
that he put everything up.
The rest of them, I'm going to scan them
all, yeah, so we can have them.
We have a, you know,
our concept art directory.
You know, in theory if all the puzzles were
done and the things were decided on,
we could actually make a pretty functional
game with really rough art early on
to sort of unblock the puzzle
design or implementation.
And some of the systems
work, which would be nice.
I'm not sure.
I'm a big fan of working that way,
but I'm not sure if we'll be able
to do it for this project or not.
We'll have to see how that works out.
[Music]
Rice: Yep.
If you're always showing this board,
won't they get spoilers from the board?
So just to bring us up to date, I need
another location for the cloud nest.
Things that came up from the art jam.
Cloud nests.
Rice: You can tell that
that's going to look awesome.
Schafer: The first thing
Peter mentioned, too.
Rice: Yeah, I think he
drew that the first day.
Schafer: And then the other
one is the dead-eye pyramid.
Rice: Why is it dead-eye?
Schafer: Spoiler. Can't tell you.
Rice: I have to play
the game to find out?
Schafer: These things all still work
but maybe this becomes his story.
The monster lands move over here.
Maybe that moves over there.
Rice: What I still am not clear on is,
and I don't know if you are,
is switching back and
forth between these stories
and how we're going to handle that.
Schafer: Yeah.
I'm putting that off.
Rice: Yeah. Start thinking about it.
So I'm just wondering then,
like if I'm here, here and here
and I jump back to this,
then what's the world like?
Like why can't I do this and what happens
that makes me so I can do this?
Schafer: I don't know. I don't know yet.
Schafer: I've been a little behind.
It's frustrating because I, when
the team is waiting for you,
that's always frustrating, so.
It's always been that way.
Like having an absolutely terrifying
deadline is the only thing that,
makes me get it done.
There's just so many other things
going on with the company right now that,
you know, The Cave is getting to this
point where it needs, you know,
it has a dialogue deadline of its own.
You know, and do I help with that
or do I work on this game?
Suck it!
[Monster Roar]
Schafer: Peter McConnell's here today.
It's fun to see what
he's going to add to it.
Schafer: So the game.
You see, we did some art already.
We had art jam with Peter Chan and
Scott Campbell and Nathan came to town
and hung out with Lee, and did some art.
And that's cool.
And that corkboard
is kind of up-to-date.
I could add some as we talk, but we're
doing a point and click graphic adventure.
I don't know if you heard that.
McConnell: Very cool.
Schafer: So it doesn't have a
high concept in terms of like
a heavy metal fantasy world
or the Day of the Dead.
It's really like a new world that we're
making up based on Nathan Stapley's art.
You know, just having that cool look
and having it be about themes
that are different, maybe
than other themes.
McConnell: Yeah. I've got questions.
Schafer: There'll be no
questions during this meeting.
Schafer: Is Peter McConnell
excited to be on the project?
You're asking me if he's excited?
I think so.
We always enjoyed working together.
You know, he's worked on
everything I've done since
Day of the Tentacle,
Monkey II, Monkey II.
Offscreen Voice: He's
like your Danny Elfman.
Schafer: He's what?
Offscreen Voice: He's
like your Danny Elfman.
Schafer: He's like my Danny Elfman.
He can do Danny Elfman
if you ask him to.
McConnell: I'm just thinking
about instruments, you know.
I'm thinking about styles
and I'm probably going to
have to think quite a bit about it,
because it's, I mean, I have some things
that are popping into my head.
I don't know if they're probably way
jumping the gun at this point.
But what comes to mind about, about
a world where things are being made for you
and it's like a playroom a
little bit, is a music box.
And you know, a little bit like
Mr. Roger's Neighborhood, which…
Schafer: It also has that
repetitive quality to it.
Because the game is
going to start in this like,
his routine is the same every day,
even though it's drastically different.
It's really like he wakes up,
the robots dress him.
You know, the arms just come out of
nowhere and make him dinner, food.
And then when he busts out and he's
doing actual 90's, 80's creepy space adventure.
Or 2001 like.
McConnell: Yeah. Schafer: Yeah.
McConnell: Then 2001 would be,
2001 will be hard to do, you know,
without a great big orchestra.
And I don't think we have that.
But I don't think, you know.
Schafer: And now it's
like a little more like now
we're running our own actual budget.
Schafer: It's like we have a certain
amount of money in the budget for Peter,
which means a certain amount of time.
And we have to like wait
until we're ready for him
to be really effective in working.
So we've got to be at a point
where we can just tell him,
here's a list of characters
that need themes.
Here's a list of areas, 'cause he's
got to spread out his time
so he doesn't just score the first two
acts and then run out of time.
So he's got to like spread it
out, look at the whole game,
think about the game play.
Then think about how much of
that money he should save
to pay for things like live musicians.
Studio time.
McConnell: Yeah, I think there is going to
have to be a signature piece, for sure.
And that is, or you know, or two
halves of the signature piece
because you got these two worlds.
Min: Yeah, yeah, that, too.
Rice: It'll be interesting to see
how we can handle that.
You know, like if there're themes that
persist in both their worlds or you know,
funny little things to do
to connect their two.
Min: I think that Pete's going to
be able to knock that out pretty easily.
I think it's more the initial, but then it's
the same thing with Tim, you know,
I mean you go crazy for two days
and then on the third day you just
kind of come up with something.
You know, that's how
creative magic happens.
I mean, and I think it's
almost like you have
to be patient with
yourself and not, not panic.
McConnell: You know, that backer
money don't last forever.
Rice: That's the truth.
Music
Lumberjack: That's not a word, is it?
Tree: No. We're done here.
Kipnis: Yes!
Schafer: Awesome. Done. Rice: Yeah.
For the last four months we've
spent in preproduction mode
and it's been kind of exploratory phase of
trying to figure out what the game is
and both in terms of design,
but also in how we're going
to actually make that happen.
But yeah, everyone's kind of had
their own separate little tasks
and those are all starting
to converge now to where
we're ready to start actually
building a puzzle in the engine.
Crook: Actual production
work is awesome.
Like we're going to go,
this could get shipped.
Like this work.
Schafer: We'll see how it turns out.
Crook: Yeah, we'll see.
Rice: Ray Crook, Double Fine animator.
Yeah, Ray started on the project and he's
been someone who's been at the company
since like essentially the beginning.
Crook: I was excited to
work with Tim again,
because Brutal Legend
was the last game that,
you know, we'd worked
closely together on.
And so I was most excited
just to work with him.
But you know, I knew
there would be cameras.
Crook: So I'm actually
excited to be starting on that.
Crook: You know, the beginning of
preproduction is really exciting
and then it seems like
eventually it gets kind of like,
you're just kind of churning.
You know, I guess just, let's
just get this show on the road,
you know, is sort of
the way that it feels.
And that's where we are.
Schafer: Awesome. Bye.
Crook: Tim has picked a puzzle,
which we're calling First Playable.
Petty: So these are some of
the stuff Peter gave me on Friday, right?
And so I think this is the stuff we
talked about when he was here,
which is the idea of them having
this little sacrificial island, which is awesome.
Cakes, in a U.  But I was
still worried about like
if you put this into game
camera mode, game layout mode,
that'd be kind of blocked up.
And I did this real rough thing.
I just got Peter's revision, right.
And so this was the idea like from
a game camera you would be,
you would kind of start here.
So we could start with a pan and
we kind of move up and we kind of…
Rice: But yeah, it's the scene
where the main character,
I mean main female character is being
offered up for sacrifice to a monster.
Schafer: Could it show up
just behind the princess?
You just see something like feet?
Like what the fuck is it!?  Petty: Yeah.
Schafer: You can't see it all, then it
comes between, like oh my God!
And it's gone.
You just never see it up close until it gets,
comes in here and like eats that one.
Rice: Yeah, it's going to be
a lot of work, for sure,
because it's just a lot of
animation and cut scenes.
So it's going to be a tough one.
Stapley: So you're saying
for the end of this sprint
we're really going to try to get the,
get the sacrifice feast all set up?
'Cause that's the thing, like if every
puzzle's going to have like say
five or so new characters, that's
like, kind of a lot of time.
Petty: Well, and that's exactly why
we want to take this to finals,
because it's just conjecture
until we kind of get an area to
really know exactly how long.
I made estimates based on our progress.
Petty: Like there's always this period
that when you start any game
where you're trying to,
you're trying to build it,
you're trying to build something both
at like artistically you're like yeah,
it's the right mood, that's the right
game play, that's the right look.
But you're also trying to build
something to get an idea of
how long it takes you to
build the rest of the game.
And part of that is you need,
you need enough information
about the rest of the game,
like you know, there's always this
theoretical ideal that you never get.
Like the whole game is written,
every puzzle's designed,
you know, all the art
direction's completely done.
I've never in my whatever years
I've worked in the game industry,
ever seen that happen.
Some projects are closer
to that than others.
So there's a lot of
uncertainty at that point.
Stapley: Yeah, sounds good and scary.
Schafer: Bagel, why you so scared?
Stapley: I think because I haven't seen
anything like in the game yet, you know.
Like it's still the lumberjack dude.
I'd just love to see how easy
it's going to be reshape things
and put things in and take things out
and change things and add things.
Petty: What you really have to do,
I think, is lay the best foundation you can.
Be mindful of what you're making and then
just be clever as you're making the game.
Look for opportunities to save
time or to reuse things
or to go in new directions that
are just more efficient
or take some of the lessons you've
learned from the earlier areas
and adapt your later areas to it.
So, that's, and that's,
that's what I try and do
and I think most people on the
team try to do it in any game.
[Music]
Offscreen Voice: She wants
to be skinny, right?
And look skinny.
So maybe it's something that helps
her look slimmer sometime?
Schafer: Corset. Offscreen Voice: Yeah.
Schafer: But you put
corset on the buzzard.
Oh, wait. That could be awesome.
Offscreen Voice: That
could be totally awesome.
Schafer: So strange. A corset buzzard
with a drumstick in his arm.
This is where I
start getting interested.
Schafer: Like I haven't seen like the
maiden feast thing all wired up yet,
but that is in the game, I hear.
Have you seen that?
I've been out of it in meetings.
Things are happening so fast.
Petty: You know what did
so far in it, is you know,
we had this sort of layout
drawing that we did.
And we took those layout
drawings and cut them up.
And you can sort of see things
exist in the tool here in parallax.
We don't have the game camera
authored or anything, like you know,
you could rough in the game play
right now if you wanted to.
This isn't the, a real monster design.
That's not a real bird design.
Those aren't real character designs,
but they are, you know,
they have the underlying
script components to them.
And so, you know, once those,
you can sort of see here this is just,
if we run the game at
this scene at the moment
we don't actually have a main character.
So you know, one could hookup
dialogue and have proxy object
dragging and all that sort of stuff.
So that's the biggest thing I want to
do with it, was put enough of it together
that Bagel could do some painting
and learn from the painting.
And if the programmers want to script
that one first they can.
Franzke: Stuff should go time-wise like,
well, at least roughly, right,
you need those animations
Kipnis: Think of the sound guys,
that's what they use as well.
Petty: Well, this happened
but their workflow,
all they do, is they take…
Kipnis: Oh! [Power out]
Schafer: Well, it is lunchtime.
Offscreen Voice: It could
have been worse.
Offscreen Voice: Do you see yourself
having a huge workload on this?
Crook: Yes. Yeah, we
started going through it
and I figure, I mean it's
a Tim Schafer game.
He likes characters, he likes dialogue.
And there'll be cut scenes.
Crook: I don't know.
I'm not sure what Tim wants
as far as fidelity on cut scenes.
Like I don't know.
Petty: The question is how
Full Throttle are we?
Crook: Right. Right.
For an animator this is horrible. But,
Franzke: I mean, like what if you could
just do all that stuff in Maya
Crook: We'll see how much of it we
can auto-gen as far as like lip-sync
and that sort of thing.
I just, I just hope, you know,
sometimes you do something,
you think, oh, we'll just automate it.
And then you do it and like
ah, it's not going to work.
You know, we need to just have,
you know, artists go in and do this.
Crook: So this was sort of a
test animation that I did yesterday.
And so she's stuck in this cake.
And then this just shows you her
turning, just to see what kind of,
if we can get a quick turn out of her.
And so we already have
the composition decided on
so we know what the position of
each of these characters will be in.
So when Bagel did the
initial designs, which is here,
he took that into consideration.
And so we know that she will
never have to turn any more than
what she does right there.
Rice: Just because that's
kind of a whole new process,
the 2D animation is something we
haven't done here at Double Fine.
And we're doing it in a way that is
similar to how we animate in 3D so that helps.
But that could easily be something that's
a lot more work than we're expecting.
Petty: Yeah, I'm not sure how we're
going to handle the tentacles
because when we talked about maybe
doing them purely as flip book animation,
because we are, we don't have, we
can't have enough joints in this engine to do,
to like animate them all freely.
Schafer: Is there a special close-up
monster different than the...?
Petty: We don't do any special close-up.
We do one version for everything
unless we have to do it,
because it's just a lot more work.
Schafer: Maybe not to joint everything
that you don't want to joint.
Or is it the painting of the details or is
the mouth shapes and all that stuff?
Petty: All the above.
Rice: We're still working on like our first
playable puzzle from the actual game.
We kind of bit off a big one.
So that's happening now.
Crook: So you know, when
I was creating lists
and I've been working
with Lee on schedule
and it's, it's, it's going
to get hairy, I think.
Petty: And then his
overall layout of that area,
I think this shows, this shows where
it is relative to the village.
Schafer: Things look great.
Schafer: So we'll meet with Peter.
Chan: This is kind of the square, but I,
you know, it could be a lot bigger,
but I wanted to just show what it
might look like down the street.
Schafer: I guess I'd like, I haven't
seen any, I mean, I like the...
Schafer: Yeah, some things are bugging
me about those mushroom houses.
For one, I hate mushrooms.
But two, it's like, oh, mushroom houses.
What is that making me think of?
And I thought Smurfs.
Schafer: You know, my only worry about
the mushroom town is if it invokes Smurfdom,
you know, because there is that kind of
Smurf shape with mushrooms a little bit.
So when I see the big castle's one big
mushroom, you know, there's parts,
there's shapes of mushrooms that don't
evoke that and there's shapes that do.
Petty: Like this doesn't really,
right? Chan: OK.
Schafer: No, that looks more like a…
Chan: Greg? When is my last day?
Petty: August tenth. August tenth.
Chan: Wow. OK.
So then we are, it's...
Rice: Getting there.
Chan: We're running out of time.
Schafer: Get drawing right now.
Chan: We've only just scratched the
surface really, by that.  We're still...
Schafer: We'll get more money
later and have you back.
Rice: You know, we got a lot of money but
that money goes a lot of places
and it's expensive to run a studio like
Double Fine in San Francisco.
So there's only so long we can have
this many people on the project
without running out of money.
We've got to make sure that we make
something great in that amount of time.
Schafer: OK.
Chan: Anything else? Schafer: Not me.
Petty: No, no. I'll call you soon.
Chan: OK, cool. I'm going to hang up.
You guys have a great rest of the day.
Schafer: Thanks, you too Peter. Bye.
Chan: OK, thank you, bye-bye.
Schafer: So like I really do like
all this stuff, and this stuff.
And that all works, too.
Like I was, I hope I didn't hurt
his feelings by saying Smurfs.
Sometimes you never know...Smurfs..
Petty: It's really hard not to
offend artists all the time.
Schafer: But that's my only
worry about some of this stuff.
Because I, I mean,
I like it but he did go,
like the very first thing
that he ever talked about
was this Japanese/Scandinavian
combination mushroom thing.
And so it's really hard
to say like I like it,
but I had seen anything else,
except I did also like
some of Bagel's crazy geometric
weird thing that he was doing, too.
That was kind of a unique
look for the castle.
Yeah, I mean I know Bagel's
got a lot of backgrounds to do
but I would like to see if he could come
up with any ideas about the buzzard.
Petty: So is Bagel, yeah, I mean, so
what we have to do, like with,
I guess we can talk about this
in the reviews or review meeting,
but Bagel right now, just, just
to paint what we already designed
for just the sacrifice puzzle will
take him this entire sprint.
He doesn't, he really doesn't have
time for, for any concept art at all.
He has time to interpret it like
when he gets to like paint it
and that's sort of built into the time.
And if, we can certainly do any of that
but it comes at the cost of
we either need to come up with
another solution for painting that-
Schafer: The problem with that is that
doesn't really solve the problem
of like having a game
be in Bagel's style.
'Cause if he isn't doing the concept
part of it, then it's not really,
Petty: well I dissagree...
Schafer:  it's his rendering style but it's not his like...
Petty: But that's what his painting is.
You're not using the
content from his painting.
You're not using the "Bob's Big Boy"
Schafer: When I talked about
like wanting to capture
some of the crazy stuff
from his fine art show,
there was a little guy on the table or the
woman with the mouth in her hair.
Like those are more ideas than
about a rendering style.
So like I wanted to
capture some of Bagel's,
some more surreal ideas in
the game concept, too.
Not just, not just his
rendering style, for sure.
Petty: Well then we need to
come up with another plan,
because right now it's not possible.
Schafer: But, 'cause I'm torn.
Because I also want Bagel to do
concepts, like come up with crazy ideas.
That's one of the things I like about
his art, is that he has these, you know,
kind of crazy surreal
ideas in his painting.
Not just the rendering style of it.
Rice: But yeah, I mean it was
a hard choice, you know,
when Tim decided that he wanted the
game to reflect Bagel's style.
Ultimately that means that he's going to
have to paint a lot of the game,
if not all of the game.
And it's going to be what makes the game
have kind of a cohesive feel and look.
Petty: I don't see how
it's going to work.
So we could either do
something like, you know,
someone else could render the characters
to give him time to do concept
design or someone, I don't know.
Something like that, some hybrid
sort of rendering style solution
that can work in a very similar style.
That's the only, you know, we'll have
to figure something like that out.
Because there just isn't time for
one person to do all that.
Schafer: I love this meeting wherein
we talk about can't be done.
Because those are always like,
those are kind of a drag,
'cause you're like trying,
you're trying to invent stuff.
You know, you're having this
problem with nothing to something,
like OK, I got an idea.
And someone says
that'll take three years;
you can't do it.
And you're like oh.
Do you know how hard
that was to have that idea?
Schafer: OK, I have to go do something.
Petty: OK. So...
Schafer: As much as
I would like to talk about
how we can't make this
awesome game in time.
Petty: I thought I was coming
up with ways that we could.
Schafer: I know. I'm going to
check out that inventory stuff.
Rice: Bye.
Schafer: Hey, Anna.
Kipnis: Yeah?
Can I see all that cool
inventory stuff I missed?
Petty: We're just going to wind up
shipping a game about a red bot
and a fucking lumberjack.
Sorry, Tim.
We decided to ship these instead.
Crook: Ran out of time.
Franzke: We ran out of time.
We did create all kind of tech for it...
Thank God it's up to you to make a game.
Here's a tool set, go
do whatever you want.
Rice: Yeah, I think there's
always a point in a project
where everything kind of gets real
and you see the amount of work
that you have in front of you.
There was a bit of an eye-opener
just through the docs
and the processes as far
as how much work is left.
And how much we can, we can do.
And the amount of time we have left.
Rice: It was an eye-opener that
we needed to get to the moment
where we're like OK, we need
to start building this game.
And we're getting to
the point where yeah,
where now the real work is beginning.
Schafer: Who was it,
it was like Miyamoto.
He said that famous quote about like
it only hurts until it's done,
but if it sucks, it sucks
forever, you know.
Schafer: So like OK, we'll suffer now,
we'll put the extra work
in to make this great,
because no one's going to remember,
you know, no one ever says about a game like,
oh you know, that game had a really
reasonable production cycle.
That was, I really enjoyed that game.
It was really moderately scheduled.
Rice: This was our
fourth milestone of 13.
So we need to start kind of pushing
forward, getting some content together
if we're going to stay on track.
Schafer: I mean, off of
what I'm pushing for
is like we should just think
about this problem longer,
because we're going to
have a creative solution
that's going to allow us to have
the great thing that I want,
but have it not take 20
years to put together.
It'll take, we'll think of the cheap.
You know, Lee and those
guys are really smart
and they could probably think
of a clever way to, you know,
cut the work in half and get it done.
Schafer: But it's hard to
commit to that in advance.
Like OK, I'll have a clever idea
and it'll cut this work in half,
'cause you know, those things you
don't know they're going to come.
But they always come.
[Music]
Offscreen Voice: Bye, guys.
See you tomorrow.
[Music]
Rice: Potentially getting some
art interns from the Institute.
That could do, you know, like the
menial tasks nobody wants to do.
Franzke: Well not even menial,
like, I mean all of my plans...