Stapley: Yeah, that's pretty.
Pretty colors.
Stapley: Yeah, I was
looking at the end there.
The 20th of September,
October, November, December,
January, February, March, April.
So yeah, everything looks cool here.
Yeah, those last
three months right there
seems like there's going
to be a lot of changing.
[Laughs}
From November to February
looks a little crazy.
Yeah man. It's going to be pretty nuts.
[Music]
[quite fantasy music]
Petty: Well, then we need to
come up with another plan
because right now it's not possible.
There's just not, one artist can't be
the primary, like he's the, he's the,
you know, like literally he's the
renderer for every object in the game.
And do concept design
on the schedule we have.
Schafer: I think if I hadn't been
through the process before,
I'd think the project was
falling apart last month.
It definitely is a little bit of a
tension as you switch gears
and you're talking
about practical matters.
But it wasn't that tense, you know.
Petty: For all the artists
involved but certainly for Bagel,
we're going to have make, you're
going to have decide, I guess,
which, what you want the hierarchy
of his time to be spent on.
[Ambient sci-fi music]
Schafer: I want him to come
up with both the, you know,
that really just like content
and then actual style, both.
Petty: There's other options there,
that we talked about all those options.
I don't think we've committed to
one particular solution yet.
Rice: I think it's an ongoing
conversation, so not really.
Schafer: I mean yeah, we're doing,
since we're doing a game
that's like a different engine type
than we've ever done before, it's like 2D.
A whole different engine, new devices
we'd never worked on and an adventure game,
which we would have never made a
straight adventure game here at this company.
So we're doing so many new things
with this project that we're just learning.
Every time we try to do something,
we find out like that's not going to work.
We do have to, of course, correct
and try different solutions.
But that's totally normal, expected.
Offscreen Voice: Don't
fuck with my wall.
Rice: But I mean, like a lot of it isn't
like, there's a problem, we're fucked.
It's like we need to
pay attention to this
and try to start figuring out
ways to make it work.
And we started thinking about
that and feeling more comfortable.
Schafer: Well, we have, we brought
on Levi and he's helping out.
Rice: We have some new people,
but like they're getting familiar
with everything pretty quickly.
Ryken: I was actually, on
Friday I was looking at this.
Just getting inspired.
This is the museum near Tokyo.
It's super cool and I went there
and I bought that there.
And for Friday, I just,
the first thing in the morning I was
getting inspired looking at that.
And then someone was
like, you know what?
They're playing a bunch of those right
now and apparently for like two weeks
they're playing all of
those studio Ghibli films.
And I'm just going to
be there every day.
It's happening right now. Yeah.
Over the weekend I
saw three: I saw Nausicaa,
which is like a big inspiration for stuff
that we're doing right now.
[Offscreen] Yeah we just
watched that last week.
Really great, it's really great.
Rice: Yeah. We had
like another art slot.
We didn't know what we
were going to fill it with
and like right now it makes sense
because concepts the most needed
and that's why Levi's around.
But I mean, who knows?
Like later in the project we could be
ramping down on concept
and need more animation
and have to switch it out.
But yeah, we always had one other spot
for an artist and I'm glad that it was Levi.
Offscreen Voice: How far along did
Peter Chan get with his contributions?
Rice: How far did Peter get?
I think the last stuff that Peter did
was some environment
designs for spaceship stuff.
Schafer: All right. It's been
good talking to you, Peter.
Chan: Thank you again, you guys, for
everything and it was a lot of fun.
And to be part of it.
So thank you for inviting me.
Schafer: We'll see you again.
Petty: Thanks, Peter.
Rice: Yeah, it was a bit of a bummer.
I mean, he was offsite so it wasn't
like we were hanging out all the time,
which would have been super fun.
But still, like I did look
forward to every Friday,
getting like a drop of art from him.
But Levi's around so like having him right
next door and getting to see his stuff,
which has been like a totally different
take on it and you know,
being able to hang out with him
in the office has been fun.
Rice: Yeah. I don't know if you
talked to Lee much about
what you're going to start
with, concept-wise.
Ryken: Yeah, I have concept
stuff for boy world stuff.
Rice: Did you check out
Peter's? Ryken: Yeah.
Rice: Yeah, are you scared?
It's a lot to live up to, man.
Ryken: I'll get out my tracing paper.
Rice: Yeah, I don't
think it works that way.
Ryken: Peter Chan did a
bunch of the early stuff
and I've been looking at
what he's been doing.
This is me, actually look at this.
That's bootleg P. Chan.
Schafer: And we have interviewed
an intern, an art intern.
I haven't met her yet, but everyone
seemed to like her and think she was good.
And that would help, too.
Offscreen Voice: Oh no, you filmed that!
Schafer: Please also join me in welcoming
Marius from Germany, where did he go...
There he is! Marius Fitz...
I'm going to have you
pronounce your last name.
Can you pronounce your last name for us?
Fietzek: Fietzek.
Schafer: You know, Marius was
the one who made an adventure game
as a job application for Double Fine,
which seems very nice.
Fietzek: Hey, I heard about the
Double Fine Adventure and was super-hyped
and yeah, I thought like if I want to,
if there's a chance to work with my
idols on the 2D animated game,
then this is like the only
chance maybe ever.
So I made an, application video game.
Schafer: Our plan is to actually
release that as a Double Fine Adventure
and then pocket all
the Kickstarter money.
We'll give you a small percentage of it.
How long will Marius
be here, Mr. Greg Rice?
Rice: Three months.
Schafer: You get three months, holy cow.
And what will he be doing?
Rice: Who knows? Schafer: Who knows.
Rice: Animating.
Schafer: You'll do some animating on Red's.
Fietzek: But I started with the
whole cinematic approach on
the very first cut scene,
just to see how it feels.
I thought of a very quiet start
where we first see the spaceship,
because I don't, I don't remember
a point at the space boy part
where we actually see the ship.
Schafer: Well, Marius is great.
Like he's like, he'll just show us,
you know, a story board
and it's really hard to like
how someone do something
that's really great and really funny,
but just for what you were thinking
of it, maybe it's not right.
Schafer: And the same
way the girl starts.
She's just laying on the hillside
and it's not a cut scene,
but like a steady state;
you exit out of it by tapping.
And the same way with this.
It's really got to be that it
pans over and shows him
and he's laying there on the bed,
and the same kind of just, you know.
[Schafer] So you got to like tell him,
like I had to tell him like this
whole sequence was backwards.
And he's like, oh great, OK, great.
And then I come back the
next day and it's completely different.
Exactly the way I wanted and it's
perfect and it's like, oh, that's great.
[Schafer vocalizing sound effects]
Schafer: That's awesome.
Schafer: You know, it's like,
finding someone like that is really,
it's hard to find people like that
and so you kind of hang onto them.
Of course, he's supposed
to go back to school.
So then you have to figure out whether
you want to derail someone's education
by trying to recruit them to
come to your company.
Which of course, I have no problem with.
I'm already done thinking about it
and I've already thought about it
while I was saying that sentence,
so, so much for his education.
[Laughter]
Rice: We're finally like fully staffed
and we've got like our team,
all of our budget's totally spent
on everyone who's on the team.
So I think that, you know, a month or
so from now it's going to feel like
everything's just kind of moving
forward steadily and the game is being made.
Rice: At the time when we
started the Maiden Feast,
that was kind of the only puzzle
that was far enough along
that we had enough of a design to
actually start building stuff.
So we did know going in that it was
like a super kind of meaty puzzle
that was going to be a
tough one to implement.
And we still, you know, it was kind of
all we had to go on at the point.
Schafer: I had the Maiden's Feast
designed so they had to like, oh,
we got to pick that, 'cause that's the
only thing that's really designed.
Rice: But by the time we'd gotten it
to like the first pass kind of state,
then we had designs for
this Cloud Colony stuff,
which we knew was just
a lot easier to implement
and a lot more indicative
of the rest of the game.
Schafer: So navigation across different
layers and pointing and clicking,
talking to people, camera motion
is all part of Cloud Colony.
Rice: One of the nice things about being
able to make those kinds of decisions
and jump around is we can like
really look at in the moment
what is most important for the game
and be able to kind of like change tracks,
without having to like clear that
decision with a publisher.
Schafer: So we kind of left Maiden Feast
where it was, which is, you know,
has like a stand-in, a couple
stand-in pieces of art in there.
Much as it pains me to leave that
unfinished, but we'll revisit it soon, I think.
Schafer: This is a kick-off meeting
for the Cloud Colony.
Required reading for this meeting is
this document everyone' read, I'm sure.
I've already started working on it.
So I think it's just good to
go over all the puzzles
in case it exposes things we haven't
thought of or just questions you guys have.
Are you ready? Ready to begin?
Schafer: This is the part of the game right
after the Maiden's Feast when you get,
when you break away and you hitch a
ride on that buzzard, on the corset.
And you fly.
It takes you up into the air.
She's the sacrifice girl who's just chosen to
run away instead of being sacrificed
and feels that she may
have just endangered,
she's been told that this will
endanger her entire town
if the monster's not appeased.
So now the monster's all upset and
she's feeling like I have to do something
to get rid of this monster and to
protect my family and my town.
But before I get back there I'm going
to have to like figure out a plan.
So she arrives in the home world,
if you will, of the bird,
which is a little village made of
primarily nests that have been,
that are buoyant on these really thick
clouds, that we're calling the Cloud Colony.
[Music]
Schafer: I feel much better because
I actually, like I felt good
after I wrote that cloud document,
but that was really only like four puzzles.
And the spaceship one has like
sixteen puzzles in there or something.
So I'm catching up now.
[Music]
Schafer: Aha! Work. I did work.
This is the spec for
the whole spaceship.
Designed all the puzzles
for the spaceship.
Offscreen Voice:
Really? All the puzzles?
Schafer: Yeah, all the
puzzles for the spaceship.
And this is just two-thirds of
the puzzles for the girl's world.
But there's still, I mean, there's
still a lot of stuff to design.
Schafer: But it's like I have
plot points, you know.
I have things where I know
I want that to end, Act One.
And then that ends Act Two.
And then I have these
plot points that happen.
And then to get to that plot
point you have to create
obstacles and puzzles at the same time,
which come out of the story.
Break out of routine.
Spaceship boy has this routine that
he's stuck in every day in space
and he has to break out of it.
That's the first puzzle.
You do work backwards.
Like you know, it's like you actually
aren't designing puzzles.
You're designing the
obstacles in a lot of ways.
Like you say, you had a situation in
the game where character,
you just know there's a plot point where
they have to shoot the President.
And so, I don't have any plans
to shoot the President.
So, but anyways, say that
was a puzzle in the game.
The President's really bad.
You got to shoot the President.
You know, I work backwards,
so some cool wish fulfillment,
like OK, he's going to be, he's
sneaking into the White House.
How would you sneak into White House?
You could wear a mask that made
you look like a visiting ambassador.
Like how do you make a plaster cast
of his face to make the mask?
Then maybe it's to trick him into
tripping and falling in cement.
And then at each point you think, OK,
was that an actual revelation?
Like you don't want to have, it just be
a series of tedious chores.
It's got to be like oh, I have a really
clear problem that I need to solve.
Like the three most obvious
ways to solve it don't work.
And the game anticipates that and
like has a great response
for when you try to
execute that solution.
You put a little like, aha!
Good try, no.
But did you think about this?
And that little nudge is like,
oh, you know, kind of,
like doesn't give you the answer
but kind of points you back towards
the ballpark where the answer is.
Schafer: This is the first puzzle.
So the puzzle is that you
open this a little bit.
And then you try to go to it, it closes.
And then there's some
really counterintuitive,
almost opposite of normal way of
thinking that makes you realize, ah!
If I did this really weird thing,
that would actually work.
The thing you had to do with
the lock is take the lock
and actually lock the gate shut.
So now when you try to pull the chain,
it can't pull the gate up and instead...
'Cause then the player's like,
oh, I'm so smart, you know.
I figured it out.
Now that a lot of stuff is
designed ahead of those guys
and they're able to look
at it and work on it.
That always relieves a
little bit of tension.
Rice: Tim has filled in,
it looks like boy world
and I think he's even put
more girl world stuff in.
Have you even looked
at this, really, Levi?
Ryken: This is all Tim does?
I thought he was supposed
to be writing things,
not just writing little
things on Post-its.
Rice: Yeah, he's writing the
whole game on little Post-its.
Ryken: Oh, OK.
Rice: There wasn't much there before,
so it's nice to see that it's filled out.
Rice: It's definitely unique
and different than
anything he's designed
or written before.
So I think it's cool to see that
he's trying something different
and kind of going out
on a limb a little bit.
I haven't seen any writing yet,
so I don't know what that's going to be like.
Because it does seem like this
game has a much more serious tone
than his other games have,
but I'm excited to get to that point
where I start seeing Tim's writing,
because I'm sure it'll be awesome.
Rice: So far this is in the game.
This is all in the game.
It looks like this.
And now we're going to be
starting on some of this stuff.
Rice: And we have an approved
girl, so that's exciting.
Petty: So let's see.
So let's look at the
suicide girl. So she's got...
Schafer: See, you call
her suicide girl, too.
Petty: Yeah.
Schafer: It's sacrifice girl.
Petty: I know it is.
So which of these dresses
do you like the most?
Schafer: My favorite one is that one,
but I like the original one.
I like that one, too.
Schafer: So I just put them in front of
my daughter and let her pick.
That solved the whole problem.
Schafer: These are the princesses
from papa's new game.
Schafer: I call them princesses.
Which one do you like best?
Think really hard.
Why do you like em?
Daughter: Because she's so beautiful.
Rice: And she's looking good.
We just got her in the game.
She's walking around and everything.
The boy's getting there.
We've done like two rounds on him.
Schafer: Scott's been working
on characters in the morning.
He's been kind of splitting his time with
a book that he's working on,
an art show or one of the
zillion things that he does.
He's very busy.
Campbell: So it's an ongoing kind of,
kind of project and this
is the culmination of it.
Culmination of like a year, you know,
like a year and a half's worth right now.
And then we have a book coming out,
so that's what we're doing, so.
Schafer: He's drawn some of the
sacrifice girl and spaceship boy.
He's been drawing some of
the Cloud Colony people.
And I'm supposed to
look at those, right.
I've got to give him feedback on those.
Schafer: I do like that guy, too.
But then again he is doing a cool pose.
Campbell: And it's going great, man.
It's looking really good.
I definitely feel that like relaxation
of like knowing that like these designs,
even if they're a little unfinished,
I know they're going to go to Bagel
and he's going to make them like,
fucking make 'em Bagel-style.
Dude, I just swore again.
I mean, I thought for sure I wasn't
going to swear in these things.
I'm mellowing out, dude.
But yeah, he's doing great.
He has a lot of work
ahead of him, though.
He's stressed about it,
but Bagel's the kind of guy,
he's like just this kind
of chill dude, you know.
He's like, I know.
He's like, I'm going to, he's like,
I'm going to have a lot of
work ahead of me, but ah.
'Cause it's like it's all fun stuff, you know,
he's doing what he loves,
which is like painting
that stuff, you know.
And he's definitely, he's
definitely feeling kind of nervous,
but I'm so excited for it to
be his, his look, so yeah.
Offscreen Voice: So Bagel's in the
studio this week? Rice: Yeah.
Bagel's in my house this week.
Offscreen Voice: Perfect.
Rice: He had to take
Marius's spot from the couch.
So Marius got kicked out.
I'm like running a hostel right now.
Stapley: Yeah, it's weird.
There's a lot of farting going on.
He has these weird nerdy
glasses that he wears at night.
Schafer: Why is Bagel in
the office this week?
I don't know.
Hi guys.
Schafer: Hi, oh my god you look so real.
Lee: He's come out of the camera!
Schafer: The microphone is
working so well today.
Bagel: My microphone is awesome!
Crook: Now we can't turn you down.
Schafer: Lee was starting some
new processes with art production,
like trying to get Bagel to
be pretty independent
where he could just paint actual art for
the game right into the engines.
So getting that set up was really hard
to do over Skype or Google Hang Outs,
like we do.
We don't always have the smoothest
conversations over that,
I don't know if you noticed.
Stapley: [inaudible]
Petty: I think we're going
to do it tomorrow.
Stapley: [inaudible]
Petty: What's that?
Petty: I'm sorry,
I can't make it out, dude.
Stapley: [inaudible]
[Laughing]
Stapley: But it is good to kind of
sit right with them, you know.
Crook: Yeah, I think this
texture, the painting style
goes really well with this sort of weird...
Stapley: Brush stroke.
Crook: the way we're animating it.
I think it goes really well with it.
I think it's cool.
Stapley: But yeah, there are some things
that are easier just to talk to,
like walk over to Lee and
talk to him, I think.
I've already done that like three
times today, which is pretty nice.
Rice: And here like with
such a small art team,
like it's going to be really important
that he's not only painting stuff
but like making sure it gets
into the game right
and looks good and he's viewing it in
the game and seeing how that changes.
Petty: So like Brandon
spent a lot of time
making sure that all the
tools he was writing
were going to help Bagel and make
sure that that was a really smooth process.
Brandon: The main thing that I've been
working is enhancements to our scene editor
so that the tool works a little
bit more like Photoshop
in terms of being able to hide and show
the layers that you're working on.
I got the Nav meshes in
there so that instead of
just editing these in text
files you can actually,
you know, individually kind of lay out the
geometry for the walkable areas.
Just really trying to flesh the stuff out so
that the workflow for artists is a lot smoother.
Rice: And it's almost there
so I think that's the,
that's the idea, is to try to get him
comfortable with that process.
Stapley: Yeah, so you can see...
Right. Right, right.
Still totally getting used to this shit.
[Music]
Stapley: Hey, bros. What's up?
How's it going, fellows?
Offscreen Voice: So, has
this been coming along?
Stapley: Oh, it's almost done,
it's almost done.
No, I'm just kidding.
It's not done at all.
I'm going to give up on it
and come back to it later.
And there's a bunch of other shit to do
and I like don't have any fresh
eyes on it anymore, you know.
I've just been looking at the same thing
for like a week and I'm over it.
I'm going to just work on it until stand-ups
and then Tim's going to check it out.
Petty: In terms of like
how good the readability is.
If it's feeling right to you, you know,
story, theme-wise and all that,
before he digs into
some of the other areas.
And then you know, like there's a lot of,
like because that Cloud Colony...
Schafer: I can see how the
world's going to look pretty
and how it's going to all look
like it's one cohesive thing,
but the secret thing that I'm hoping for is still,
we have some of the,
Bagel's ideas that only he would
come up with for the landscape.
Kind of bizarre.
He doesn't have those in there yet.
Stapley: Yeah, this was Peter's,
Peter's concept ideas.
Lee's layout.
Would I do a painting of this?
I'm not sure.
I don't know if I would.
But like I'm doing a painting of it now.
OK, man.
I'm wondering about
that Bagel filter thing.
I'm just wondering what it is, you know.
What if Tim's happy with it.
I should talk to Tim.
Schafer: I have not
talked to him about that.
I haven't talked to him on this trip
about how he's feeling about everything.
That'll be interesting.
Hopefully we get some alone time.
Petty: I just don't know
about the painting Bagel.
Now how are you
feeling about the like...
We've been going back
and forth a long time
just trying to get a feel
for that whole process.
Stapley: The paining process?
Petty: Yeah.
And then like work on this big
ass fucking layered files and...
Stapley: Yeah, yeah.
I'm comfortable with that.
I'd like to actually get involved more
with like the concept stuff, though.
Petty: Yeah?
Stapley: I feel like I'm
just kind of a painter.
I just feel like people are expecting
it to be mine somehow,
you know, just 'cause, you know.
That's what people are saying.
And like it's supposed to be
my style but it isn't really.
Petty: It may be that you're feeling
like the painting isn't the side
that you care about most.
Maybe you feel more about the shape,
language and the concept design
and we, you know, Levi does
painting and you do layouts.
There's flexibility there.
Stapley: Where like
I don't paint everything
but be kind of like overlook, you know.
Kind of just try to keep
everything together.
And that way I'm able to
do some more idea stuff.
'Cause even now the way it's going,
like I don't think, I mean,
like even this way
I don't think I'd be able to do all
these paintings in four months.
Seventy paintings by myself,
anyway, you know.
Well, at least if we're going to say
like this is Bagel's style game,
then I would, yeah, at least I would
have a little bit more like yeah,
you know, that is my stuff. You know.
Instead of like, ah, it's like an
awesome Peter Chan drawing
or something, you know, that I colored.
Why don't we like finish off this sprint
until the end of the month, right.
I'll try to get all this
cloud things going.
Petty: But I think it's a
tougher thing where that
if we come up with a sketch of a plan
that we think might work,
then I think we should try it sooner
than later, 'cause fuck a sprint.
Who cares? I don't care.
There's no publisher fucking
us in the ass over it.
Like with just the whole point is,
it's just there to like be milestones
as we make this game, right?
So if we, you know, as long we're meeting
Tim's goals for the project,
as long as we think we
can actually get it done
and as long as we're all
willing to give it a shot,
there's no reason in the world
we shouldn't be flexible. Right.
Stapley: I think it was because
really when it first started,
it was going to be like $300,000
and we're going to just try to do some
retro Day of the Tentacle shit, you know.
And I know things change so much from
the beginning of this
Kickstarter thing, you know.
And I know now it's huge,
it's a big thing, which is great.
And it's awesome.
But, I think we can work it out somehow.
Schafer: You know, right now Bagel's
been doing a lot of painting,
which is not necessarily, I can see
where that would feel like,
you're just like doing a coloring
book or paint-by-numbers.
Those are just my terms, not his.
Stapley: I don't know.
I don't even know how
it's going to turn out.
It might turn out totally different.
I'm just kind of glad I got it
off my chest, that's all.
Schafer: Yeah, I think his
coming out here in person
is what allowed him to
open up about that.
I think he's over Skype.
It's hard to really talk about,
how you're feeling.
Stapley: I'm glad I said it, because
I was all worried about it.
So I think so.
I think we're going to
try to start doing that.
Schafer: Like I'll feel a lot better
once we made one of something.
Like once, 'cause I was feeling like
we had not yet accomplished,
the game was looking good
and coming along, right.
But we'd not yet accomplished that
thing of seeing something
in the playable version of the game
that had that crazy Bagel-style yet.
Like the special element of like
surrealism or just kind of
dream logic that his
paintings might have.
I hadn't yet seen in the game yet.
So once we have something like that
in the game, I'll be like, OK, great.
We just need to do that a whole bunch
of times then I'll feel a lot more relaxed.
But until you achieve that, there's
always this question of like
will you be able to achieve
what you want to do.
You know, it's tricky,
'cause you got to make,
get the game to look the
way you want it to look,
but also get done on time
with the people that you have
and also all those
people have to be happy.
Yeah, like you're
trying to get people to
contribute their whole
selfs to the project.
So that's challenging.
But it's what I spent the
most of my time recently,
like the last ten years recently, like doing,
like trying to solve that problem.
How to make a group of
people work well together
and bring the best ideas forth and
make good stuff together.
[Music]