Stamos: Just even taking like what's the
new schedule out of it for a second,
it's like can we finish the game for,
you know, the remaining amount of money?
Because I think we're in a situation
where we need to significantly increase
our funding for this game.
Or significantly reduce
the scope of the game.
[Music]
Rice: OK.
Stamos: That said, really talking about
the overall schedule.
Right now the overall schedule for
Red's is posted as April.
And I think there's a sense
from the team that
that's not actually
a feasible timeframe.
Min: I think, I think just the larger goal
is when, like hey, when's our Alpha?
What's that mean?
When's our Beta?
When do we ship?
When's that, our big trailer coming.
Those are sort of like,
like the few hi level stuff
that I like to kind of get an idea of.
When are the ports coming online?
So it does worry me, because that
does make a big difference
in terms of what to do now.
Crook: And for me, like dates and things,
just working here for this long...
I've just gotten used to things
change and so I don't freak out.
And I think, you know, there were
times where it was, yeah,
we've had people freak out and like
leave because they freaked out.
And so I kind of learned that,
you just sort of, we'll figure it out.
Stamos: Not enough of work
has been done for the team
to have confidence that
they're really halfway through.
Stamos: And I think there's
a lot of work to do still,
to understand really what the scope is,
but it's coming into,
it's coming into view.
I think it's expanded a lot from
what they originally thought.
And when projects evolve like that,
you need to really reevaluate the plans.
So having a clear plan in place that
you can iterate on is a good start.
So I want to get like the tools in place
and help Greg get the tools in place
to have that, so that there's
a plan that he can easily iterate on.
So that's mostly what I'm helping with.
Stamos: Job number one is to make
this game awesome,
because it's just too important
to do anything else.
First steps first is to figure out
at least where we're landing.
And so that's not pick a date
and work back from that.
It is more of a bottoms-up.
Let's map out everything
that we know about the game
and then really see
how long it will take.
Schafer: Like can we do that before
this milestone is over or after?
'Cause what we'll find out in this
milestone is if we can bring,
if we can bring, Cloud Colony to Alpha
to Beta that'll mean something.
Not the end of all our problems,
but it'll mean something.
If we can't bring it to Beta, that'll be
even more informative in a way.
Schafer: But I never believe
that we're going to be late,
but I've been late before,
a couple times.
Three or four. Every time,
most of the times.
So we really want to prove that we can
get the Cloud Colony done this month
so we can prove that we're,
we're picking up the pace
and we're, you know,
we can finish stuff.
Schafer: It's great. I mean this is what
I've been waiting for,
it's been really frustrating to
be in the writing cave
and the designing cave for a long time.
'Cause it's like work's being done on the
game and I'm not participating in it.
and now I'm getting much more,
being much more participatory.
And I feel like, I feel like I'm able to
point at what needs to get done
and push on it to get it done more.
Schafer: There's two things
like for me, now the first one
was pretty much the same as this is,
but it's just like harder to list out.
Things that I'm looking
to find answers for.
'Cause I want find answers to almost
everything, like is the game working?
Is the game right?
Is it, like you have
this feeling after the sprint
and like that's exactly what
the game's going to look like,
but as far, as close as we can except
for the things that are obviously we can't.
That's the first one.
The second one sounds like,
it sounds like a disagreement
but it's not a disagreement.
It's really just working at
it from the other end.
It's that I really want the
Cloud Colony be done.
I mean like done with the Cloud Colony,
'cause we've been
working on it for long time
and we have a lot of
other areas to get to.
And so I want to have it be,
as much as possible,
have the approach of like we're
not coming back to the Cloud Colony.
I want to be approaching it like we're finishing
off in terms of Beta, you know.
Schafer: So we're going to go,
actually go through the game play
and make sure we itemize
all the things that need to be done.
Franzke: That's the idea.
All right.
And you were, Greg is
the official note taker.
Rice: Yes.  Schafer: OK.
So I'm trying to solve a puzzle.
I'm trying to make Jessie like me.
Jessie doesn't like me.
So when you go over here and you interact
with Jessie, where the hell did I go?
There, what's that?
What was that?
Kipnis: That's if you click off the
nav mesh or something like that.
Like that, that happens.
Schafer: Her turning
animation's a little much.
Kipnis: It's a little much?
Do you want it to be shorter?
Schafer: Well, it makes it really unresponsive
that she has to do that turn.
You kind of want her to
just move right away.
Rice: Play-throughs are awesome, yeah.
'Cause it gets everybody in the same room
together looking at it at the same time.
It like nails Tim down to where
like he has to like sit there
and play it with everybody
in a room and get directly like,
point out the things that
he's not happy with.
Because I mean, he plays it a lot
and he'll send the email feedback
and he'll bring things up
in stand-ups and stuff.
But it's nice to just be able to
sit there and like everybody see
it on the screen together
and like know the things that he
is not happy with and that need work.
Schafer: So first I have
to solve that puzzle.
So I come back here and I'm like...
[Groans]
Schafer: So task for Oliver,
make that crash optional.
Franzke: All right.
Optional crash system.
The game has encountered a problem.
Do you want to crash now?
No. All right. Game is recovered.
[Music]
Schafer: One of the hard things
about making an adventure game
is that the team doesn't often find
the game fun when they're working on it.
It's not like a first person shooter
where even if you're working on
a first person shooter, it's fun to play it.
But an adventure game, you know
all the solutions,
all the puzzles and
you know all the jokes.
So there's no like discovery or
you know, you know, wonder or...
It's fun to see it come together
and it's fun to see that you're
making something good.
But you don't stay late.
No one's going to stay late to like
play Red's after, after hours.
Hey, you want to play Red's?
Yeah, let's do it.
Let's hook it up.
'Cause like, oh, yeah, I know.
This is the puzzle I wired up.
So and that's always been sad.
Schafer: OK. I'm trying to remember
how to actually make games.
I'm trying to program.
First let me get all the latest stuff.
It's syncing up.
Now I'm going to run the game.
Never actually done this before.
This is gonna be embarrassing.
We should film the
second time I do this.
'Cause the second time I'll be like
[makes computer noises]
oh, this is Unix.  I know this.
[computer noises]
Offscreen Voice: Is that Jurassic Park?
Schafer: That Jurassic Park joke.
Is that getting too old to
make that reference?
I'm hoping I can actually just enter
dialogue myself into the engine.
'Cause you know, when you, you know,
for a long time from Psychonauts
and Brutal Legend stuff,
I'd write dialogue and then someone
like Anna or Kee
or someone would have to
come and implement it.
But then you don't get
to really like tweak it.
Like I like to put stuff in and then
see how the timing works out
and then mess with it.
And also it'd be nice while
I was writing if I didn't think
I was just creating a whole bunch
of work for someone else to do.
It'd be great if I could,
if I'm going to put it into Excel or
if I'm going to put it into a database,
I might as well just
put it into the game.
And then I'm not creating
work for, you know,
that way Anna can work on
something else and I can just do this.
And also at my age I really would
like to learn something
so I don't have Alzheimer's.
But I think it's too late.
I think I have it 'cause I can't
figure out at all what's happening.
How do I open this scene?
How do I open?
Open in project?
That's a bunch of things.
Can you believe I have a CS degree?
Class of '89.
Voice.
X vertical
Font.
Where's the dialogue?
Where's your dialogue?
I'm going to go ask her really quick.
I'll be right back.
Schafer: And then I'll totally be able
to program this entire game myself.
I got it.
I totally had it all figured out.
Wait...
This looks totally different
than on her computer.
Why did she set me up like this?
She totally lied to me.
I'm going to have to go back there
and ask her again.
Ugh.
Schafer: Like in theory, me being able
to program my own dialogue
in the game would save time.
It's not there quite yet.
See, I'm taking up Anna's time
but it's going to save her time later,
when I can program the
entire game myself.
Let's see if I remember anything
that Anna showed me.
I don't remember anything
It's annoying because I did touch stuff
and now I don't know
if I touched something.
I pretty much reverted
everything I touched.
Schafer: So embarrassing.
Schafer: I got it. I'm in.
I've hacked the mainframe.
I'm totally, I'm seeing all the beauty
that is Red's simultaneously at once.
Well, that's a day's work. Done.
Schafer: But there's this pressure to,
we got to meet the milestone.
I just got to get all this writing done.
I can't be messing around
with like this stuff.
So I changed gears and just
focus on getting all the dialogue done
and it means that Anna has to
spend a lot of time implementing it,
but the question is will there be a point
where I can actually, you know,
get up and running enough on the
programming to make that efficient?
I don't know.
Kipnis: There's just a lot more
content, I think, in these,
in Cloud Colony than there has been
in the other stuff that we've had.
And it's a lot of work
to get it all implemented.
Crook: I don't know. It'll be all right.
It'll be OK. It's always this way.
Ryken: It's, I think back the first game
that I worked on was Brutal Legend
and that was, that was my concept for what,
you know, games are like, you know.
And in this one it's like, it's not going to
take four and a half years?
Sounds like a good game for me.
But yeah, there's a lot of iteration in
the beginning and then you find,
you get closer to the spirit of the game
and I feel like when the game
starts gelling together,
kind of like the way just recently
the girl got a shadow.
And I was like happier
than high hell that
Just the smallest little thing
goes into the game and it,
it's no longer just this, this animated
stick figure walking around.
It's gelling it together and it
gets exciting, it gets exciting
because like those things are
going to be there as we're carving out
those little connectors to the world
that you're walking in, you know.
They're going to be there when
we start on new areas already
and you're going to have a feel
for walking through the spaces
and it's really cool.
Schafer: Look at that sinking!
That's awesome.
I can't save her!
I can't save her,
I can't save her! Get up!
Oh my God, I've had this dream.
Schafer: No, I get more excited
about this game every day
because as it starts to come together,
because we started from just scratch,
it's cool to actually see
it become real, you know.
Because of the framerate I can't
click anywhere
Schafer: But I think the game
is looking a lot better,
the characters are really pretty.
The backgrounds are getting
better and better looking.
And you know, we're starting
to see the basic interface working now.
And with music in, you know,
it's starting to really feel like
a real adventure game.
Ryken: And I was just doing
the
flat paint over on the art
that we had that Lee did, sent out.
Schafer: All right, everybody.
Let us break.
And let us do this again next week.
Stapley: So yesterday I was just
sort of going through
and painting a bunch
of the scenes files.
And now I'm just addressing all that feedback
from the walk-through, play-through.
Ryken: Yesterday I was
drawing hands for the girl
and then I got sick of
drawing hands for the girl.
So I stopped drawing hands for the girl.
Hands are the worst!
Why does anybody want to do hands?
Petty: So now she has hooks?
Ryken: Yeah. She's
always going like this.
Fietzek: And yesterday I did some last
final changes on the forum post,
which is online now.
So also, this is my last stand-up,
which is so sad.
And yeah. You know, like I, yeah,
I want to say a tiny bit.
I'm not so good at this, but just
a big thank you to all of you guys.
It's been an amazing three months.
You guys are all amazing
and amazing people.
I'm so thankful for that internship
and I did a group picture of us.
Kipnis: Awww!
Franzke: That's awesome.
[Laughter]
Everyone on the team,
including you guys.
Kipnis: Aww dude, thanks a lot.
Bagel: Lets just scan that in.
Fietzek: I'll send it around.
Kipnis: Should we make it poster size?
Fietzek: It should be big enough.
Petty: Thank you, Marius.
Thank you for all your hard work here.
It's been awesome having you here.
[Applause]
Schafer: I thought we might be able
to convince Marius to stay
because we would have had to just
derail his education as I said,
but there was, I was
not expecting the real reason
he was going back to Germany,
which was for love.
And though we are
evil enough to end education,
we could not fight
the force that is love.
Schafer: We were trying to set up a
contract where he could keep doing
what he's doing from Germany,
making animatics for us.
It's kind of like when Scott Campbell
and Nathan moved to New York.
I would just try and keep
those guys working for us
because I, you don't, you know, people,
people who are talented people
don't come around every day and you got
to like hang onto them when you can.
Marius: Yeah. I can try
coming back next year.
[Music]
Schafer: I feel like now we're actually
moving at the speed that we're moving at.
As soon as they get all
locked down with the process
between Bagel and Levi and Lee,
I think it'll be, feel like
we're moving at a good clip.
Offscreen Voice: So you're back?
Stapley: I'm back in action. Red's.
No way man.
Tim should wear my hat.
[Music]
Stapley: I'd like to actually get involved
more with like concept stuff, though.
Yeah, I feel like I'm
just kind of a painter.
Petty: Well, you and I
talked about that, right?
And you said you,
Stapley: Yeah, yeah, but like...
Petty: you wanted to do,
Stapley: the way it's turning with,
because all the designs are approved,
so it's basically like, it's approved.
You know what I mean?
Petty: Individuals have changed
what they wanted to do.
You know, initially Bagel did
want to do a lot of painting.
And I think as we started getting into that,
he felt like hey, you know,
I really want to be more on the compositional
side, which is fine, you know.
But that means we're going to have
to shift things around.
Petty: Do you think this process is
going to make that better?
Stapley: Which process?
Petty: Whatever, we're sort of
being non-specific...
Stapley: I think having more hands
painting and oh, well, I don't know.
I think I would feel, well,
at least if we're going to say
like this is Bagel's style of game,
then I would, yeah, at least I would have
a little bit more like yeah, you know,
that is my stuff.
Stapley: Like this sacrifice scene.
This is actually, I did the layout
in this one and the camera angles.
And I feel good how that went.
Offscreen Voice: It's more Bagel.
Stapley: Yeah, I feel, yeah,
like this is maybe more Bagel.
A little bit.
Petty: Click down, like just
double click towards the bottom
so she walks down there.
Schafer: What the? Whoa..!
Schafer: Yeah, I like the, the first
tested out was the sacrifice area,
the new method.
And I really liked that.
It's pretty and I like that whole setup.
I like the crazy big bird cages that
are moved and ripped open
and I think those are cool.
So it's promising.
Stapley: Yeah. So now it's just,
I guess there's just a question of like
talking to Levi and Lee this week
and figuring out the paint, how to
make it look consistent, you know.
That's, I think, the big
major thing right now.
All right, you know, that's the thing,
a worrisome thing that we should work on.
Petty: So this is the
very old one, right?
Based on the color key.
So, I painted this one entirely
with a charcoal brush,
'cause when we started I thought
that's what we're doing on that one.
So it's, I think it's,
it's a little too linear.
It's too charcoal-y and
colors are all wrong.
Petty: It's been difficult.
It's weird, it's weird finding out
which area, why it's been difficult.
Part of it has been has been,
he's evolving his own approach,
to like the clouds specifically
is very different than
sort of what painted the lumberjack.
So as his approach has been evolving,
I've been trying to like paint this way
and we've been changing
it back and forth.
Petty: I kind of feel I knew the way
we should try handling this one is,
if you, say take this scene
and do like a line drawing composition
and then do like a little small color key.
And then we give it to Levi and
have him try and paint it.
Ryken: I feel like we wouldn't need
that much of a color key,
considering we were coming from
an establishing shot already.
Petty: We've been doing other things
as well, as like, you know,
I have brush sets that I made
basing on he likes to use in Photoshop
and we're kind of updating those.
So those can be given to all the
artists that are painting digitally.
It's difficult.
I mean, I think one of the reasons why
it made sense to have him paint stuff
on the back end is it was,
it would have been,
he'd be the last person
touching each asset.
So it's necessarily just going to be
more unified stylistically.
But by moving him to the front,
it creates more, it probably gives
the overall sense of things a little more
quirkiness that he would have.
But it means we have more potential
like consistency drifting going on,
on the backside.
But yeah, I think it's been, everything's
been moving pretty well actually.
I'd say we made lots of really
good progress this sprint.
Dillon: Like I'm actually
really happy with
the progress that we made
in terms of this stuff.
We got a bunch of big features in
and the tool's a lot better, kind of stuff.
Rice: Just the little things, too, just like
the cameras feel so much better.
Just navigating around
is way better now.
Dillon: It's just one of those things
where it's like, you know,
getting a basic system
in there is easy and
giving it enough love so that it
actually feels good is hard.
Like having milestones like this
where we're really focused
on polishing up an area,
is a forcing function for like
we have a camera system but what we
actually need is a good camera system.
[Laughter]
Rice: Yeah.
Dillon: So I think we may have gotten a lot
of traction in a lot of different areas
and that stuff this time around.
Rice: Cool. Thanks, bro.
Rice: Oh, what? How successful is
the Cloud Colony stuff gonna be?
Yeah, how close are you going to be
to it actually being finished .
Rice: Well, I think we'll
have a better idea of that
after I go around and talk to everybody,
which I'm going to do right now.
Crook: But it's nice.
This is working, which
is really great to have.
So you know,
Rice: Yeah.
Three weeks ago we
didn't have any cut scenes.
Crook: It's been sort of
stuttering and going, you know,
but that's smoothing out
so we're making progress.
Just not as fast as we would like.
Johnstone: So he's cleaned up.
Rice: She.
Johnstone: She, she. She's cleaned up.
And I'm really done
in like five minutes.
Rice: Sweet.
Johnstone: Jessie's.
Rice: Awesome. Cool.
Johnstone: So that's where I'm in.
That's where I'm at.
Rice: Perfect.
Why is raining on your screen?
Johnstone: Oh. It's rainy
moods as a soundtrack.
It's nice.
Sometimes it's nice to
listen to ambient noise.
Rice: Cool.
Johnstone: So why not?
Rice: This isn't going as fast
as I was hoping it would.
Miss Kipnis, I'm coming to you.
Kipnis: So I mean, I don't, there's no way
I'm going to get through my entire list,
but I'll get, you know,
I'll get as much as I can.
Rice: Cool. Cool.
Petty: You know, there's not a ton left.
I mean, I'm pretty much on schedule.
I'm running a little behind but
it's only theoretically behind.
Rice: Sounds good, man.
Petty: Yeah.
Rice: We'll see how the
play-through goes tomorrow.
Schafer: Before we start,
I'm going to guess that,
like our goal was to finish
Cloud Colony this sprint.
I have a feeling it's not finished.
Rice: You might be right.
Schafer: Oh man.
I haven't even, we have like
another two week sprint
that it would be great if we could
finish Cloud Colony in that.
I don't want to just keep setting
up the team to fail, though.
Like OK you guys, we're going to
finish Cloud Colony this sprint.
OK, I didn't do it.
OK, this time we're definitely
going to finish. OK, no.
That didn't work either,
but OK, this sprint is the one.
So I don't want to say that,
but there still is a lot to do.
I mean, you can't right now play the three
puzzle branches, any of them to the end.
Rice: So yeah. Try to figure out
now what you'll be looking at.
Schafer: Yeah.
So we don't know what's going to happen
because, even if this sprint did finish,
if we'd finish Cloud Colony
we'd be looking at like,
looking at the design of the game
and how much time we have.
That we would not probably finish the game
in April as we had previously thought.
Rice: Um hm.
Schafer: Which we're still thinking we're
going to finish in April,
Rice: No.
Schafer: we've done some math that means,
Rice: We did some equations.
Schafer: And if we go past April that
would mean going past our money
that we got from Kickstarter,
which would be not great to do.
We're having discussions with Isa
and Justin about what,
how we want to deal with that.
So I don't think we're going to
conclude any of that in this meeting,
but that's the problem that we're
working on outside of this, too.
Schafer: So see how
much we did get done.
Rice: Yes. So there's, I have two
files on Google Drive.
One is the budget, one is schedule.
The original schedule that we made
was like an attempt
to get as many people
on the team as we can
and try to include like all of the
things outside of that camp
that we need to pay for.
And then like fit a game
into that time, essentially right.
And like as we were progressing
like it was obvious that
we weren't tracking to anything
that was going to fit in that time.
So now the hope is to try to start from
scratch on a new schedule,
taking in account like what we've seen
with Cloud Colony
and how long it's taken us to do that.
How many other additional screens
and areas are left
in the game as its currently spec'd
and try to take a new stab based on what
we know now, at how long we think
it'll actually take to make the game
that you are designing.
Stamos: So the new budget for this scenario
includes going all the way to September
and the increased team size,
which the increased team size is,
you know, like four or five people.
Bailey: And has like 1.1 million
dollars more costs.
Stamos: Yes. But the thing
about this schedule
is that it assumes at a certain point
that systems work gets done
and that the team gains efficiency
and the number of scenes almost doubles
at a certain point in the project
in order to get it done.
So it's actually pretty aggressive.
Bailey: Then I have to go find,
I need to find money.
Stamos: Yeah. That is the concern.
Bailey: OK. Because right now,
you know, it looks like, you know,
the plane's kind of
diving down a little bit
and we just need to,
we have time to pull up.
Schafer: What does the
plane diving down stand for?
Bailey: That's, just
Schafer: Us crashing?
Bailey: Yeah.
Schafer: The whole company
crashing into the ground.
Is that what you're
saying or are you being,
Bailey: I mean, the nicest, so the thing is
that Red's, this project is,
it's going to determine
the studio's success going forward.
It's a major portion of my forecast
of the health of the studio.
It hitting next year
is absolutely necessary
and how successful it is once it,
you know, is out there and it's live, you know,
determines our ability to be independent
and kind of have our own creative control,
like that we're enjoying now.
So...
Schafer: It just seems wrong to
make it cost more than we got.
Because we were so lucky to get
the money that we got,
because I'm going to feel like this
moral thing to finish it
for that amount of money or less.
And I'm sure our business guy
would love for us to finish for less.
But the game also has to be really good.
And it is an important
game to the studio.
And strategically it's an important
game for us because we own it.
We will, we don't have to share
the money with any sort of other party,
investor or publisher,
you know, it's all ours.
So it makes sense for us
to make a really good game.
Bailey: We have to, we have
to deliver on the vision
and I don't think it's going
to be done in the budget.
So we have to find more money.
And I feel like not only does it need to
deliver on what the
community is hoping it is
and the people that actually backed it,
but the whole community in general
and the crowd funding that's actually
occurred since then, we're the poster child.
And we're the poster child,
you know, succeed or fail.
And so, you know, we'd like to see
more games funded this way.
Rice: I think it's also just important
to keep in mind that
there's like other impacts
besides just funding the game.
And that like if we now go get
a publisher for this game
then it's suddenly like voids
everything we've said about the project
and everything we're trying to do.
It's hard and I know like we're
looking at a number that's large,
that we're saying we need.
But like as much as possible
just trying to make sure that
it's as good of money as this money was.
Bailey: I think, you know, there are,
obviously there are financial realities
that we have to be conscious of,
but I mean the reality is that, you know,
it needs to be a Double Fine game
and the quality and it has to
deliver on Tim's vision
and so it comes back to,
you know, can we,
what would be like the
minimum scope of the game
that you would feel it's still,
delivers on how you envisioned it.
Schafer: I mean, every time I've been
up against this kind of situation,
which is almost every
time, there's scope
and then there's money,
then there's efficiencies
and I've never seen this solved
any other way than all of the above.
Stamos: Yeah.
Schafer: You know what I mean?
Some scope reduction, some efficiency
improvements, some extra money.
Not like any one of those
things being the answer.
Bailey: Ok. Ok.
Rice: We can get it done.
Bailey: Should we do like an
all hands in and team?
[Laughter]
Rice: Yeah man.
Rice: OK.
Bailey: Alright guys.
Rice: OK. Let's keep those.
Rice: Ultimately the number one
decider in the schedule
is when do we feel like we
have a game that we're proud of.
So it's trying to figure out
the best plan of attack
to get us to where we feel proud
of the game and are ready to put it out.
But I think we're safe to assume
at this point that it's definitely past April.
So we just gotta kind of
figure out when that is.
And how we're going to get there.
We'll handle it.
[Music]
Schafer: What we've really done
is we've really banked the entire
company on this one project
and if even one thing goes wrong,
it'll take down the whole games industry.
Is that kind of what you're, or you mean
it like more like a Phil Fish thing?
Now that, you're gonna use that.
That's when you know.
Listen, that was copyright Phil Fish.
I can't do that.