[Buzzing noise]
[Schafer laughing]
Schafer: Oh my god.
Schafer: There you go.
Schafer: I forgot to put my beard on
this morning, you're right.
I left that beard at home.
People are going to
know it's a fake beard.
Rice: I think that it's also just
important to keep in mind
that there's like other impacts besides
just funding the game and that
like if we now go get a
publisher for this game,
then it's suddenly like voids
everything we've said about the project
and everything we're trying to do.
Schafer: Where did we leave off?
Oh, that's right.
Game was too big, company's
going to close down,
didn't have any money
and Cloud Colony wasn't done.
Bailey: Like because right
now, you know,
it looks like the plane's kind
of diving down a little bit
and we just need to,
we have time to pull up.
Schafer: What does the plane
diving down stand for?
Bailey: That stands for
Schafer: Us crashing?
Schafer: The whole company
crashing into the ground and burning?
Bailey: [laughing]
Rice: A lot actually.
Well, I mean right
after that episode aired,
yeah, right after that episode
aired we started Amnesia Fortnight
so the team kind of took a break
from everything for a little bit there.
Schafer: Amnesia Fortnight is
coming up, people.
And you forget what we
were working on for two weeks,
that's where the name comes from.
We split the company into small groups,
sometimes four or five groups.
And each group has to make
a game in two weeks.
Rice: I think ultimately that
was an amazing process
and people had a great time and
just came back really energized after that.
And a lot of progress has already
been made in this month since then.
Things are definitely moving along quicker
and we're starting to address
a lot of potential ways to help
make production go smoothly
and on a lower budget than
it's looking like it could.
Schafer: There's scope and then there's
money, then there's efficiencies.
And I've never seen this solved
any other way than all of the above.
Stamos: Yeah.
Schafer: You know what I mean?
Some scope reduction, some efficiency
improvements, some extra money.
We've been working on
simplifying some stuff.
J.P.'s come on
and we've been trying to look at things
in the spaceship we can simplify.
We cut some room, cut the teleporter
rooms, cut some simple stuff.
But it's more like an ongoing thing,
simplifying it as we go.
You know, you want to make the game,
most of the backers
I think would be unanimous in saying
they want a great game, right?
So they're trusting me
to use the judgment
of like how much to cut that
still makes it a great game.
And they don't want us
to cut more than that,
so we just have to, we've
been working on that problem.
Bailey: I'm not privy to what's actually
going on in the scoping side right now.
Although I hear that they're,
they're making some progress.
On the funding side I was
able to bring in a few deals
that don't require any
kind of creative control.
So like Brutal Legend PC, which to me
is potentially, you know,
better on PC than it would be on console,
because it's an RTS.
It has RTS elements.
It's never actually been released
and it's got, you know,
huge amount of music
already licensed in it
So we moved that up and you know,
we're looking to release that pretty soon.
And all or, no, some or all of
those profits will probably go back to Red's.
Schafer: I mean...for
one of our other games,
he found a licensing deal in Korea
So there's extra money and revenue
that can come in through that.
And that's the kind of
stuff I would never have,
I can't whip up a Korean licensing deal
on my own, I'd have no idea.
How do you, who do you even call?
Do you know any-?
We got such a response to Majus's print
from the last episode
that we can now, now selling the print.
Each one is a new line of dialogue
that I can put in the game,
so think about it that way.
Bailey: I don't know how much money
is actually going to be enough.
So for me, like my mandate is more.
Because I want Tim to be
able to completely check out
and when he feels the game's
done, then it's done.
Stamos: New addition to my office.
It's pretty exciting.
There's nothing much on it yet.
Oh, except there's a
red milestone right there.
I want to see how that goes.
We're working on all kinds of things
throughout the whole studio.
But when it comes to Red's we're
I come in as more of a
"how can we control costs?"
Hansen: This still is adding up to six
and a half months of tech work so [laughing]
we gotta find out.
Franzke: Oh that's just even
split across all the ...
Hanson: Well it was eight
and a half months before
Franzke: But that actually makes sense to me,
that this is kind of like a relief [laughs].
Stamos: More, more needs to be done
to really understand
what's left to do and
how long that will take.
Really like kind of refactoring all of our
assumptions about that schedule.
Really I think getting some project
management attention on it.
Matt Hansen coming in and working on
that uber-schedule so we can
really plan out what's happening
a little bit more down the road.
Hansen: Obviously Greg's already
the producer on the project.
But you know, it's super-important
for the studio, really important for us.
And you know, it's one of our
completely self-funded projects
so it's one of the things
where it did make sense
to bring on additional production help
to make sure that we're, we're running as
effectively and efficiently as possible.
I have some expertise from working in
adventure games in the past
so I think that's something they
wanted to bring onto the team
to help make it go smoothly as possible.
I'm actually pulling a lot from my
experiences on those games
to understand how to schedule the game,
scope it properly and stuff like that.
Hansen: I still have this remote deployment harness as
something I'm going to have to talk to Tim about.
I really want to push forward on that.
I think it's going to be really helpful
for debugging the game later on.
Franzke: I agree.
Otherwise we're just going to
shoot ourselves in the foot.
Hansen: Yeah.
Rice: And yeah, it's been helpful.
I think it's just like , it's nice to
be able to kind of hand it off to him
and kind of get ahead
of things a little bit.
It's going to be really helpful.
Hansen: Developing an engine and
a game at the same time,
it's always been a challenge
for a lot of different games.
You'll hear that as a common story for
a lot of games where they're, you know,
it's like, Limbo's a good example,
where they were trying to
develop the engine for Limbo,
they're also trying to create
the game at the same time.
It's huge, hugely challenging.
Hansen: All right. That's it.
Thank you very much.
I'll start laying this out and then
let's talk about maybe later.
Franzke: Yep.
Hansen: Later next week. Thanks a lot.
Stamos: So that's been huge.
I think that
having additional gameplay
programmers added to the team,
but who have design experience,
that that's probably helping.
Rice: Yeah, we just added
a handful of people to the team,
kind of staffing up a bit.
And it was people that were on The Cave
and that just shipped a few weeks ago.
[Applause]
Gilbert: Well, we shipped The Cave.
[Cheering]
Gilbert: On 742 platforms,
so that's good news.
Anyway, I just, you know,
a toast to everybody
and they just did an
amazing job on The Cave.
Group: Cheers!
And now what you have
all really been waiting for, cake.
Group: [laughs]
Schafer: Scoop it up with his hands
Put it in everyone's mouth
Line up.
Rice: And so they just are wrapping up their
final tasks and bug fixes for that
And as they become available,
we're just trying to figure out
what makes the most sense for him to be
working on and right now that is Reds.
So we've got someone from every discipline
added to the team and kind of helping
to lighten people's loads and add some
extra manpower to the game.
Schafer: Everyone's here, OK. Awesome.
Dailies. Film crew's back.
Not that you notice.
I'm sure you guys are all, for those of you
who have not ever been filmed before,
if you ignore them, really,
They'll just, they'll catch
you picking your nose.
Rice: We're too big now. I don't know
how they're going to do this.
Schafer: I know, look how huge we are.
Let's get this over with. OK.
Yesterday I was going to write those
last  three things for the Cloud Colony,
but I did a whole bunch of
other project review stuff.
LeBreton: It was pretty easy
to pick up on, you know.
Anna was teaching me
a whole bunch about the systems
that she wrote on the game play,
which is mainly what
I've been working with.
Just figuring out how,
how dialogue, I've been,
a lot of my work has been wiring up
the dialogue trees, you know.
We got the writing from Tim
and then we got scratch VO,
so I wired that up so you
can pick, "tell me more"
or "what about this" or "see you later."
Thomas: I guess you're better at
spotting fakes than the other birds.
Hey, can you take me here to my home?
You can? Great!
Ever seen this place? Great.
Can you take me there right now?
LeBreton: I enjoy all
phases of a project.
You know, if it's a good project then
it's fun to be in on the early inception
where you're getting to like, you know,
help really make big
important creative decisions.
It's fun to be in the middle
where you're producing stuff,
you know, you're building it
and eventually hit that
critical mass where it's like, yes,
we have a game now; we know
what we're building.
And then late in the game,
if you're not, you know,
if you're not stressing out too much
about like, you know,
fires that you have to put out,
it's really fun to like see the
last few steps come together
and really feel like some, like you're
putting polish on something.
So all of those are cool.
But yeah, I think we're very much
in the middle.
We're kind of like in
the early middle in this.
So yeah, no.
And I've worked, you know, I've, yeah,
I've led stuff before but also just
been in the trenches guy.
So you know, depends,
again, if it's a good project,
then I'll enjoy, and I can contribute
something substantial to it.
That's all I really care about.
Garner: It was on budget, on time;
everything was great.
You're going to, you're going
to go home early, no overtime.
Then I saw Episode 7
and I was like, aha.
Just the normal stuff.
They were just like,
would you be interested in DFA,
Tim wants you on that project so bad.
He's always talking about
Dave being in on the project.
Schafer: We got Dave Garner,
famous fan of Ico
and Shadow of the Colossus.
Garner: That shit is so awesome.
Schafer: And adventure games.
Yes, Garner's here because
adventure games are not dead.
Garner: Adventure games are not dead.
Garner: When I came on, I initially,
like the characters have
so much style in them.
The first thing that I
thought about was like,
I'm just going to like focus
on animating real subtle stuff
and like focus on the face
and like focus on the eyes.
That stuff's important in
like films and stuff
but we don't usually do
that stuff in games.
But I feel like that's one of the things
that we want to try to do with this one.
Garner: This is when we were
experimenting with like,
you know, what kind of an
attitude should he have?
Like sort of blank look on
his face, that's like kind of bored
because he's on the ship
and getting sick of this stuff.
And he's got like, you know,
his idles would be like, he's just like,
overall he's not too stoked on all
the stuff that's going on, on the ship.
But then when you start
playing with him and explore,
like we were saying it'll
start getting really cool
when he's just going
to be like, oh my God!
This is awesome!
A lot of people aren't
really going to notice that,
but like, hopeful some person
is like, oh yeah, that's really cool.
Like that boy, like I've seen him
change throughout the game, which is not
something not I've really
done with a character in a game before.
Is like have them go from,
you know, one character type
and, like actually end the
hero's journey having gone through it,
make, you know, an
emotional journey as well.
Which is something you see
in movies, just not so much in games.
Schafer: Who else got added?
We got Lydia.
We've had Lydia for a little while.
Lydia's a great effects artist,
technical artist.
Does a little programming on the side.
Small teams, everyone has
to do a bunch of stuff.
Choy: Generally I just go through and
just try to add things wherever I can,
because like with this Cloud Colony.
The more, the more there's
like little support ambient effects,
the more alive it feels.
Schafer: I think this ground
looks so pretty now.
And the little dust, and
the poofs and everything.
And look at that thing up there!
What's happening up there?
Is that 3D?
Petty: Well, it's an old
PlaysStation One trick.
We just took the texture
and put it on crisscross polygons.
And just spun it around in 3D.
Schafer: Oh now I hate it.
Now that I know.
Cheating, now I hate it.
It looks amazing.
Melian: So here's like a new
thing we're trying out.
It's actually using a 3D, a 3D element.
And you'll see it again.
So we're experimenting with that now.
Melian: I think so.
I think that's the idea.
If we can get these 3D elements
working and kind of blending in there
without popping out too much,
I think that's the idea.
And we'll go in and try to
do that more and more.
Schafer: Whoa color!
Oh there's a mom!
Hey, hi, mom.
She's got hair that comes
off of the crystal ball.
Peck: I guess last week was
like really my first time,
my first week where like I really got
to spend like a lot of my time on Red's.
Really fun.
Basically Lee's been working really
hard getting the environment white boxed
so you can actually just walk around.
And I'm just following behind him
wiring up the basic puzzle structure
as it comes in.
Yeah, this is the first piece
of color art we've got on this.
Like a rough color.
But still amazing.
It really reminds me of like,
you have a giant art book,
like hard cover picture
book in front of you
and just like turning the page
and being really immersed in the art.
Like you know, with the old
pixel-based adventure games,
they didn't have like this
camera flowing over things
and zooming in and panning out as much.
And this really feels like
I'm being like guided through this,
this really beautiful experience.
So that's what's really
captured my imagination so far,
is like this story is just being
presented in such a beautiful way.
I'm really excited to see like
where, how far we can push that.
Peck: Let me just load up
a certain level accepting.
Yeah, I'll open up the galley. Yeah.
Yeah, the bedroom and the
galley have the rough color.
It's amazing. It's like super cool.
Look how rough this is,
but there's still this like epic scale.
You know, you're supposed to be
floating out in space in a space suit,
but everything but man.
This really blew me away
when I saw that. So yeah.
I'm excited to talk to Bagel when he
comes in and be like, awesome job, man.
Stapley: So yeah, I guess lightings
down here and just try to tie it
a little in with that one.
I feel like these are, I mean
they're not totally different.
This color, I kinda like
this being more white.
I feel like this is a little too orange.
I mean, I guess it's just the
orange light, but still, yeah.
Maybe a little bit more yellow.
Hey, Tim. I'll get him later.
I say go for it.
Brand: It's a really
good learning experience.
I really like Bagel's style.
Yeah, he drew like a really
awesome style guide
that might pretty up the
different areas of the ship.
You know, the vibe each one should
give off and like the color palettes.
And a lot of the references
he was using to derive that look.
So like the player living area,
utility area and then there's an off-limits area
for later in the game.
He took that and then did the,
some even more like specific breakdowns
with just a bunch of
inspirational windows
that, with those shapes
and colors that he likes.
Stapley: I always go to orange.
Orange and brown and red is
like shit that I always fucking do.
I mean, I feel like, I mean it's
a little crutch that I have.
Not a crutch but it's
like my go-to color.
All the time.
But yeah man.
You can nail it.
Stapley: Your colors are awesome.
Rice: And I'm excited to see the space
stuff starting to come together, too,
because Tim just delivered the
dialogue for the boy's,
like first segment of the
game and it's amazing.
It's hilarious.
And you can so easily see how
fun it's going to be to play through.
Rice: Yeah, but like reading through it,
I don't see any holes.
Like I feel like,
Schafer: It's fucking perfect.
Rice: I feel like the game play
programmer could script that all up now
without needing any
questions, which is awesome.
Schafer: So no
questions will be allowed.
Schafer: I think spaceship boy's
stuff is easier, like the basic setup of it
leads it to, it's funny because
it's just, there's more humor in it.
And you would think you could
just make everything funny equally
but like the boy stuff's
just naturally funnier
because he's all alone with his mom,
the tension between him and his mom
and all the little robots and all
the silly scenes he finds himself in.
I have to figure out something for the
girl's world that makes it that easy to put,
to put jokes in there.
Here's a picture of
the climax of the game.
Do you want to see my pictures?
Total spoiler right there.
Can you see that?
Stamos: Yeah, I think that the
change that I've seen the most is Tim,
you know, absolutely.
Because he, he seems really
motivated to kind of get things going.
And also he's, he's
getting really close to
the point of the entire
game's designed out.
And I think that will be a big,
pretty big milestone.
[Juicer whirs on]
[Whooshing]
[Tim whistling]
Schafer: Lemon.
[Wet grinding]
Schafer: The juice fast is
all part of, you know,
when New Year's comes around
you make a bunch of resolutions.
And it's, my resolution was not to
die before my daughter got in college.
And also watching this documentary
and seeing my gut enter the room
like five minutes before I did.
It was just like, ah, got
to do something about that.
So now I look all shrunken
and my neck's all wiggly.
So you just can't win.
You just can't win and
I got a gallstone probably, so.
Just lose, lose scenario, documentaries.
[Whooshing slows down]
Schafer: I need a glass. Did
anyone else want juice?
Schafer: Yeah. I used to get a
lot more sleepy in the afternoons
and I don't know if that's coffee
or that's just being super fat.
Schafer: Alright. Pack up some
juice to take with me.
Cheers.
How much weight did I lose
while I was drinking that?
Did you notice?
You see like shrinkage?
Like, blugh.
Schafer: According to the Internet,
I'm like 230 right now.
Schafer: Like one site said
my weight should be 160 pounds.
And I started this at 260.
So I'm down 30 pounds.
Daughter: What?
Schafer: You get to come
shave off my beard.
Daughter: Papa, I don't
know how to shave.
Schafer: Well, there's a time
in every girl's life
when she needs to
learn how to shave.
Schafer: Here we go.
Here we go.
[Buzzing]
I'm really not going to do it.
I'm not going to do it.
This is terrible.
This is a horrible mistake.
Look at that.
Schafer: I used to just grow
a beard every Christmas,
like a Christmas beard, it'd
start around Thanksgiving.
Ray got me started on that.
And then one year I grew the Christmas
beard and I gained so much weight
while I had it on that when I went
to shave it off, I was like holy crap!
Where was all this hiding?
And then I was like,
I'm going grow it back.
'Cause you actually believe
that if you grow a beard,
you can totally hide
the fact that you're fat.
No one will figure it out.
I didn't mean to look at the
people with beards when I said that.
And as, like when I get down
to that weight again, I'll shave it off.
And so I shaved it off.
Schafer: I feel really dumb with this.
Try to get respect in a meeting.
I think here's a new design, you guys.
[Laughter offscreen]
[Buzzing]
This is now, this is my look
from like the '90s.
It was most of '90s.
I'm going to go all the way, you guys.
Schafer: If you think about it,
the car is just a metaphor for my body.
They're both essentially
really good looking,
but they've been, you know,
neglected a little bit over the years.
It's got some scratches.
There's a big knife hole
in the top of it, just like me.
It's a little rusty.
It doesn't start in the morning.
It's full of gas.
Etcetera, etcetera.
And my car is something that
I've been like just looking at,
I should really take
care of that eventually.
Kind of like, like, ah, I should
really lose this weight eventually.
So I tweeted like anyone
know a good mechanic?
And of course, John Romero
and Brenda Romero,
like we have this guy who's perfect for
a MoPar, which is what my Barracuda is.
And I went down there
and John showed up.
And of course I'm all excited
about getting my car fixed.
And then John pulls up in this amazing
like, pretty much a brand-new,
like Road Runner,
like '68, '69 Road Runner.
And it's all shiny.
The engine is cleaner than
anything in my house.
Like you could eat off it.
It's beautiful.
And my car's sitting there all sad.
Schafer: My sad old car.
Schafer: Which brings out a whole
bunch of different issues for me.
Like why aren't I rich like John Romero?
Next year I'll get on that.
This year I'm just going
to get the car fixed.
And I started feeling the money flow out
of my body as the guy was talking about
all the work he wanted to do on it.
Schafer: How expensive is this going to be?
I just want to get it running.
Schafer: So I need this game to be a hit
to get out of the debt I'm going to accrue
by getting that car running again.
[Engine roars]
Schafer: I think the
situation with our cars
really shows our levels of
financial success in the industry.
Schafer: And then John took me for
the most terrifying drive of my life.
[Engine accelerates]
Schafer: Jesus Christ!
[Romero laughs]
Schafer: It was like, in the car,
he hit the gas and it felt like,
like a sledge hammer just
punched in the back of my neck.
Just snapped back like
Aaaagghh!
[Engine roar; screaming]
And then John's driving.
I'm sure John is a really good driver,
but I'm not 100 percent sure about that.
[Engine roar]
Schafer: I thought I was gonna die.
Romero: Yeah!
[Laughs]
Thanks for the ride, John.
[Booing; Jeers]
Offscreen: Who are you?
Offscreen: Looks like a baby!
Schafer: All right. I know I don't
have the authority anymore.
Just look at me.
You'll get used to it.
Schafer: I shaved the beard,
I'm on a diet.
Fixed the car.
I'm getting my writing done.
It's just a new, all new me.
For a couple months.
Then i'll just go back.
Schafer: Red's.
Let go to projects. Red's,
We finished the sprint on Friday
and we're now looking at the build
and trying to see how we
get ready to actually play-test
and maybe a HOF-style
play-test with you guys.
Who would like to do that.
Maybe even, well, soon. Soon.
Let's just say soon.
Rice: That stands for Hour of Fun.
It's something that's been happening
here at Double Fine for a long time.
Schafer: All right. Everyone
excited about the HOF?
First HOF.
Who's new, raise your hand,
if you've never been in a HOF?
So you've all done HOFs before.
Let me tell you about the Hour of Fun.
Schafer: So way back on Psychonauts,
we found a lot of people had not played
the game, like some of the animators
had never booted up and played it.
I was like, how are we going to understand
our game unless everybody plays it?
So we had the mandatory
Hour of Fun on a Friday.
Everybody had to stop working
and play the game for an hour.
And then we did this thing
where we met afterwards
and be like, ask everybody
what they thought.
And it was really terrifying
that people actually talked about it,
but really good because we
got a lot of good feedback.
And so we did it all through Brutal.
We'd play the game and then
everybody would just get to say
whatever they felt about it.
Schafer: When you're milling around,
talking to people, try not to,
we try to not to influence people
too much when they're playing the game,
because we'd really like to get,
I think the most important feedback
is getting people to talk
about what they're trying to do,
because that's the stuff you
miss in adventure games a lot,
is like they're dragging this object
that doesn't make any sense.
And they're like oh, well, 'cause everyone
knows the bananas are flammable;
I'm just putting them in, like oh God.
Like we never thought of that.
So catching what
people are trying to do,
getting them talking
out loud is really good.
For the most part just watching,
observing people and just, we don't,
just try not to, there's a tendency
you want to explain, like oh my God!
That's, that's going to be much
better when you play.
Don't worry about that,
that's going to be really great.
Just don't even bother with that.
Just let them, let them
hate the game, 'cause you know,
the next HOF they'll be like, oh my God,
you got so much more improvements in.
It was great. OK.
This is going to be exciting. Whoo.
Schafer: Everybody will be playing the
game and then meeting afterwards to say,
I don't like this game.
Or I love this game.
Then we'll also have an
anonymous survey
where people can say
I just don't like Tim, whatever.
Rice: So we're going to be doing that
on the Cloud Colony this afternoon.
We've been working to kind of
polish that level up a bit
and get a lot of the details in there
that a first time player would need
to be able to understand what's going on.
Franzke: So the main things that we
need, just make it playable like,
can you basically go through
the entire Cloud Colony
without needing to load,
reload the game and stuff like that.
Well, the major things that I am
focused on is mostly crashes.
Really, it's kind of anything that
seriously goes wrong under the hood
where stuff just falls over and dies.
And it's good we got test
support last week a little bit,
so finally testers playing the game.
And looking at stuff and
they find things which is good.
And then we can go in
and fix those hopefully.
Rice: Yeah, we finally
testers on the game.
So they've been, you know, finding bugs
and putting them in our bug
database for us to fix.
Lo: Before I started
working as a tester,
I would basically spend eight hours
a day playing video games every day.
And now that it's my job,
I come home and I'm like,
I still look at a computer monitor
but I like, I don't really feel
like playing games that even,
that I've been excited for.
In fact, I think it actually made me
less excited for certain games.
I'm only excited for like
games that I really love,
whereas before I was like, oh,
I kind of like that game.
I might buy it.
And I'll play it.
It actually made me more
selective of the games
that I would actually beat nowadays.
And it takes a lot for a game
for me to actually complete it now.
So yeah.
But before there was an issue where
you pick up the ladder from that kid,
and then you pick up the egg.
There would be, it would just
crash the game for some reason.
There's that.
She just shoots in the top of ladder.
She doesn't have any
pupils for some reason.
Franzke: Very often it's like,
like a big shaky house
in the way like if you push it
at the wrong place it would fall over.
Just the way it is.
But yeah.
The trick is to find, the trick
is to find all those places
that the user can directly influence.
Directly or indirectly make
sure that those are failsafe.
And any good.
Schafer: OK. Thank you for
coming to our very first HOF.
We have the build, ready to go.
Some of you might have
installed it already.
Oliver sent out a mail,
a copied it on my mail so you
can just install it on your computer.
And it should just magically run
if you click on the "run" batch file.
It is a point-and-click
graphic adventure.
Offscreen: What?
Offscreen Voice: They don't
make those anymore.
Offscreen Voice: Those are dead.
Garner: Adventure games are not dead.
Schafer: Thank you.
Schafer: It has been almost one year since
we launched our Kickstarter, by the way.
And now we're having our first HOF.
And so we have done a lot of stuff
to get this adventure game engine
up and running and working
and we have a several room area of
what's called the Cloud Colony to play.
And we'd like to watch you play it.
Franzke: If it crashes like please come
to any of the Red's programmers
so we can help you, hopefully.
Also if it crashes during the game,
which hopefully it won't, please don't.
If you press F1
and then go to "load" you can restore
the previously, previous game state.
Schafer: OK, see you later.
We'll call you back in
here in about half an hour.
Schafer: What, you didn't
find a bug, did you?
Kipnis: What?
Schafer: You didn't find a bug, did you?
Stapley: To soften the blow of failure.
Yeah!
Offscreen Voice: Add something
on to that, some choices, right.
I sent one to them.
I think it was like,
who's Jessie or
something like that, right.
And then he said it, and I thought
it would take me back to
where I could ask something else,
like something else about the towers.
I guess I'm going down, the talking
tree or something like that.
Raz: Man, I don't know,
I don't know what,
like what's the first thing to get,
what to say, how do I kill this guy?
Rice: All the other one's good.
Have you seen the one here,
if you, go ahead, nothing.
Schafer: We aren't talking about,
Rice: We're talking about you.
Just keep going.
They updated the one here.
If you aren't coming up
that ladder, it's really nice.
Ryken: Adventure games are very quiet
during HOFs, a lot of thinking going on.
Petty: Oh, Drew crashed it.
Schafer: What? Who crashed?
Kipnis: What was the last thing
that you did, do you remember?
Inversin: I just went down the ladder
and zoomed in on her
and the curser appeared and then
the arrow appeared and it just froze.
Franzke: Yeah, I'm not sure what's
happening with that crash button.
Chi: This is what happened
when I went in here, so.
OK, this is where I crashed.
Franzke: OK, thank you.
Franzke: That's the other thing,
that Tony plays,
through Visual Studio in debug.
And he could reproduce a new bug.
So it's Windows only, XP only.
Dillon: That sounds
like a fun bug to fix.
Rice: That's the prettiest scene too.
[Music]
Schafer: Hello, hello.
[Murmuring]
Schafer: Hello. Thank you for playing,
thank you for playing Red's.
The first people who
have ever played Red's.
Patrick, you looked sad
there for a second.
Did you play?
Hackett: The game was
extremely charming.
It's really good.
But...
[Laughter]
Schafer: But...
Hackett: It's, there's just small things
like I wanted to speed up some
of the lines when they were repeating.
I wanted an explanation of
what was in my inventory.
Franklin: The areas, someone said,
I think it was a little unclear
where the camera would pan
and where it wouldn't.
Also as visually, maybe it wasn't
clear if there was like,
hey, there's more
down there or there isn't.
That was a big one.
Muir: I definitely had camera issues.
When it stops working,
you're like, oh shit.
Like I can't go, you know,it's like I'm
walking to the edge of the screen
and like it's happening and
then it gets really confusing.
So I mean, I guess it's just like
a little buggy in some of those areas.
But yeah, just no camera bugs,
I would suggest.
Yeah, that's my suggestion.
Eliminate the camera bugs.
Remo: Obviously the background
art is incredibly gorgeous.
The whole game is really beautiful,
but the specific style of
the art means everything
just looks like part of the background
and I don't get that feeling that
I often get in adventure games of like,
oh, these are hot spots.
I should be clicking these things.
And then when there were things that
I thought I should be able to click on,
like a big nest of eggs or something,
instead my character would just try
and path to like a plane behind it
and go around, because
it's not actually clickable.
So I felt like the game was
discouraging me from
trying to actually interact with
things and find things,
which is like to my memory,
what adventure, playing adventure games,
that feels like a big part of it.
And I felt like this game
didn't want me to do that.
Schafer: I'm a strong believer in being,
having a thick skin about feedback.
Like, 'cause when I've done writing,
I've done writing in a writing group
and you get together and you read
your stuff and people give you feedback.
And you should be,
you should say thank you when they
say something bad about your script,
'cause that's the thing that
if you can turn it around,
it now makes your script better
or your writing better.
So any feedback we get, even
if it's negative is like a gift,
because that's just an opportunity
to make the thing better.
And it's better you hear it from
your team than a game reviewer
or someone in the public.
Boehle: As I just was exploring the dialogue,
I kind of got a better sense of like,
oh, I want to kill the creature but oh,
I guess the next time the creature's
going to be there in Shellmound.
and oh, I guess I need this sap
to attract the creature in Shellmound.
and know I need to take
the tram to get there.
And so I liked how it was
a very natural progression,
just by talking to people
without even having to solve puzzles,
just to figure out what
I wanted to do as the character.
Martz: And I agree that it has like a,
kind of an open-ended quality,
but I definitely would have appreciated
some more like concrete goals.
Dawson: A little more back and forth
between the characters.
Each kind of revealing a little bit
of their world to each other.
That might have filled you in a little.
Muir: I think I especially noticed it
when I was talking to the Harmony dude.
And it was just like everything
that he said was just like, oh my God,
that's another thing
that I don't know about.
So like the whole world felt
super-alien and just like, just super-weird.
Schafer: So you really have to
get good at trying to like
pry out of them what
their experience is.
Like if they think, well,
this dialogue sequence is too long,
but it's really that the music
that was playing is looping too much
while they're doing it or
the dialogue is too long.
And you know, just, you got to,
you got to take all that feedback
and try to turn it into a
useful task to make the game better.
LeBreton: It sounds like
partly you were just like,
like when you're talking to the elder,
you were just kind of feeling
some exposition fatigue, right?
Like,
Muir: Yes.
LeBreton: he had lots to
tell you and I don't know,
spreading that out somehow or just...
Muir: And it was like single world,
single word questions
that you're clicking on to like,
for their progressed like,
LeBreton: Metal Gear.
Muir: Yes!
It totally reminded of Metal Gear.
I don't want to say that.
Schafer: Well, we're going
for a Metal Gear thing.
LeBreton: Obviously.
Schafer: Who found the cardboard box?
Schafer: That was great.
That was pretty good.
Most of it was directed toward stuff
that we just know we have to do anyway,
that's already on the list to get done.
Schafer: You've been
through HOFs before.
Schafer: I was going to say, watching it
through other people's eyes,
I was really proud of how much
work that you guys got done
because it was like, the girl had an
egg on her head and shoes on her feet
and she was kicking up dust
and she was climbing ladders.
And I was like, this game
is way too complicated.
Who came up with all this stuff?
So we'll start thinking about
a thread for all of this.
Thanks for everyone hustling
to get the build running.
It worked great.
I was very proud of it.
It was awesome.
I hope no one's feelings got hurt.
Schafer: To some like, yeah,
I do need to clarify the goals and the characters
that's going to be hard to do.
Just more work for that one,
but there's nothing that came up
that was really terrifying,
like oh God, how are we
You know, when you're doing a game
that has a lot of physical
action and stuff in it,
sometimes people are like,
it's just not, the bad,
the swordplay's not fun, you know.
And then you're just like, oh,
how are we going to solve that?
You know, it's just
another iteration around.
But I think everything, everything
that was said could easily
be turned into a task that
we can use to make the game better.
So that's good.
Schafer: I appreciate
you guys playing it.
Thank you for playing.
Thank you for staying and chatting.
Thank you for clapping.
[Clapping]
Thanks for coming.
Fill out your surveys.
Thank you.
[Music]
Schafer: And some people were
looking for a different experience.
Like you can tell some people were
really into just progression and beating a game,
which is not necessarily what a,
I mean, adventure games are kind of about that,
but they're also for enjoying the ride.
So hopefully make it
as enjoyable as possible.
Bye. Thanks for playing.
Muir: Hey, it's nice. I like it.
It's really good.
Schafer: Awesome.
Thanks for playing. Cool.
Muir: It's awesome. I'm excited.
Schafer: That's nice.
Brad.
He doesn't mean that.
He's going to say something really mean.
It's not as good as Iron Brigade.
OK. Cool.
Awesome.
Just slap my face.
[Music]