Brown: Good, a little more slowly.
Technician: And, 115.
Kaufman: Not quite.
We won't activate
the Omicron Inhibitor
until we're ready to take
the shields down.
Brown: Mm!
Yes.
Sorry.
I'm steppin' on you,
but: Wow. Yum.
Schafer: "Wow. Yum."
Brown: Dude, I love when--
When they get it right,
it's like, fuck.
Schafer: I want to eat your voice
when you poop it out.
Brown: It's the best.
Just fucking poopin'
in my mouth.
I'm saying that just for you.
[Music]
McConnel: Um...
I just really like to...
to be here
whenever I can make it
up the...hill.
It is a little reminiscent
of the field that the girl
starts out in, now, isn't it?
When I did that theme,
um...we hadn't moved yet.
Uh, so I sorta had
to imagine that field
and work to the picture, um...
But you know, uh...
The idea of a...
of a beautiful field
with solitude
that you can go to to just
get away from everything
and with a little village below
is-is definitely, uh...
you know, definitely resonates.
So maybe I...now that we're
moving back to the girl's world,
maybe it's time for me
to take more of these walks.
[Music]
Schafer: What is happening here?
What has been going on?
I've been so isolated
writing in here.
What else has been going on?
Every time I play the game,
it's got new crazy stuff in it,
which looks awesome.
Franzke: So here's the start screen.
And if I can basically
linear blend into 8-bit mode
and come out again and go back.
And the game is actually
full--fully playable.
Schafer: I don't know. Oliver just
snuck that in over the weekend.
He's like, "Hey, hit this--
hit this key."
And I was like, "Why?"
And I hit it.
It was like, pow, awesome.
Franzke: Um...and there are a bunch
of things that are happening.
I mean, obviously it's
pixelated, but we're also,
like, kind of compressing
the color range as well,
like in the old days.
So we're kind of
trying to emulate
that you only have 256 colors.
Like, since the beginning
of the project, I was like,
well, you know, I really like
the old-school games.
I like the pixelated art style
that we had back then.
Um...and then I was like,
well, I wonder if I can
just, like, take the image
and do some
just shader work to it to, like,
make it look like, you know,
it's a game made
in the '90s sometime,
like a little bit 8-bit.
Uh, and it works
pretty well, actually.
So far it seems okay, actually.
I thought I would be
way more stressed out.
So far it's okay, and probably,
uh, when you do the--
when you can do
the whole cutting thing,
you can cut, like, you know,
months in the future;
I will be sitting here like,
oh my God!
Schafer: And the team is bringing up
the last parts
of "Act 1" to alpha level.
Um, starting work
on the pyramid.
There's a pyramid
in the game
that's getting brought
to alpha this week,
and it's looking awesome.
Well, alpha is just that
there's something rough
in there
representing everything.
There's like, mm--
all the assets are, like--
Something's in there
taking a place for them.
And then--and then you get
them all workin' the way
you want them to for beta.
And then after beta,
you're hopefully
just fixing bugs.
Way ahead of schedule.
Rice: We're--we're good.
We're where I said we should be.
Schafer: Well, things move quick
once you--
You know, you have
certain deadlines.
Like, we wanted to get
a bunch of, um,
voice done so we could get
a PAX trailer.
And, um, also 'cause
the animators
are waiting for the voice
to start--
They haven't finished, like,
a single scene in the game yet
'cause then you want
the final voice in there.
So we wanna get that done,
and once it starts rolling,
it, um, it goes pretty quickly.
Crook: You know, when they play,
go through the playthroughs
and stuff right now,
sort of the animation
is sort of the least
polished, oftentimes.
And, um, and so sometimes
it's rough,
like, to sit through
playthroughs, you know,
and-and know that the quality
is not there yet
just 'cause you haven't
gotten to that phase.
Schafer: Greg came in;
he has a question for us.
Brown: Greg!
Rice: Hi.
Brown: How are you doing?
Rice: I am doing well, how are you?
Brown: Hey, I'm good.
Rice: Sweet. Um, no, I just,
uh, I got an email
from our new executive assistant
that was trying to set up
Tim's flights,
so I wanted to see
how things were looking
and if she should
go ahead and do that.
Brown: So if each one of these
characters has at least
80 lines to read, then, yes.
Rice: I think we're gonna
have enough written.
Schafer: So that's a question
for Malena or someone
with access to the database.
Rice: We can have Malena
run that right now.
Schafer: Okay. Today we're gonna start.
Please welcome Malena.
Malena Annable.
Annable: I'm so happy to be here
with you guys.
Schafer: Here in person.
She's come through the magic
of the screen to our world.
Just like the monsters
in "Pacific Rim."
She is a producer,
and she specializes
in localization
and things involving
the dialogue database.
Um...even though
she's up in Portland,
she remotely tracks
all that stuff
and she does localization
for all of our games.
And, um, she is the one pushing
on me for the writing deadline
to get it into Khris' hands,
'cause it kinda goes,
she gets the raw writing
and puts it in the database,
and, um, and gets the script
all ready to hand off to Khris.
That's a good question;
why is she here?
Maybe she's up to something.
Annable: Yeah, I wanna talk to you about
more dialogue things and...
Schafer: I have to write more dialogue?
Annable: Yeah, you do.
Schafer: God.
Annable: You don't want me to write it.
Schafer: Gotta be done by now.
It's gotta be done by now.
Annable: So, yeah, so I'm-I'm busy
with that all week.
I'm happy to see everyone.
Schafer: But if I write it this week,
it'll screw up the schedule,
'cause...
Okay.
Annable: So I want Tim
to write in the way
that whatever feels
most comfortable to him.
And as fast as possible.
Dialogue is so important
to our games,
so making sure that we have,
like, a really strong system--
I have--there's
a dialogue database
that Paul Du Bois built
and it's amazing.
And it's just--for me,
it's just management of,
like, you know,
tens of thousands of files.
I mean, "Brütal Legend,"
there are over 35,000 lines
of dialogue,
and I had to manage that
across five languages.
And...it wasn't that bad.
Rice: But, yeah, we could have Malena
check out current status
of lines per character.
And so if that happens,
you think, um, like,
casting-wise we'll be ready?
Brown: Um, I think we will.
I think we're, like--
I think by the end
of this meeting
we will know who we're gonna
choose for everything,
and then it'll be me calling
and checking avails
on them all for next week.
Schafer: And then a lot of our friends
are coming back.
Richard Horvitz,
the voice of Raz,
is gonna be doing some voices.
And Jennifer Hale, um,
from "Brütal Legend"
and "Mass Effect,"
is gonna be--
Yes, Shepard
is gonna be doing,
uh, I think
the Mom computer.
Um...and that's all
we have to announce
right now as far as voice,
but that's very exciting stuff.
Get that all wrapped up
so we'll actually have something
that we can put into the game
and show at PAX.
This weekend?
This weekend, oh my God,
it's coming up so soon.
We're flying down to LA to
record the voice for the game,
at least a third of it.
It's a third of the voice
for the game.
And we've got some, um,
interesting people
coming down to do voice.
Some old friends,
some hopefully new friends.
We'll be locked
in a room together,
me and Khris Brown,
for four days.
[Music]
Horvitz: There is no room in the Space
Weaver's life for friendship.
Brown: Aww...
Horvitz: He slides alone,
like a shuttle of yarn
across the warp of time
on an ever so--shortening--
Schafer: Fucked that up.
How can you fuck that up?
You totally fucked that up.
Horvitz: I love that!
That is so fucking good.
All right. Here we go.
Schafer: It's kinda like he's Pee Wee,
rebel, loner.
Technician: And, 24.
Horvitz: Look, see, see,
look at this,
look at this island
in front right here, see?
And it's just like this
hairline's receding.
I can't stand it.
Brown: Really?
Schafer: Lice check? Lice check?
Brown: It looks good.
Horvitz: No, not...
Brown: Tim, you have lice.
We have never cast
a game this quickly.
Um, and we have
never cast a game
with, um, a budget
this limited.
I mean, it--
with the exception of, you know,
with "Day of the Tentacle,"
you have, like,
1,500 lines,
you know what I mean?
But even then, I think, um...
I think we probably spent more
money on "Day of the Tentacle."
That's Tim,
who started the company,
and he was one of the chief
game designers at LucasArts,
working on, like,
"Monkey Island"
and kind of this whole, um,
set or series of games
that people feel
really strongly about.
They have a really strong
emotional connection
to those games,
and then we've continued...
I started at LucasArts in 1990.
And there were 60 of us.
Like, LucasArts was 60 people.
I mean, we were a bunch
of goofball rejects.
It's not--it's not
how it is now,
where you have guys
who go to college
and then video games
is a place
where you can be
successful financially.
Do you know what I mean?
We were all kids
who were alone...
and computers were...
our friends, you know?
And so then we were
in a safe place
where we could be together.
So, yeah, we super bonded.
Um, all of us.
I mean, we all still
talk to each other
and I think we'll
for the rest of our lives.
Schafer: Yes, we do know
each other really well,
'cause she was back at Lucas
back in the '90s.
So we've known each other
for a long time.
You get into a lot
of strange, um...
kinda routines
in the studio.
When you--it's like--
for some reason,
sitting in the recording
studio is grueling.
Like, you're just sitting
in this little chair,
you're hearing voices,
but like after a day of that
you're like, oh my God,
I was in this tiny room all day.
Like, I mean, maybe it's
like editing for you guys.
But it's like,
you're in a tiny room,
faced with a big control panel
and you're talking
over this inter--I don't know
why it's so exhausting.
I am so delirious from
that 30-hour session
that I, uh, I don't even know
who I am anymore.
Brown: It's almost like it was
"Brütal Legend."
Schafer: Oh, God.
Thirty hours.
I delegated all the hard
sessions of that one.
I only come
for the movie stars.
Brown: You're tellin' me, man.
Schafer: I mean, I only come
for the stuff.
Brown: You only come
for the important stuff.
Schafer: I leave the stuff where
the script is really
idiot-proof.
Do you like that term?
That's like a writing term.
Like, it's director-proof.
Yeah.
In screenwriting
class they're like,
"You gotta really write your
script so it's director-proof."
Brown: That's because people
were working with directors
who aren't me.
Schafer: It's just--it's a...
That's obviously
not the way I feel.
Brown: What?
Schafer: That's obviously
not the way I feel.
Brown: You just--okay, so I wanna
hear Frank's blowjob story.
No, your writing is awesome.
It's perfect and fantastic.
Schafer: It doesn't compare
to Frank's blowjob story.
So in between takes, um...
you just start to, um...
for some reason tell
extremely dirty jokes.
This is going in a weird
direction, obviously.
Brown: Well, the camera's off, right?
Schafer: Nope.
It's like, um,
going to some weird,
uh, foxhole
or trench together.
Technician: Hi, Jan.
[Offscreen] Hey, how are ya?
Technician: I'm good, how are you?
[Offscreen] Good. Good to see you.
Technician: You too.
[Offscreen]Check, check, check, check.
Check, check.
Check, check, check, check.
Cash, cash, cash.
Mark?
[Technician] Yeah, you're--no, you're good.
No, please no more.
Schafer: The boy, Shay,
that's the story about a boy
who was, um,
raised essentially
by a giant spaceship
all by himself,
and he lives alone
on this giant spaceship
and it's very quiet
and lonely.
Um, and he's cared for by...
uh, there's a mom
and a dad that appear
on the computer screens
and take care of him.
And these big, like,
knitting arms
come down for the mother
and that's you, the mom.
Hale: Oh...
Schafer: And it was great when he was 7,
but now he's 14,
he's startin' to feel
like he's tired
of this kid stuff
and he wants to do
something real with his life
and go out on adventures.
And so he meets
this shady character...
People who do--the professional
voice talent people,
like Jennifer Hale
and Richard Horvitz,
who just do this all the time,
they walk in the studio,
they don't know anything
about it, they grab the script
and they cold read it,
and they nail it
after a couple lines
like that.
Brown: And they walk in, and it's like,
okay, they gotta pull it out.
So it's--it is the hardest--
you know, as Jen Hale says,
she's like,
"It's not just acting,
it's acting on steroids."
It is the hardest job.
And you can't rely on
your facial expressions.
And how frantic
is she when she's,
um, "Shay, where are you going?
It's not safe. Shay!!!"
with three exclamation points?
Schafer: Um--
Brown: Is it like yelling, or...?
Hale: On a scale of 1 to 10.
Schafer: Um, she--this is when even
more hell has broken loose.
Like, the ship is actually
being attacked now,
and Shay is running
to go fix it.
He's gonna go get
his space suit.
And he's running
down the hallway,
and so you're
in one of the orbs
and you're doing
your normal thing, like,
trying to calm him down,
but then he's not stopping
and you're like,
"Hey, he's not listening to me.
He's not listening to my--
He's not being
calmed down by my thing.
And then, what's he doing?"
Hale: Okay, so 4:48, is it,
"Dear God, he's going to die,"
or is it, "Hey, listen to me"?
Schafer: No, it's the--it is the first--
the former more.
Hale: "Dear God, he's going to die."
Schafer: Like he--like's running out
into a tornado, kind of like--
Hale: He's running
into a tornado, okay.
Shay!
There you are.
Something's happened
to the ship, but don't worry.
Your father's
gone out to fix it.
Shay, where are you going?
It's not safe!
Shay!!!
Brown: There we go.
Schafer: Wow.
Schafer: Nice.
Brown: Perfect.
You know,
and the actor loved it.
I mean, you really want an actor
who loves what they do.
I don't hire celebrities
for a payday.
At any other company,
at any other studio,
people will say,
"Oh, let's get so-and-so!
You know, we're X studio,
we have X million dollars.
Let's just pay them,
because it's gonna be
rear ends in seats."
And I'm like,
why do you want someone
who's only here
for a payday?
Otherwise, it's a waste.
It's a waste of money,
it's a waste
of the actor's time.
You don't want someone
who's just, like,
not having fun
and not into it.
And that's the thing
about Tim's writing
and that's the thing
about Double Fine,
is that it's so incredibly
rewarding, the actors,
they come in and they do it
for essentially what's free.
Hale: All missions are cancelled.
I love you.
Brown: Good. Can we get,
um, three in a row,
um, slow and super sincere?
Hale: Uh-huh.
Brown: Of "I love you"s?
Schafer: Is that just
for personal use?
He--this boy is--
now that he's 14,
he's startin' to feel like,
"I'm sick of these--
I wanna do some actual action
and get out there."
Kaufman: Yeah.
Schafer: And that's when he meets Marek.
He's, like, the wolf
who comes out of the cracks;
he's been watching.
Brown: Do you wanna hear the aud,
or are you good?
Kaufman: Uh, yeah,
I'll listen to it again.
I-I-I...you mean, my, uh...?
Brown: Your read?
Kaufman: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
David Kaufman, Marek.
You came because you are done
with children's games.
My name is Marek,
and what I'm about to show you
is no game.
Schafer: We were talking about that
when we were casting.
It was like, well, we have this
other guy we know can do it,
but I really like this guy's
voice, and it's new.
And I usually tend to go
for that, like,
really unique voice
more often,
even though it's a risk,
because sometimes
you bring somebody in
'cause you like the audition
and you don't know
anything else about them
and it turns out they
can't do anything else
except for that exact thing
they did in the audition.
Or they can't hit
the audition again.
Sometimes we've
had people come in
and they just can't seem
to capture
the magic
of the audition again.
And even--
so we'll play it for them,
like, "Listen to this audition."
And they'll be like, "Um...
I don't wanna do it that way."
He's--the way you read that
is a nice contrast to the mom,
who's--the computer
is like this--
the ship's computer is like this
really over-mothering mother
who's just, you know,
everything is sweet
and she's being so sweet
to the boy all the time,
and then you're just, like,
you're not cutting him any slack
and you're just like,
"I'm not here to love you,
right?
There's war going on."
Kaufman: Tell no one.
Do you understand?
No one.
Schafer: Whoa.
Kaufman: No one.
Schafer: I like that; scary.
Brown: Perfect.
Yeah, having this dude
in here has just, like,
made the game, like,
whoa, fuck.
I mean, to see those people
come to life, I mean,
as you saw with Marek, like,
all of a sudden, you know,
it wasn't just these
lines on the page.
It was like, holy shit.
Like, yesterday when
I was listening to him
I was like, oh-kay.
This game, uh...um...
It's not just a funny
thing anymore.
Like, it's not just like,
oh, this is really sweet
and we have this sweet boy
and he's coming of age.
But once we had Marek,
it's like, that's the linchpin,
do you know what I mean,
for the boy's story.
Like, once we have him,
that was crazy, you know?
And I--and I went home
and I was like, okay,
this game has a heart,
it lives and it breathes,
because we have that conflict
and we have that intrigue.
And that's, I mean,
that's so amazing.
The game went from being,
like, oh my God, it's cute
and it has beautiful
characters and da-da-da.
But, like, Marek--
And I'm--
seriously, like, I am--
these guys will tell you,
like, one, I'm s--
a total super bitch.
Two, like, like,
there's--I--like...
There's no reason for me
to tell you this.
Like, there's zero, right?
Kaufman: That's awesome.
Brown: Yeah. It's fucking awesome.
Schafer: She's even understanding
what a bitch she is.
Also that.
[Music]
[Mario game sounds]
Schafer: Sorry. I'm getting
really into this game now.
Brown: No, it's super cute.
I like the little sounds.
Schafer: Oh, I walked right down
the thing, the thing!
Brown: I really...
I'm trying to resist
getting...this.
Because I wanna play
"Animal Crossing."
Schafer: Get "Animal Crossing."
It's good for you.
Brown: I--no, I can't.
Schafer: "Animal Crossing"
made me a better person.
Brown: Really?
Schafer: Yeah, 'cause it's all about...
Brown: Making nice things?
Schafer: Just every day--
no, just every day
doing a little bit
of stuff.
Not, like,
rushing through things
for a goal
or anything like that.
It's really--
I think it's mentally good
for you to play it.
Dang it, I really suck
at this game.
Brown: 'Cause every minute that
I'm not either working or...
Schafer: Hello!
Hello there.
Black: Hi, Tim Schafer.
Schafer: Welcome to the project
"Broken Age."
Black: Thank you for having me here.
Is it well lit enough?
I feel like we're
in a dark shadow.
Here we go.
Schafer: I feel good about this. Good.
Black: Tell me about the project.
What are we doing today?
Schafer: I'm so glad that you asked.
Black: Is this who I'm
gonna be voicing?
Brown: Yes.
Schafer: Yeah, Harm'ny.
We're, like--yeah,
he's kinda like a guru.
Brown: He's like
a cultic personality.
Schafer: And a little,
like, not shady,
but a little bit like,
"Heyyy, hey."
'Cause he's a little bit
of a fraud.
Black: Okay. I have no idea
what's going on.
Schafer: And Harm'ny's main thing,
he runs the cloud colony,
that's his main thing.
Black: Harm'ny is a cult leader.
Schafer: Yeah.
And a little bit of a fraud.
Black: And he runs the cloud colony.
And is he also
like other gurus,
where it's also about,
like, uh...
"Let me give you my seed.
It's--believe me, this is--"
Brown: See? All the guys wanna
touch your vagina.
That's what I said:
Does he wanna touch vaginas?
Because all those dudes do!
Schafer: We don't really--
Black: Well, all the gurus,
it comes down to--yeah.
Brown: For sure!
Schafer: We don't really explore that
very much in the game,
but I don't think it's--
Black: No. And we don't need to.
It's-it's-it's there, though.
It's underneath.
Brown: It's implied, it's implied.
Schafer: I think people assume.
Seeing Jack again
was really fun.
Um, I haven't seen him for--
since the end of "Brütal."
And so it was fun
to see Jack again.
He was a good sport.
Black: I feel like
I need to research
a little while
before I start acting.
Schafer: We told you way too much.
Okay, so there's
a few lines today
and there'll be more in--
we haven't done--
we've only written the first
half of the game so far.
So when we're at the second
half, I hope we can get you
to come back again, yeah.
Black: Okay, you ready?
Technician: Cool, I'll give you
a take number,
then we'll be rolling,
and if you need
your headphones adjusted,
just let me know.
Black: All right, and...
Technician: It's take 1.
Black: Take 1, self "Action."
Oh-ho-ho, oh my!
A fresh face rises from below.
Oh my!
Schafer: I like that.
Black: Wait, let me be more of
a cult guy.
Oh my!
Oh my...
Oh my goodness.
A fresh face rises from below.
Hello.
Before you ask,
let me answer.
Yes, you may live here
in Meriloft forever.
Brown: That's perfect.
Schafer: I love that gentle version
you just did.
Brown: Love it.
Schafer: That's awesome.
Black: Before you ask,
let me answer.
Yes...you may live here
in Meriloft forever.
Schafer: Yaaay, I love that one.
Black: Oh, now we're gettin'
somewheres.
Schafer: Yeah, it was really fun
to watch Jack come in there
and just start with one thing
and he does it
over and over again
and he kinda hones in
on the character.
And we're not directing him,
but we're directing him
by not directing him
in that he knows that
if we hear something
we really, really like,
we'll chime in and be like,
"That! That's perfect.
That's amazing."
So if he's not hearing anything,
he's just gonna keep working it
and working it until, you know,
he gets something that he likes
and then we'll
probably like it, too.
Black: What? No!
What? No!
Uh...I mean...
Take it away.
I need it like I need a--
I need it like a blue jay
needs a bowling ball.
Schafer: Maybe he--yeah, he really
recomposes himself
and does--goes back to his
total, like, smooth guy voice.
Black: Oh, okay, yeah.
Black: What? No!
I'm...uh...I mean...
take it away.
I need it like a blue jay
needs a bowling ball.
Brown: Good.
Schafer: That's awesome. Great.
Black: Am I--am I all finito?
Brown: Yeah.
Schafer: That's it for now.
Black: That was so easy!
Schafer: That's so easy!
Yeah, I do have the little one,
and this one.
Black: I feel like I should do
something dramatic so that--
Schafer: You wanna punch me?
Black: Yeah.
That'll teach you to not give me
a very big part in your game.
Schafer: That felt right.
That felt good.
That was dramatic.
Crook: How was recording?
Was that good?
Schafer: Oh, yes.
This is, like, like, dailies.
Rice: Tell us all about it.
Schafer: Uh, recording was--was awesome.
Yeah, Marek was awesome.
He does this kinda creepy thing.
Kipnis: Who is he?
Rice: Who is he?
Schafer: He's...he's someone
who does a lot of game--
no, a lot of game work,
but, um--
Kipnis: Was it Lee?
Schafer: I didn't recognize his name.
It was Lee Petty.
No, he did it
different than Lee.
Like, Lee was kinda like,
"Yeah, you, gah..."
That sounds like Lee.
Rice: Yeah.
Schafer: He was more like,
"Come here further--"
He was--he did it
a little creepier.
"While you've been traveling
and plating ice cream..."
Rice: Oh, that's awesome.
Schafer: "...and playing with trains--"
And, uh, Richard Horvitz,
who did Raz,
did, um, a couple of characters.
And he did the Space Weaver.
Not as good, of course,
as Dave's,
but it is Raz.
None of the cut scenes
have been animated
because we just got
the professional VO in,
so you'll hear
the professional VO,
but we haven't animated to it,
so it's a lot of, like,
animatics,
like, sliding around,
which I'm sure
you've seen before
in games, maybe.
Rice: You gotta wait till you have
the voice to animate to it.
-Ah, okay, right.
Schafer: So some of the--
some of the background art
is final
and some of the in-game
animation is more final,
but, uh, the cut scenes
definitely get super janky.
Crook: We've got all the pro VO,
and so...
we just have too much work to do
for the animators that we have.
I mean, we used to have
a much bigger animation team,
uh, which was--
it was probably a little more
than double, maybe,
than what we have right now,
when we were on "Brütal Legend."
Um, and, you know,
people have left
and we've just never
replaced anybody, so...um...
So, yeah.
So, yeah, so we had to hire
an outside animation team
or a company.
Schafer: We have so much
animation to do,
we have to use outsourcers,
which we've never done.
I've never done outsourced
animation before
'cause we've always tested it
and it's always looked terrible.
But this group looks good,
and the test we did looks good,
and so hopefully they'll
just do some awesome stuff
that'll help us get
the game done on time.
Is that it?
Rice: Yep, I think so.
Schafer: Get it all out.
Let's outsource the rest of it
and take it--
call it a day.
Petty: Pleasure cruise.
Rice: Perfect.
Schafer: Woo!
Gardner: Oh, see, he's typing.
See, that's someone
typing in Portland.
What's gonna happen?
Look! See?
Aww.
See?
He, like--I think he
even is a backer, too.
Yeah, see, he is a backer.
Ha!
This is Alex.
He's the guy
that's supervising
all of the stuff
over at Super Genius.
And they're the people that
we're doing the contracting with
up in Portland.
So you can see
in this animation,
it's really--
this-this hand gesture
of the wolf, the attention
that somebody spends,
it really feels
like there's more
than just two drawings there.
And it's that sort
to attention to detail
that we just don't
have the time.
What we get with Super Genius
is that we get to add
all that character
to the animations
and we get to spend
all that time saying,
"Hey, this'll just be hilarious
if we make him, like, you know,
skip down the, you know,
the hill instead of just copy
the walk animation
and paste it there."
And we get the--
we get to add all that stuff,
but instead of
right now being like,
"What are we gonna do?
We're screwed!
Like, there so much work to do!"
And then you ship a game
and it's like you just look
at it and you're like,
wow, we didn't polish that,
we didn't polish that,
you didn't polish this,
you didn't polish that.
Like, there's always,
like--there's--
you ship a game and there's--
all you see is, as an animator,
is the stuff
you didn't polish.
And, uh...
You know, with Super Genius,
it's like hopefully what
we're gonna see is a game
where it's like
that game where you're al--that
I've always wanted to work on,
where everything's polished,
where you look at it
and you're like,
the whole thing is--is all--
is done all the way.
How about this?
Hey, Ray?
Will you--so--
Crook: I'm workin'!
I'm workin';
leave me alone.
Gardner: I know, I finally
got you workin'.
I want you to see this, uh--
Crook: I turned this over to you
so I could just work.
I'm just kidding,
I'm just kidding.
Schafer: Oh, yeah.
Our expert crack team
of judges
are the animation department.
I mean, the animators,
they're the ones who are--
Ray's the lead animator,
so he's in charge of making sure
that everything animated
on the project looks good,
including the outsourcing team,
so we leave that up to him.
Crook: Once we got
the--the pro VO,
it kinda changed
the wolf a lot for me.
It's fine. I mean, I don't think
Tim has seen this scene, so...
I hope he's--he's still okay
with--
See, I hope he's still okay
with that sort of, like...
Gardner: Oh, this?
Crook: The, like, poppy gestures,
you know?
Where he, like, comes up
and he's like, bum-bum, bump.
I mean, it's--
it's probably okay.
-It's probably okay.
Roberts: Yeah, it--
Until--until Tim sees it
and says--yeah.
Gardner: If he was--like, if he just
drew back slower--
Crook: Right.
Marek: Affirmative.
Crook: "Affirmative."
Yeah, I think we should
just slow it down.
I think he should be more like,
"Affirmative."
Gardner: All right, cool.
Then I'm gonna give 'em
the note to watch
out for that.
Crook: And just--just make it
less poppy.
The--but he delivers it
pretty quickly, so...
We'd better let Tim choose.
And then-then-then-then
Elliott can win.
Roberts: Fuckin' Lee.
Schafer: All right.
Rice: Cool.
Schafer: Don't show this stuff.
Rice: I won't.
Just, it's pretty.
That's all you need to know.
Hamilon: Yeah, that this part
of the game is pretty?
Um...but yeah,
this--I mean...
Yeah, this is cool.
This game looks good.
I wanna play more.
When you--are you guys gonna
have a demo of this game?
Greg: Also meeting today
about a PAX demo, um,
and what the scope
of that will look like.
Start figuring out
a plan for that.
Schafer: Okay.
Rice: Should be fun.
Kipnis: I would...I would vote against
a public demo for now.
Schafer: What would we have at our booth,
then, if we...just do a trailer?
Rice: Nothing.
Schafer: What do you mean, nothing?
Rice: It'd mean we have no games
at our booth right now.
Schafer: I mean, depends how we show it.
Like, showing adventure games
on the--on the--
like, at E3 and stuff
was always a nightmare,
'cause, like, you can't get--
it's not like jumping into a mech
and shooting a bunch of stuff,
or even playing "Brütal Legend."
Like, so, you can't--
it's hard to really kind of--
I mean, now that we have--
that headphones are more common
and stuff, I think it's a little
easier to demo them.
But you're still, like--
sitting there for a while
being stuck on a puzzle is not
something that's fun to do,
and people are lining up
behind you to see the game.
Petty: The big problem with this
whole thing, potentially,
is that we're gonna disrupt
all this--
we just spent
all this effort
getting everything
into a flow
that's going to unblock
our dependencies.
And so even doing
any of this work
is probably going to
disrupt that somewhat.
It's hard to say how much
until we look at that.
But, um, polishing the spaceship
to beta right now,
uh, I think would be
the absolute worst thing,
because we have so much
areas of the game
that have issues we've
gotta work through.
And people like myself
and Bagel,
some of the animators,
need to stay out ahead
or we're gonna get
exactly where we were,
where everything's blocked up,
and part of that happened
because of the last
trailer we did.
I mean, obviously,
there's an undeniable benefit.
It's hard to quantify
the benefit, is always the issue
with making these decisions,
right?
'Cause, like, well,
people get excited
and that generates goodwill,
but...
Schafer: Like, the two things
that I want spoil each other.
Like, showing really
meaty gameplay
and not spoiling things are,
like,
kinda mutually exclusive.
Rice: All right.
This is all good stuff.
Schafer: Except you're doing the smile.
You're doing
the "I'm really unhappy" smile.
Rice: No, I'm not! I, like--
Schafer: "Yeah, life's shit
like I thought.
Yep, that's exactly what
I thought life was like."
Rice: No, I mean, I've always
been about trying to, like,
figure out how we can do it
without disrupting.
But, uh, now we just have
to figure out what that means
for our PAX plans, so...
Schafer: I mean, in the end it's not even
about it being disrupting.
I really don't care about
disrupting Lee at all.
I mean, it's really--
that does--no.
No, I mean,
it's not even about that.
It's like,
if we really felt like,
oh man,
it was such a juicy reward
at the end of it, like,
if it was really, like,
that demo would really
turn people, like,
millions of people
into fans of the game,
like, I feel like
it would be great.
But I feel like showing
the spaceship to the press
would not necessarily convert
a whole bunch of people,
you know, um...
Petty: Well, that's what I meant
by disruptive: Is it worth it?
Because like you said
in the earlier episodes,
no one cares how well
a game is produced.
I don't think anyone cares
how well a game is promoted
if it comes out
and it's not good.
Schafer: The one--at least the one
discipline here
that we can agree no one
cares about is production.
Crook: You said both those things.
Schafer: I don't remember saying that.
Petty: But, I mean,
it's the same thing.
Like, good production/promotion,
if it's not--
if we--you know, I want it
to be as good as it can be.
Rice: It's just a hard--like,
it became a lot more important
with all the press shit
that went down
'cause, like,
now what does it look like,
oh, suddenly we're taken
off the floor map of PAX
and we pulled out of PAX?
Like, that looks bad.
Schafer: That's 'cause I thought someone
was gonna throw acid in my face.
You can say that:
"Tim was worried about acid."
Rice: But, yeah.
Petty: Okay, but then
what if we showed
a press demo that
wasn't totally polished?
Which is worse?
Giving 'em ammo to hate on?
I think that's worse.
Schafer: Honestly, I--if I could
do anything right now,
it would just be
sit out this PAX.
Rice: Yeah, we--
Schafer: I feel like we just don't--
Rice: I think we might have to
if we don't do a demo.
Schafer: I don't know if--
can-can we, now?
Rice: We'd probably have
to pay for some stuff.
Petty: We could have
a kickass merch booth.
Rice: Uh, yeah...we could do that.
[Music]
Bagel: Uh, I think it's going good.
It's pretty rad.
I think we've all, like,
gotten a lot better at art,
you know, over the last year.
So lookin' at all the old stuff
is, like, kinda hard,
but we all see stuff, I think,
that we know we wanna change.
And, um, it's getting to
an exciting time right now.
Uh, it's polish phase,
you know, just figuring out
what we're gonna polish
and just lookin' back
at all of our old stuff
and bringing it all together
into an awesome game,
you know?
But, yeah.
I feel like it's goin'
pretty good.
Pretty exciting,
but it is also super scary
that we only have, like,
what, four months left.
Right?
But, yeah, I'm gonna go--
I'm goin' out to San Francisco
on the 16th of September,
and, um, I'm gonna be out there
for two weeks,
and we are gonna, like,
talk about polish,
figure out a plan,
and then just start nailing it.
[Music]
Schafer: We've got some professional
voice in the game now.
You can hear--uh,
and it's awesome,
'cause they're good.
Black: Oh, my!
A fresh face rises from below.
Before you ask,
let me answer.
Yes, you may live here
in Meriloft forever.
Rice: Yeah, it's one of those
things that, uh...
changes, uh, the production
values of the game
in a very short amount of time.
Like, 'cause it
kind of all comes
in at once,
in one big chunk,
and suddenly you
go from having
very non-professional acting
to very professional acting.
And it--and it just, uh...
I think it just reminds
you it's real.
Schafer: A huge difference.
It's--it's huge.
I mean, we've been looking
at these temporary cut scenes
for so long where
the characters are all moving--
'cause they don't wanna put
a lot of work into it
until they have the final VO.
Now that we have the final VO,
they can just go to town.
And so we're gonna see, um,
a whole different
game experience
where it just feels
so much more polished.
Rice: And in a game that's so much
about character and story, um,
like, it's gonna be
really important
that that is sold correctly
and those actors
are selling it right.
So, you know,
Tim's an awesome writer,
and now to have, like,
people who are able
to take what he wrote
and, like, even make it better
is pretty amazing.
Schafer: And "Act 1" of our game is now
in alpha, which is exciting.
[Offscreen] Woo!
And--woo!
But it's lookin' good.
Rice: Cheers.
[Music]
Schafer: It's gonna be fun
when we can actually, um,
celebrate, you know, shipping.
And--but it'll be kind of sad,
'cause it's been kind of fun
to do all this and...
[Music]
I'm not gonna celebrate
till the whole thing ships.
I suppose we'll have
some sort of celebration
on shipping "Act 1."
Then I'm like, don't talk to me
until it's done.
April/May.
April/M--
Definitely between
April and November.
Depends on how many
the first act sells.
If it sells a lot, we'll just go
all the way into 2016.
Just kidding.
[Music]
Kaufman: Okay, that's all we can do.
We're pulling out.
Don't make the same mistake
you did last time, boy.
I-I don't understand.
What is it about this creature?
Brown: Excellent.
Schafer: Let's throw in for the fans--
edit together the lines
to make a big dirty, like,
"Spock and Kirk having sex" video.
I like to put stuff
in there for them.
"Pull out now, boy."
Brown: I just...
Schafer: "Think about baseball."