Rice: Whoa!
You must have just been off it?
Remember how buggy
all of this used to be?
Those were the days.
[Music]
Schafer: And Act One of our game
is now Alpha, which is exciting.
And, whoo!
And Nathan "Bagel" Stapley is
here in town for two weeks.
There he is, Mr. Stapley, Bagel Stapley.
They recognize you by your hats.
Stapley: Thank you very much.
Schafer: Yeah. No one can still
pull off trucker hats except for you.
It's awesome. And wait, why are
you here, Bagel? To paint?
Stapley: Oh, yeah. Talk about Beta.
Schafer: Beta.
Stapley: Polishing and Beta-ing.
Schafer: Awesome. And we, yeah,
we finished our last one week sprint,
which was finish up Act One
as far as Alpha-ing goes.
And then we're starting on
some final polish for some things in Beta.
But it's looking good.
Gardner: And the family
starts getting a little nervous.
And then we have this
like big dramatic like...
Lee: Dave you were
saying to me earlier
you think we needed a separate
scene for that little shot there?
Gardner: This background, yeah.
That's a separate.
And I have a spot in mind for you to put that.
Schafer: Holy shit!
Gardner: So here's her,
there'd be like a shadow coming
over her and she's starting to get scared.
Now like I think what would be really
cool is like for that sequence to kind of be quiet.
And then when we cut to her, she
gets excited and the crowd is like, whoa!
Like it's Mog Chothra!
So like, and we'd cut to like the threshing ocean
and like the dripping and the effects
are all totally going crazy here.
Schafer: Blue whale falls off of it
Gardner: And the crowd is just like totally,
there's going to be the laser eye
goes bshhhh, and like shines on her.
And that'll be a pulsating laser shot.
And she starts kind of like going ooh,
like I like the way it's dancing off my skin,
the color, you know, like she starts
getting really excited about it.
Like, and then we do the shot
where the tentacle comes in.
That's a little long; I'll
cut that down and then smash!
What do you think if I did,
look, here he is, without the,
without her even being onscreen.
It could be cool.
Schafer: We could even start with
her and like cut to that during the line.
Here could be like, look, he's
so majestic, even more than we were told.
Gardner: Yeah, that's perfect.
Schafer: People clapping over there.
Gardner: Awesome.
Schafer: And this scene
where nothing is happening...
Gardner: This is the one where
the laser is shooting at her.
So actually this one would
be cool if the laser's on her...
Schafer: But it could be,
that could be when these
two other maidens are saying this.
Like she's already said, see,
he's drawn to this flame like a giant moth.
And you could have this moment
of suspense before he eats her,
where they're saying,
offscreen, kind of quieter.
Wait, no way. Please, no.
He's going to eat me.
Gardner: Yeah.
Schafer: And the team is kind of working on
finalizing the first half to get that to go out.
And so I'm kind of in
this mode of a little, it's panic
but it's in a good way because
you see the clear delineation
of how much more time you have.
And that's all you get to work on
and it'll be taken out of
your hands when it's done.
So you really have to prioritize
when you look at everything,
'cause you could, you could
mess with everything in the game
and just dink around with it
and polish it and do all this stuff.
But if you can only do like out
of the 50 things you could think of doing,
you only can do ten of them, then you're like OK,
I got to fix the ten most important things to do.
And that's nice in the way that it gets you to
really focus on what's important about the game.
So I'm in that mode of like thinking,
if I can only do ten more things
to make the game great, what can I do?
Petty: I think we're going to
repaint those maidens' faces anyways,
but you know, at this point if Bagel
and I were to list all the
things we want to repaint,
it'd be the entire game, every
character and we obviously can't do that.
So if like there's one that's featured
prominently like that candle maiden,
then we should for sure hit it.
But if we're not going to cut in
close to the rose maiden,
then I don't, probably don't want to touch it.
At least it'll be lower in priority.
Schafer: Cool? Exciting.
Petty: It's cool.
I think it's really going to
help to get that thing in there
and get all those little bits polished.
It should really hopefully give
Mog Chothra some actual weight.
Stapley: Thanks, guys.
Gardner: Easy peasy.
Stapley: Yeah, now we're going to like polish,
like tons of draw overs and tons
of notes and tons of things just to change.
And yeah.
Like all the art's in there.
And now we just have to like push it
and pull it to make it more awesome.
Stapley: Is it weird having him in the middle,
is it bad for the game play to kind of
like have him in the middle of the scene?
Petty: He's off to the side, what do you mean?
Stapley: I mean like, I don't know,
it is just because of this,
I mean it's like I'm looking over here all the time.
I mean, I know we could put
this foreground shit in there,
but it'd still be like, errr.
Like if he was just taking up the whole screen...
Petty: I don't think that would look so good.
You're going to be staring at
like no depth or fidelity.
Stapley: Yeah, I kind of like that, I don't know.
Stapley: Oh yeah, totally, totally.
I think there's a thing with, just consistency.
Making it look like it's a
cohesive piece, you know.
There's a lot of things that
you can tell who painted what and
I don't know I'm bothered by that,
or if anybody cares about that,
but yeah, that's one thing that
I want us to put like, see.
Stapley: Also that egg is fucking huge over there.
Schafer: This one?
Petty: You don't like variation of egg size?
Stapley: I do like it.
I like variation. I like variation.
Schafer: No, no, no.
But does it, but is it jumped out?
Petty: So there's a small bird with
an extremely large egg-laying area.
Stapley: A huge butt.
Schafer: Say it. Cloaca.
Petty: Cloaca.
Petty: I was trying to get Tim to say it first.
Schafer: Massive Cloaca was
the original name of Brad's game.
Stapley: Cloaca? Is that what
eggs come out of birds?
Schafer: That's the uni-hole.
Petty: It's the uni-hole.
It's there for procreation and defecation.
Stapley: Oh my God, that's crazy.
Petty: I don't think I've ever worked with an artist
who wouldn't spend infinite time
polishing the smallest detail
if everything else being equal, you know.
So there's like just artist
tendencies to want to do that.
And you have to do a certain amount of it
for the game to be meaningful
and be beautiful.
But then you also have to keep in mind
all the other things that we have to do,
you know, playability and just
what the overall experience is like.
And that can be difficult to keep
your eye on towards the end of a project
because your head's down, trying
to go through all your lists of stuff.
But you have to kind of look around you, too,
to make sure you're not just polishing
a corner that no one cares about.
Petty: If you had to pick
one scene that is visually,
you think overall works the best
and maybe one that works that least.
I just want to get a,
Rice: Shellmound's my favorite and I think Meriloft,
the main is my least favorite.
Petty: Yeah, I think my least favorite
is the Cloud Colony main as well.
I would agree with you guys.
Petty: It's kind of a tricky scene to kind of balance,
but that's what we're going to
try and do without changing it too much,
just because there's a
lot of stuff hooked up.
Stapley: It's definitely spotty
right now, spotty as shit.
Petty: Yeah. There's four exits
and three focal points.
It's kind of an overloaded scene
from that standpoint.
Stapley: And that big hole's super-distracting.
Schafer: It's also weird how solid
the cloud looks right there.
This little horseshoe.
Petty: But yeah, that's what
we're going to try and solve.
Stapley: Yeah. This is like the original one.
And you see this big thing right here?
I don't know what that is.
I don't know why I put it in there.
I have this thing that's like kissing
the edge of this frame, which is also weird.
It takes your eye over and
you don't want anybody
to be looking at the very corner of the page.
All this contrast, is basically just
showing off this shape,
which is like not really that important.
I think the important thing is really kind of right here.
So we're like experimenting with it.
I don't know if this is totally there yet.
It seems a little dark down here.
But just playing around more with like a
better composition-type kind of like,
so your eye goes to the places that we want it to go.
Petty: It's just like anything.
You can have like a painting
and it's all about focal points
and where you're drawing the eyes.
So you can have a beautiful
corner, but if that's not,
the painting's not about that corner
then it's actually more of a distraction
even though it's executed really nicely.
And games are the same way, right.
There's all these different elements
and you don't really ever see it
fully put together and understand
how it all flows until the end.
Because then that's the only time
you have all the information,
or at least more of it, about
where the emphasis should be put.
Schafer: But we planned out things,
I mean, we've already polished a lot of the spaceship
and we're starting to polish Vella's world a lot,
so I actually feel really good in that
we've already done a lot of polish on the game.
It's not like you'd play the game,
it doesn't seem like a wreck
and oh my God, how are we
going to pull this thing together.
I mean, I definitely see the art
getting more and more polished.
It's just hard to look at it
and see if the game is fun
and making sure that that
fun is getting more and more fun.
That can only be found out by play-testing.
Rice: And so Tim and I and a couple
people have doing a lot of play-testing
with people now finally actually
sitting down and playing the whole game,
which has been super exciting
and super informative.
We've been making a lot of new
bugs and tasks and things out of that.
But it's just nice to see like
people being able to like sit down
and actually just play the game
as if it was the final game, you know.
You can actually like start from the beginning
and you have the actual
whole like start sequence.
You can switch between the
characters, you can play all the way
through those stories up to
the part that we're shipping in January.
Kipnis: Yay congratulations!
Rice: You did it!
Schafer: I've never watched any
of our adventure games be played
in that level of detail, like sat
behind someone and watched them play.
In the old days we would have one pizza orgy,
which was like a big play-test session
with all our friends and relatives
where they all talk into one big group.
Kind of like that HOF that we did.
But these were actually
just watching someone.
And watching what they
do with the cursor, like oh,
they put the cursor over the
right spot but they didn't click.
Why didn't they do that?
And, or they'll, the object
you want them to touch is here
and they'll go all around the room this way.
And like, what are they doing?
Why are they doing that?
That's so crazy.
And just noticing when
they're tapping their fingers
and when they're, you know,
laughing and all that stuff is really fascinating.
Rice: Yeah, we've kind of
had a little cadence to it,
so it just started with people
internal who are really kind of into,
to adventure games specifically.
Just because they'll be a little more keen
to kind of understand what's
the goal and what they're trying to do.
Remo: I like that the ship design
is like very interlocking.
Like I still don't go to the like
most optimum way every time,
because I don't always remember
where everything goes,
but I feel like I'm starting
to actually understand the space
and how it's spatially connected, which
is a really good feeling to have in a game.
Kipnis: So what are you
trying to get accomplished?
Remo: I mean, I, getting out
of range of the mom arm
when I'm trying to get to the boom arm.
And then get the weaver
to go to the correct location.
Kipnis: What is that for, though?
Remo: Save guys, I don't remember. Sorry.
Yeah, I can't remember offhand.
Rice: Now we kind of started opening
it up internally to more people
who don't particularly play this kind of a game.
Sullivan: Yeah, I could maybe,
should come around the side?
Gollaher: How do you do it? Yeah, exactly.
That's what I'm trying to figure out.
Sullivan: I don't see any
like connection back here.
Gollaher: So there's, yeah,
but there's a path up there.
I don't know where else to go.
Sullivan: Me, either.
Rice: But now we, after that, we kind of
had to start moving to people external,
which has been fun, too.
Just because even people who
are internal that aren't on the team,
like you know, they see stuff on people's monitors
or they hear things around the office,
that could like sway the data
that we're getting from them a little bit.
So it's good to get people
who are just outside,
know nothing about the game,
to come in and check it out.
Schafer: Gaijin Games is right across the street
and Mike Roush came over with
one of his coworkers and tested the game.
Roush: It's pretty immersive.
It freaks me out.
Schafer: What's that?
Roush: It's so immersive.
Like I just, I was, just found
myself just zoning out in the world.
Schafer: That's acceptable.
Schafer: There's another layer
of baggage, of course,
when you bring in another developer,
'cause you want them to like your game,
because you know, and think
that it's better than their game.
That's the main goal.
You want them to go away,
going God, this game is so much better.
Well, I told you my tip.
One of tips I learned is whenever you
feel like saying the word "jealous",
just say inspired.
And you'll sound like a much
more positive, healthy person.
So I'm always really inspired when
I look at other developers' games.
Peck: I've never done that
much play-testing before.
Just watching someone play
an adventure game.
It's really, it's really like
taxing on your concentration
to not just be like, ohh, you know, like.
There's a lot of, there's a lot of
down time mentally for the player
when they're just kind of like
going from one hotspot to another.
Yeah, I did an internship at EA
and that was very different
because I was working on like
this racing game on the Wii
and they would do a lot of testing
kind of either offsite or out of sight from me.
I would just like see a report from somebody
that they'd written up after they had,
you know, I imagine gotten like
a bunch of teenagers off the street
and paid with pizza to play
the game for like a couple hours
and they videotaped them
that was, it doesn't really, obviously
doesn't compare to like actually
sitting on a couch behind someone
and like watching them play the game.
It's a pretty amazing experience, actually.
It's like watch someone play a section
of the game that you, that you scripted out.
It's really exciting and frightening
and you learn a lot.
So yeah.
It's been a pretty positive process, I think.
The game's definitely been better for it.
Roush: It's put a lot of questions into my mind,
which I think is really awesome,
'cause it's like I kind of
wasn't trusting mom a little bit
and now Marek, now I
don't know if trust him.
So I kind of feel like I don't know,
it's like I'm playing as an innocent little kid
and I don't know what's going on.
And you know, in the first hour
I feel very connected to him.
So that's, I think that's really huge,
'cause I want to be connected
to my character in a video game.
The part with the train and the avalanche,
I did kind of feel, that was
like the hardest for me.
I was kind of starting to lose
a little bit of interest, whereas this,
I'm just like, I want to fucking go
to the next place and see what's going on.
Schafer: That's the toughest,
that's the toughest one because in my head I was like,
OK, there'll be this routine for the boy
and he'll be stuck in it and
the puzzle is to get him out.
So that means if you're
stuck in it, it's getting repetitive
and if you want to get out, that
means it has to be kind of frustrating.
And so when people say like I
found that routine really frustrating
'til I broke out of it, is that bad
feedback or good feedback?
Because it's almost exactly the
way I'd described I wanted it to feel.
But when someone actually
says it to your face, ooh,
it's really frustrating, that part.
Like you don't want someone
to feel frustrated with your game,
but that is what you were going for.
Rice: I do think it was pretty good.
It was one of the better, I think
the thing we still need to talk about,
though, is like what happens if
they wouldn't have gotten out there.
If we have any plan for long, long term stuff.
Schafer: We could do, yeah, that's the thing, now we could add a failsafe
for like pick whatever we think
is too many missions to go for.
Rice: Yeah. Like I wouldn't have wanted to go
much further than where they were.
Schafer: So as long as it
was a good kind of frustration
where they knew there was a way out
and they just had to figure it out
and then they did figure it out
and then they felt smart and that's good.
[Music]
Schafer: We did all this play-testing
and we took out a bunch of places
where everyone was getting stuck.
Then I was worried that we
were making it too easy,
so we went back in and took out
some of the hints that we put in.
And now we can test it again and
make sure we didn't make it too hard again.
So it's kind of a back and forth thing.
But it had me thinking about Act Two.
That Act Two definitely has
to be harder than Act One,
that only makes sense, right?
Your player is more advanced now
and you're used to like these kind of puzzles.
We had to kind of step up
the complexity of all the puzzles.
And I was thinking it was too simple.
So I'm looking at the chart again.
Nice chart, huh?
Two colors.
Offscreen Voice: That's Act Two.
Schafer: That's Act Two in a nutshell.
And that final picture at the bottom,
looks like two testicles?
That's actually the climactic
scene of the game.
There I sketched out the first shot of
the game, that's the last shot of the game.
I just want to make all my changes
to the second half that I'm going to make now,
'cause to make them really work,
some of them might have to be pre-,
like set up in the First Act.
So they don't just appear out
of nowhere in the second Act.
Things are going good.
I mean, this January thing is real.
When we first split the game I was like,
we'll just say we're splitting
the game to make Justin happy, you know.
But we really will find a way to just
not have to split the game later.
But as the more, the closer we got,
they were like, well, I think we
really have to do it, so we...
We're definitely splitting it.
[Music]
Min: All right, let's do this.
Stoddard: So moving on,
I'm going to give you guys
kind of a broad view of the game.
We're going to kind of skip
around the scenes and stuff.
[squeaking, sci-fi sound fx]
Stoddard: All right.
This is the hillside.
Min: This just looks amazing.
Correia: I love this right here.
Min: Yeah.
I could be here for an hour.
Min: Yeah, it just looks amazing.
Correia: And I actually dig the music.
To me, it has a Zelda vibe to it.
I don't know.
Min: That's a good thing, I assume.
Correia: To me, it's a great thing.
Min: I'm glad it passes your test.
Honest, it's fantastic.
Everything sounds great.
I did hear like discrepancies
in terms of volume.
So obviously we have mixing issues,
where like the wolf was
way, much louder than Shay.
Correia: I just think all the
dialogue in the game is too loud.
Min: I'm not worried about the loudness
as much as the relative volume
of the dialogue with other dialogue.
Correia: Yeah, yeah. Relatively, yeah.
Min: So it's like, yeah...
O'Rourke: I noticed like a few
lines, it's not like overall.
Min: Yeah. And that's probably
just a general task
once everything is done,
you know, that we spend, I'd say,
a few weeks even to get basically,
you know, nuance each one of those lines.
Because again, that's the star
of our game, is the dialogue.
Correia: But the dialogue's
everywhere, stepping over everything
so like you could have
great sound designed,
but it seems like half
of it's getting cut out,
just 'cause of the
ducking and the dialogue.
Stoddard: The ducking's very sensitive.
Correia: Ducking's aggressive.
There's dialogue over everything
and so the sound aside everything
else has to kind of sit with it.
O'Rourke: I think that's kind of like a compromise
we make in an adventure game.
That little bit
Correia: Yeah, yeah, exactly.
So with that like slider,
because it's so heavily dialogued,
like the dialogue has to be perfect over say,
having like the best...
Min: It's definitely going to be challenging.
And this is one of those things, I think
we can sell to the production team easier.
But from the looks of the way
the game has gone, it's just,
it feels like it's just demanding
this triple "A" attention, you know.
To us, it's really challenging because
we just don't have a triple "A" budget.
Stoddard: I'm definitely going to
be asking for some help from you guys.
Like the reverb template stuff would be huge.
The Foley thing would be enormous.
O'Rourke: I'm in.
Min: Let's get some lunch.
Thanks, man.
This helps a lot.
I've been like going out of my
mind trying to get this thing...
O'Rourke: And then we just all jump
into a freeze frame, right, for the end?
Stoddard: Go team!
[Heavy stepping sounds]
Min: So we are tracking Foley.
Like I think, I still think it's
very important that even though
you're very, very limited in your
budget, it's important to take the time out.
We can't do everything.
We can't do Foley for everything,
but on some of these kinds
of things that the player hears a lot,
which are footsteps, we try
to be very specific and custom.
And then I think that's important.
So even if you're super on
a shoestring budget,
you can see we can do things in some office.
Not the best acoustic treatment or whatnot,
but we try to track those things
organically and I think that has a lot of value.
So yeah.
Stoddard: But yeah, that's, that's been the cool
thing about working on this game,
is 'cause like it just covers a lot of ground.
There's a lot of stuff going on.
And Pete and I have been
having discussions about that,
'cause he called me up and he was like,
you know, I played through the game.
I'm like seeing what Tim's trying to say
and all the coming of age stuff and he's like,
I don't know what cereal he was eating,
but this is like insanely good.
And like he's like, I'm going to have to
go all over the board with music.
McConnell: So here's everything
we're doing in two sessions.
It looks like a mess, but it's actually,
here's the cues prioritized.
Here's the amount of time that
actually the sextet has to record.
And then that's translated into how
much session time we can afford for each cue.
And hence this.
It's very simple, you're just you know,
playing a couple notes.
We just need to get them, we just
need to get it all happen.
McConnell: We put down all
the small ensemble music
for Broken Age on track, on tape.
I always, I still say tape.
I still say records, too.
[Music]
McConnell: Like this story is so
wonderful because it's so complex.
It's, you know, it's not just, oh yeah,
the young people know everything
and the old people screwed
up the world, you know.
No, it's not, it's not quite like that, is it?
No, the young people don't know everything.
Maybe the, maybe the grownups have
been through some things, you know.
And yet there may, they've made
terrible mistakes and I think that,
that is really fun to engage musically.
McConnell: I don't know
much about Part Two.
I've been told things, you know.
I've been told, you know, that
there's a, I've been told a rundown of it
but honestly, what I've been told
I don't entirely understand right now.
And you know, I think that's, I think that's really good,
because the score is going to discover
what Part Two is when Part Two happens.
[Music]
McConnell: That was janky.
I think we have that in an earlier take.
McConnell: It's a, it's a real score
for a real, for a real story.
I think it's, it's kind of a
labor of love for everybody.
I think it's really, really what it gets down to.
It's this, you know, people get excited
about, about working on a project
and you know, in this day and age
the people who you happen to run across,
who get excited about working
with you and you're able to,
to put something together with them,
might be on another continent.
[Music]
[Orchestra warming up]
Pogson: Yeah, so this was,
this was pretty exciting.
I guess the interesting thing about
the MSO being involved is the fact that
I'm actually a Kickstarter backer of the game
and I was well before I'd ever spoken to Peter
and well before this project
came on our radar.
Pogson: Really all of Tim's games
and certainly Peter's scores
are pretty much all of my
favorite games from my childhood.
They're games I spent huge numbers
of hours with my friends playing as little kids.
So much so that things like Day of the Tentacle
and certainly later on things like
The Dig and Grim Fandango
and all of those old
LucasArts games, we used to act,
when little kids playing around playgrounds,
we used to sort of almost
act out the puzzles.
So for me, those LucasArts
games are a real nostalgia trip.
And they just really remind me of those,
those days when we were younger.
And then I was watching one of the backer
videos and saw that Peter was mentioned.
It actually wasn't far before
any of the episodes about
Peter really being involved.
But I thought, oh, wow!
Peter's in this, which makes
total sense because him and Tim
have worked together for a very long
time and I hadn't really thought about it.
And I sort of thought, you know what?
I wonder if there's an orchestra recording there.
So I had no idea whether they
were having a proper orchestra do it.
Obviously I had access to an orchestra.
Conductor: So good morning, everyone.
Thanks for being here.
This is for a video game.
We're working with Peter McConnell,
a composer who's in L.A.
and he's on the line now and
we'll be talking with him as we go.
Upstairs we've got Hai, Chris and
Nick and we've got a fair bit to do.
So that's enough talking for now.
We're going to start with
SM03, Shellmound Battle.
[Music]
McConnell: Love that tuba.
Pogson: Stop there, mate.
Turn back to trombone and tuba
and move ahead there.
We've just got to go with the one note.
McConnell: Perfect.
[music slowly builds in intensity]
Pogson: I really admire any
game that puts music, you know,
as a really important element of the game.
There are so many games, even really big budget ones,
and some of the biggest budget ones,
where you can just tell that
they haven't used real musicians.
Yes, they're very high quality samples and so on
and perhaps there are people
who don't notice the difference.
But I always do.
And I think the really great
part about this is that,
I'm actually very proud that we're able to bring that,
that full orchestra palette and that
authentic sound to a project like this.
And I think Peter was very,
very pleased as well because talking to him,
it was always a dream of his to be
able to use a proper orchestra for this.
And, but didn't think it was
going to happen and now it has.
And I think it's important to me, as a backer,
as well to have that, that level of quality on there.
So it's great.
Should be good.
[Music]
Conductor: Thanks Brett.
Thanks brass, woodwinds.
Thank you. Fantastic.
McConnell: I cannot believe we got that.
Stoddard: Awesome.
Anything else.
McConnell: No, let's get a beer.
Stoddard: This is the Shellmound Battle.
[Music]
Gardner: It reminds me of Goonies.
It's like that.
It's like Jaws, but by Elfman.
[Music]
Ryken: That's what they're going to
play when we get the Game of the Year.
Rice: That one's so good!
Gardner: Amazing.
Stoddard: The only other one we have...
Gardner: I still wish all the animation
was done before you guys,
Stoddard: Well, that's what's
happening with this one.
This is for the final scene, which
I think Elliot's working on right now.
Stoddard: Basically, the symphonic recording,
live instruments and pro voices
all like happening at the same time,
which is creating quite an amazing bottleneck.
But it's also kind of communicating
with Tim and with production
and with the animators,
because a lot of that stuff is
still being worked on visually.
Crook: I've been doing all the play
blasts for all of the spaceship cut scenes,
so that we can have a meeting with animators
and you and go over what we might want to change
before we move into final animation on those.
Offscreen Voice: My name is Marek.
And what I'm about to show you is no game.
Schafer: What are those hairs?
Marek: There will always be war.
We did not start it.
Marek: What we can do is protect
the weak and rescue the helpless.
Schafer: I think the animation
of the wolf is hilarious
and it's great but it's a little out
of character for Marek.
Like Marek is so somber and serious,
but when he's like putting his arm around him
and like it seems really jovial
and stuff like that.
And Marek is like this, I always
saw him as more just like super-intense,
brooding, like intimidating
kind of guy, like that.
Like he's a little too chummy
in this, especially the beginning of it.
Crook: One, just, tear runs down Dave's cheek.
Gardner: I mean, part of it
is that he's supposed to be
selling the boy on this whole deal,
that's why I was trying to,
Schafer: But he's not selling him like, like hey buddy.
He's not like Bruce Campbell,
like he's not, I don't about Bruce Campbell.
But like he's not like,
he doesn't have that kind of charlatan
sounding salesman-y tone to his voice.
And it's not, like his character.
He's more just like,
Gardner: Can I see it again?
Schafer: Are you good enough
for this mission kind of like.
He's got a coldness to him that I think...
Gardner: I really hate to lose all that, like stuff.
'Cause it's just, I don't know, I'm happy with it there.
Schafer: But it's a little too goofy.
I would say overall the whole thing's
a little too goofy, so I feel like it all,
it needs a sombering pass on
the whole thing, you know, for sure.
Just to make his character correct.
Gardner: I could cut out the
like arm over the shoulder part.
And I think we should cut all this stuff out.
Marek: There will always be war.
We did not start it and we cannot stop it.
Gardner: As much as I don't
want to do that, 'cause it's amazing.
Schafer: I think it's all great, but let's get one thing clear.
I think it all totally needs to be changed.
I do think it's a totally wrong
take on his character.
That's what I'm saying.
So we, so I don't want to just kind
of like do a couple tweaks here and there.
I think, we have to understand that he's supposed
to be cold and calculating and a little scary.
And these make him seem really friendly,
like now you've met your new best
friend, which he's kind of like not there yet.
Like he's not,
Gardner: I mean, yeah. OK.
Schafer: Were you here that day that
I had to tell Dave to reanimate that scene?
That was exciting.
Schafer: Oh, good.
That's like one of the worst
or hardest parts about
doing like a creative collaboration with anyone.
You have this great artist and creative
people from different disciplines
and they'll do something that's
just amazing and everybody loves it.
And by itself it's a great work of art,
like that piece of animation
or a piece of music or something.
But then you go like, but that
doesn't fit into this larger thing.
That is wrong for the thing that
I'm trying to do with this bigger thing.
So take that, all that work
you did and throw it away.
That's the worst part about it,
but you kind of have to do that
or else you have everything
going in all different directions.
Schafer: So, sorry.
It all was really cool.
I'm just here to take out things people like.
Gardner: It'll, it'll, like we'll have it,
like I have a movie file of it,
so like ten years from now
I can be like, look how wrong Tim was.
Offscreen Voice: Did you guys fix this yet?
Gardner: Yeah. We're good.
Gardner: So you can see this is a long cut scene.
Four thousand frames long.
Straight through all of it.
Basically I just, you know, cut out a ton of stuff, put the wolf standing there.
And then I send it over to Super Genius
and then they add all the like minor flurries.
So it's, it was, like luckily that character
and the acting that we were looking
for is easy to sort of refurbish,
which is also great because we
were like, we were talking about
how those big other scenes of this,
like I need get onto those things.
Crook: We're supposed to be locked
down on our timing on all of our cut scenes,
which means Lydia can take it to do visual effects
and Camden can take it and do sound effects.
And so timing lock is supposed to be done by then.
Except for these, the scenes that
we don't have the dialogue for.
So I think Tim's going to go down this
week and record some more dialogue.
So, but you know, I mean, we have plenty
of other work that's, that has dialogue.
So I wouldn't say that's, that's,
we're waiting for it, you know.
It's kind of a good excuse to have.
Oh, it's the dialogue.
We used that excuse for a long time with Tim.
He's like, now you have your dialogue.
Schafer: So I'm going down next
weekend to record Shay and...
Rice: This weekend.
Schafer: This weekend.
Schafer: Next, this. Right?
You guys are coming down?
Yeah, it's going to be a party
in the studio and record Shay.
But we're very excited to announce
Elijah Wood is in the game.
I can now say that out loud,
because we've got the rights to
announce Elijah Wood is in the game.
It's not announced yet.
It's totally not announced yet, so don't tell anyone.
Schafer: So look at that.
Elijah Wood follows me, nice.
Sweet. Anyway.
Actually, the very first data point in this whole thing,
data point is a thing we use around
the office when we want to sound smart.
So the very first thing that happened was years ago
I read in Entertainment Weekly
an interview with Elijah Wood
and he said his favorite video
game of all time was Monkey Island.
And I was like, that's great, because
no one ever mentions, you know,
he was talking about it like it was a work of art
in a way that people don't usually talk about video games,
especially back then in the
public, as being works of art.
And I was like, that's so nice!
He must be an adventure game player.
And since that, and it turns out it was true;
he was an adventure game player
and he tweeted about Broken Age.
He'd seen, he'd gotten wind of the Kickstarter
and gotten wind of the whole project.
And he tweeted about how great it looked.
And I thought, that is awesome!
Brown: Were you thinking for the boy,
were you thinking of like asking Elijah Wood for that?
Schafer: That'd be crazy if we did that.
Brown: Well, you could listen to his
voice and see what you thought.
Schafer: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Brown: 'Cause I don't know if you
guys have any kind of relationship at all.
Schafer: Just on Twitter.
I mean, I would love it but I need to, I don't know.
I don't want to get my hopes up in case he can't do it,
but also I want to make sure that that
voice would be the exact right for the boy.
I bet he could do it.
He's a pro.
Schafer: And I was like, oh God,
that'd be crazy if he would actually be in the game.
That'd be crazy.
But I don't want to like, you know,
I'm having fun with him
just being interested in the game.
That's fun enough.
But like ah, I don't want to ruin it by asking,
but I was like he's, would you, this is crazy,
but would you, would you ever
want to do a voice for the game,
like a little cameo or maybe all
the lines for the main character?
Schafer: I just got a direct message from Elijah.
Rice: What? As we were sitting here?
Schafer: Yeah. It says Tim, I sent you a,
I sent an email to Izzy at
WME to inquire about the game
and told her that I'm a huge
fan and I want to be a part of it.
Rice: Yay!
Brown: Bull "S". For real?
Rice: That's what he said.
Schafer: That's the truth.
Want to see it?
Brown: That's f-ing awesome; I'm freaking out.
That rules.  He's super sweet and adorable.
Schafer: Apparently he's the best.
Brown: Everyone who's worked with him, loves him.
Schafer: That'd be great.
I hope it works out.
Brown: He watched the documentary
and is talking about the poop thing.
Why is, that's going to be my legacy.
That's horrible.
Wait until you hear the hilarity here.
Wood: Rice Krispy Treats.
Rice Krispy Treats, dudes.
Schafer: I asked for those.
Could you please...
Wood: Do you want like, do you
want it to be more conspicuous,
like underneath the sweater or
are we just like, fuck it, man?
Schafer: We are just like, fuck it.
Wood: Yeah, yeah.
Here's the game.
Wood: Ahhh!
Schafer: There's Shay.
Marek: It is not time to deploy the rescue system yet.
Wood: Is that Marek? Schafer: Um hm.
And there's our scratch dialogue.
Wood: Tim, this is great!
Schafer: You can tell he plays adventure game all the time.
He does.
Wood: A lot of experience.
Schafer: We don't want to give any spoilers out, though.
Don't play too much, you'll,
Wood: Wow, this is awesome.
Amazing.
Schafer: OK. Cool.
Schafer: And he was totally
into it, it was really great.
Because he obviously played
a lot of adventure games
and from the very beginning we're like,
this is a page where you're going
to say a lot of kind of nonsensical things
and he was like, oh, you mean like
this is where you use every single item
in your inventory on a character?
And you get a bunch of dumb
responses, not dumb responses,
but he knew exactly what adventure
games were like to play,
so he knew how to read the lines.
And it was one of those great
experiences where he got every joke
and he made them all funnier.
Wood: Do you know how to repair hexapals?
That sounds like a "no".
That sounds like a "no"?
Schafer: I'm sorry.
Are these Rice Krispy Treats gluten free?
Brown: Don't ask him that!
Wood: I don't know, actually.
Schafer: We're thinking they
are, 'cause they're rice.
Wood: I think they are.
Schafer: It's very thoughtful of you.
Wood: You're welcome.
Schafer: Is there anything he
won't do for you, Khris Brown?
Brown: I love him.
Schafer: He spends a little bit
too much time doting on Khris,
that's the problem with him.
He loves Khris too much.
Brown: Whatever, jealous.
Schafer: I know, I'm jealous of you.
But then I got the Rice Krispy Treats, so.
Brown: Well, I'm watching my waistline...
Schafer: Can't eat them on camera,
though, 'cause they think I'm on a juice diet.
Brown: What?
Schafer: I'll eat it behind this napkin.
Brown: Here's what happens
when you're on the juice diet!
Wood: My name is Shay and this is my
life on the incubator vessel, Bassinostra.
Schafer: He added something to Shay
that I was worried we wouldn't have,
because Shay has this kind of character
where he's irritated by his computer,
for being overprotective and so he's
kind of like acting really over it.
And then wants to go on a really
big adventure of his own that's real.
But that could, if it's done wrong,
come off as a really kind of
whiny, irritating character,
like waaahhh, like he's so over it.
Like a jaded character.
I thought that'd be irritating.
But the way Elijah read the character,
he's very empathetic.
Like he's like, he seems really warm
and just like he is just frustrated
and kind of pushing against
the restraints of his world.
So I think he just added a depth
to that character that wasn't there.
Or wouldn't have been there if
we hadn't had an actor of that caliber
doing the role.
Wood: So it's time for a mutiny.
Time to put aside childish things.
Time to grab the wheel of this ship
and steer it straight into the storm.
Schafer: Ah, Red's, we are announcing, some voice,
we're announcing Elijah at the
VGX Awards this Saturday
and then we will be having all
our VO will be final for Act One.
But we are working now on the
finalization plan for everything that's
going to happen to make the shipping
of Broken Age in January go flawlessly.
The flawless execution...
of Broken Age.
We're working on a step-by-step plan
that has not been circulated yet,
I don't believe.
But it's what you might expect
if you're on the Broken Age team.
There's a whole bunch of stuff to do.
Oh God, a schedule, oooh.
I hate when these sneak up on you.
We're in the middle or starting this spaceship Beta for art.
Sugar Bunting Beta for animation and
gameplay programming is
already on space Beta.
Rice: Yeah. The dates that we're
aiming for currently are January 14th,
I believe, is the backer ship,
which is Levi's birthday.
That's how we planned it.
Yeah, so then there's also holidays
that are in the middle of there,
which will also prove...
Schafer: And then four days for the Dead Eye God and the Pyramid and the...
Rice: And the forest, yeah.
So those are the tricky ones for sure.
Gardner: There's so much animation
that needs to be polished still.
I mean really.
Crook: Well, well, there's a lot that's,
that's done but it's just not in.
Somewhat slow going but,
Schafer: OK.
Does anyone want to say
anything about the schedule?
Like how easy it looks?
Petty: So let's say we do address the feedback
that we have on Sugar Bunting to get to Beta.
Like everything's in it.
And then also enough on space boy,
spaceship to get that to Beta.
Or maybe we slip a little bit.
I guess what's our plan if you know,
if we do say we get to the end of this sprint
and there's clearly some outstanding
things on spaceship
that we haven't yet reached?
How do we prioritize that versus
Shellmound, which is up next?
Because if we keep going on, we're
going to be cutting into what
we're calling bug/fix/polish time, but
really that's just bug fixing time.
Because the programmers can't
guarantee a stable game
if they have like two weeks of bug fix.
I mean, that's nothing.
Petty: Coming to a head is one way to say it.
Wrapping up nicely and elegantly is another.
And yet a third way is, crash landing a plane.
I'm not saying either of those is appropriate.
Gardner: The way that we've been doing
stuff, we kind of slip a little bit
and I'm worried that we're just going
to keep slipping until the very end.
Rice: Yeah. And I think that's why it's good to have
this kind of picture of the rest of development here,
to where we know like the 14th and
the 28th are the days that we're looking at.
So that's the time we have to work with.
And I think just trying to prioritize and weight things
to where we're making the most of
that time is going to be the challenge.
Petty: And I guess my interpretation
of looking at schedule is, that sort of,
we need to have a much more
structured definition of arbitrary polish
to that date or we're never going
to get the game's bugs under control.
And you know, I'm sure there
are categories that are simple.
It's not like we're going to leave
a missing animation
or someone locked in a "T" pose, right?
Like that's clearly a bug.
But you know, if I really liked to
have that plant waving in the background
or it's not quite as polished as,
or the composition's slightly off
in this one frame, well, I think
the ship has sailed at that point on that stuff.
Unless there really, unless it's incredibly low risk
and there's nothing else that's prior priority.
Rice: But yeah, there's a lot
to do in the few months left.
Rice: There's just a lot to do and
everyone's kind of aware of it.
So I think people are just really
trying to push forward right now.
Yeah, it's about two months
'til we're saying pencils down
and total bug fixing mode.
But I would imagine that people will
start pulling longer hours and you know,
trying to get every last bit of polish
into the game as possible.
Crook: We just realized we have
a lot of work still ahead of us,
so I'm just, you know, at night
I can, I kind of focus on animation.
I don't have to answer questions
or run around, which is fine;
that's what I'm supposed to do during the day,
but it doesn't let me get a lot
of the tasks that I have on my list.
So it's just, it's a, you know,
it's a process that everything's
sort of by hand, you know, still.
It's a craft that is, you're still sort
of hand building things, you know.
It's not really a production line.
And those things take time.
So, but that's what makes the job fun.
That's why I like Double Fine,
'cause we still do that.
You know, we still sort of do things by hand.
But you know, it can also make it hard.
Schafer: I feel bad for Ray.
Ray's a family man; he shouldn't
be staying here late.
But he is.
So I say no, no, don't do it.
Although I totally rely on him to do that
so the schedule actually makes sense.
Schafer: This footage would be better
if I made this into a metaphor,
like the way that car turned out
to be a perfect metaphor,
but you know, making a game is
a little bit like decorating a tree.
You take small ornaments from a box,
you hang them on the various branches.
The branches are a metaphor
for the backers, who hold up.
The ornaments are the sound effects.
And lights are the voice actors.
See how that works?
Now do you understand game development?
[Music]
Schafer: It's loud, isn't it?
Wake up, everybody!
It's exciting, though, isn't it?
Don't you love that smell?
I'm just worried that a paper wad will get shot off,
like that guy who got killed in Voyagers.
It was a similar thing.
Yeah, there's a paper wad stuck in the...
[Loud pop]