Offscreen Voice: Tomorrow,
how's it going to play out?
Schafer: We're going to, let's see,
tomorrow, come in here, push the button,
there's a big plastic button
in the middle of the room.
We all push it at the same time,
put our hands in and then push it.
We totally should have that.
That'd be much more dramatic
than like Greg sitting at his desk
and Chris and then they tap
and then they're like, OK.
It's off.
But that's the way it's going to go.
[Music]
Gardner: There's so much animation
that needs to be polished.
Crook: Well, well, there's a lot
that's, that's done, but it's just not in.
Somewhat slow going.
Schafer: OK. Does anyone want to
say anything about the schedule?
Like how easy it looks?
Rice: But yeah, there's a lot
to do in two months left.
Schafer: Where's the warmest
spot in this, in this office?
Crook: Just snuggle up to me.
Crook: This sweater and,
Schafer: Oh, wow.
He's so warm in there.
Look at you, you look
like a longshoreman.
Crook: I was so cold yesterday.
Schafer: You're like a lumberjack,
like a lumberjack by the sea.
I just need to be by Anna's heater.
Schafer: Hey,
is this thing even on?
Kipnis: You want it on? Here.
Schafer: Gather 'round
the fire, everybody.
Rice: We each should have a little fire.
Schafer: Hello. Is everyone here?
We'll have him, quick. OK, anyways.
Hey, everybody. What are you doing?
Mr. Petty, what have
you been working on?
Petty: What we're doing up until,
for the next couple weeks
is getting all the new content
and, which I think in art,
there's very little new content.
It's mainly us repainting
and polishing and refining.
Ryken: Yeah, we're coming down
to the wire but it's going good.
I'm working on little fix-y things.
Things that were painted really crappily
and are now, I'm in the time to polish up.
Schafer: Bagel's right here.
Ryken: Yes, yes.
I'm fixing,
Petty: You better be referring to other work.
Ryken: I'm fixing the things
that Bagel's "fixing", right now.
Ryken: We're just getting
down to the point where,
[Offscreen Voice]
Ryken: What?
Ryken: Oh, look at that! That's crazy.
Didn't I just do that. Petty: Yeah.
Ryken: He's so fast, man.
You have the rim light working on him?
Man, maybe I'm just slow.
Petty: In some cases
we're repeating characters,
because now that we see
like the range of what they did,
like we repainted a Mog Chothra,
Levi did for like the third time.
And part of that is because
his presence in the game
was much bigger than when
we originally painted him.
And the type of stuff he needs
to do for like the boss battle
or for these other areas
is a greater range of movement
and a lot more close-ups
and has various mouth states.
So the best thing to do is like
sometimes you can keep patching asset,
but sometimes it's best to
just go, wipe that clean.
And we know exactly how it's
going to be used now, just repaint it.
So that's pretty much what we did.
And it'll pay off, because
he has a lot of screen time.
Ryken: Yeah, we're not
as pressed as the animators.
We kind of just listen to them,
working their ass off over there
while we kind of just pretty things up.
Gardner: Today I'm trying to get this
scene in, 'cause it's such a big one.
It's going to be a series of
like four different cut scenes
that we put together in the game.
And like none of those
are in the game right now,
and that's like,
really close to shipping.
So it's like this last, bit of time.
Just like every other department,
we're all kinda just like
rushing through everything.
Choy: The animation, like overall,
like animation just has more work,
but a lot of times my time
is compressed into like the last,
like couple of weeks that I can do work,
because I come after everyone else
and like I guess, right before audio.
Stoddard: I'm finishing all the sound
in two weeks. Schafer: Yay!
Stoddard: I'm going, I'm basically following
the animators as closely as possible,
because I'm trying to jump on all the cut
scenes as they come in and like do them.
Schafer: Ray's like,
good luck, 'cause we're so fast.
Stoddard: I'm trying to save January 6
through 10 to mix the game.
I'd really, really like to
have that time to do that,
so I'm trying to get in as much as
possible in the next two weeks.
Choy: Kind even Camden and I had a lunch
where we were kind of talking about like,
OK, well, we're here at this stage now
where everything's
supposed to be wrapping up.
Like what do we do?
Like what's the social fix for it?
And like part of me's
like, oh, you know,
like I'm just going to be
really like irritable all the time
and just like be really hard,
kind of hard to like work with.
So like if people want to make
changes they'll be like, oh my God,
did I piss her off even more?
So like this, like some of that,
like there's like you kind of
have to be a little bit of a wall,
otherwise like, just so people,
not necessarily to like stop changes,
but just so people will
like kind of think twice
or like maybe think smarter when
they want to polish something.
Schafer: So it's a little tight.
This means more late
night food for free for Ray.
See, so it's really saving Ray money,
'cause he's going to stay
late to animate all this stuff.
Rice: And this is just a bunch of rice.
Crook: You see, this is the size.
Schafer: I've been doing
a lot of press stuff.
We went down and showed
the game at the VGX Awards.
Did you guys watch?
It was fun.
I got a lot of love
on Twitter from that.
And a lot of people who hadn't heard
of the game before were just crazy,
because I always assume the entire
world knows all about the game.
But I got this like, what is this game?
This looks kind of cool,
this is awesome.
Keighley: This is really exciting,
'cause this is a guy I've loved for so long
and we now have him
live on the VGX stage.
Not you, Joel, but
Tim Schafer is with us!
Tim Schafer!
Tim is of course the creative
genius behind Brutal Legend,
Psychonauts and Grim Fandango
and his latest is the Kickstarter
funded adventure game, Broken Age,
which raised over three million dollars.
McHale: Three and a half million, Geoff.
Schafer: Thank you.
Schafer: He's funny. He's nice.
He was nice to me off camera.
He was like, hey, get ready for this.
I'm going to ask you if you were
high when you designed this game.
McHale: @Brandon
Victoran asks, hey, Tim.
What was the
inspiration for the project?
Schafer: Well,
McHale: Did you get high or something?
Schafer: Uh, no, no.
McHale: Sorry.
Remo: It's been getting really tangible,
how excited people are to play it.
Like it's been very visible and
you can really, you can really feel it.
So it's very, very exciting, like
we have a big list of stuff to do
to get the game out.
You know, Greg is
obviously driving that stuff
so it's going to be
pretty crazy few weeks,
but I think our community is
going to be incredibly enthusiastic.
Is going to, and really
help us get the word out.
So it's really good times.
Rice: I think that there's
going to be a lot of excitement.
Like I think we've been
doing some bigger things,
like VGX and stuff that's been
building up, you know, hype.
And I think that ultimately the people
who are going to care the most about
the game are the 90,000
that already bought it
and they're going to be
super-stoked playing it.
So I feel like there's going to
be a huge ripple effect from them,
of them just sharing their excitement.
I think that that'll just be
something that we should
try and capitalize on
as much as possible.
Bailey: the big splash,
so you're thinking?
Rice: Yeah, well,
I just think that yeah,
they've been waiting
15 years for this game.
Bailey: There is the counterpoint,
just so you know, which is that,
that all the adventure fans
are really interested in this
and it's a very small market and that's
why most publishers got out of it.
Rice: Yeah, I know.
Bailey: So those fans have
basically already backed the game.
Rice: Yeah. But that's what we're
going to prove wrong, right?
Bailey: You're going to
prove that wrong, OK.
Rice: Everyone is a skeptic.
Bailey: But it still could, it can
be somewhere between it, right?
Where is the genre, is say,
you know, 500,000 people.
Rice: Yeah, I think that that's where
the quality of the game is going to be,
ultimately makes a call.
Like I think if it comes out
and reviews really well
and people have a really great
experience and are talking about it,
I think the game will be able to kind of
live on through really solid sales.
You know, if it has
kind of average scores,
then it probably will
be a different story.
Schafer: Broken Age is
a welcome return to
the graphic adventure
games by Tim Schafer.
See, I can't read this,
it's got my name in it.
Schafer: We hired some
old friends of ours
who are game reviewers
in the previous life
and asked them to write
a review of Broken Age
as if they were actually, just got
a copy and were reviewing it.
To know, you know, is there some
big thing we have overlooked or what,
what might a review
look like for the game.
And they came back really good.
Positives: intuitive point and click interface,
good balance between exploration,
character interaction
and puzzle solving.
Game recognizes when players
are stuck and provides clues
without giving them answers.
Negatives: I missed the inventory command
and the opening with Shay and the spoon.
Phfft. In the gaming industry
mock reviews are a common thing.
We have never done our own,
so that's the good thing.
It's like a part of what we're trying
to do is being a real self-publisher.
You know, being your own publisher
is taking care of these things,
which are like mock reviews,
'cause they affect how much or how
you plan your launch, you know.
Like you would plan, if we got really
like, if the mock reviews were like,
ah, it's kind of rough,
but they'll probably have it sorted out
by the time they launch Act Two.
We might think that wouldn't, we'd
be inclined to put it in the early,
early access section of Steam, you know.
But if it came back, oh,
it's super-polished and it's great.
It's like a first episode of something,
and that means it really should be
in the other section of
the Steam, with regular games.
Schafer: No.
I mean, Microsoft did play tests
for Psychonauts and people were like,
it got like fun-ativity
ratings or whatever.
And oh God.
Is that what this is?
Schafer: Here's the marketing document
that Microsoft made for Psychonauts.
Based on the twelve focus
groups conducted worldwide,
the primary weakness of
the game are the story line,
which is considered unoriginal,
childish and overly complex.
Tongue-in-cheek nature of the game
is a weakness, most simply did not get the joke.
Others disliked the satirical humor.
In addition, many feel the humor
would get old limiting replayability.
Humor should be incorporated
into the game as a
secondary or supporting characteristic.
Humor should be simplified
and made immediately apparent.
[Laughter]
To help international appeal,
limit game components
that feel especially
Americanized, i.e. summer camp.
Thank you, marketing research.
Yeah. Limit, so you can
obviously take this stuff too far.
I mean, good God.
Thank God we got cancelled. Anyway.
That's not what we're doing this time.
This time we just sent it to three
reviewers that we knew and asked them
to write reviews, just as if
they're writing actual reviews.
As mean as you would have been.
If you've ever loved the Tim Schafer
game, if you've ever loved whimsy,
you will love this game.
I'm glad to see the return of the
genre and the return of a legend.
See why I can't read these?
That's just embarrassing.
But it's good.
Yeah, there's no like, like it was
always problematic near the end of Brutal
to hear the recurring
stuff about the RTS stuff,
'cause that's really hard,
like what are we going to do?
What the crap,
what are we going to do?
And EA was like,
we're just going to, it's good.
We're going to ship it how it is.
But here there's nothing
about the quality of game.
It's more about, we have to hit the
pricing right and we have to make sure
the puzzles are hard enough,
especially in the second act.
As pricing will directly affect
the overall Metacritic score
breakdown of price to Metacritic
score has been included, see page 8.
For the purpose of this summary
will assume a $15 to $20 price point.
Oh, I don't think that's
what Justin's assuming.
He thinks if we charge $15,
we'll get 80-85 Metacritic.
If we charge $20, we'll get
79 to 80 percent Metacritic.
Charge $25 to $30, we'll go to
70 to 60 percent of Metacritic.
Interesting.
Schafer: That's just him saying,
I mean reviewers, I guess,
take into account how much a game
costs when they give it a score.
So it costs $60, you know,
like geometry wars.
If that cost $60, you might give it
a lower score than if it cost $15.
Schafer: We don't know yet.
That's the whole discussion.
Bailey: I know it's happening.
I just kind of disagree that
that reviewer should take in,
price into consideration
when making this review.
Rice: Yeah, well, especially now
since price fluctuates so much.
In the sense things go on sale so
often and prices change and go down.
Yeah, that's a tricky one.
Bailey:  And so I saw, when I, I did my
research so like it showed that indie games
can be anywhere from
like $2.99 to about $29.99,
as like the acceptable pricing.
There was one for $34.99...
Rice: What was that?
Bailey: Well, it was the Monkey Island
one that came out, that Telltale did.
Rice: Of the Telltale,
Tales of Monkey Island, yeah.
Bailey: But I'm going to
treat that as an outlier.
It'll be like, OK.
The idea would be on
release you would pay $24.99
and then you get both
acts, Act One and Act Two.
Bailey: It is a small genre and those
games used to sell, like the Grim Fandangos
and you know, Full Throttles and
stuff, used to sell like 500,000 copies.
You know, there were the hundreds
of thousands where there were.
And you know, that's one of the
reasons why if you can't sell, you know,
millions upon millions now,
you know, games are considered failures.
The good thing about us, is since
we're publishing ourselves, you know,
and it's digital distribution
and we can handle almost
all aspects of the publishing.
And so for us it actually doesn't
have to make a huge amount of money.
And 500,000 copies,
if it sells 500,000 copies,
we'll be enormously
successful as a studio.
That will supply like all the funds
we need to be completely independent.
Rice: Anyway, this is exciting.
So, cool, man.
Rice: Yeah, it's coming.
It's actually nice, 'cause
when these decisions are made
and you're just like committed to them,
then you just kind of sit back and
I don't know, watch things happen.
Bailey: Yeah, can you imagine?
What would it be like if we sold like,
if we sold like blockbuster
numbers for a publisher?
God, it'd be crazy.
Yeah. Don't know.
Bailey: No, I, it's, you know,
basically it's the studio's dream,
which is to continue to
operate independently.
Bailey: But like this is, the awesome
time, the awesome thing about this timeframe
is that there's not a lot
being featured on Steam.
So we could potentially, best case
scenario, like Max Paine, I think got,
they got a month
of a feature, basically.
If we could get that from the 28th
all the way through February,
that would be amazing.
Bailey: Are you OK with
that, rather than, I mean,
'cause I would love five
dollars more and everything,
but I didn't want like, I just don't want the game to be,
Schafer: No.
I mean, I feel like you guys
have talked it through enough
and I was nervous about it coming out at $30
and the mock reviews wanted it to be $20,
so I think,
Offscreen Voice: Split the difference.
Schafer: Is this a bad time
to propose not splitting the game?
Considered that lately? Wouldn't have
to think about any of this stuff for a while.
No, I'm excited about shipping.
I'm excited about it.
Bailey: I think this is
actually going to probably be,
I think it will result in a better showing
than if you had kept it all together.
Schafer: I think it definitely got
more people talking about the game.
Bailey: Yes.
But it's like, the more
opportunities you actually have to sell,
actually potentially better.
Schafer: Sell each puzzle.
I don't like this puzzle;
I'd like to return this puzzle.
Bailey: Micro transactions to adventure games.
Schafer: OK.
Bailey: You know you have the fun start,
about the build lockdown and timelines
for all the stuff that
needs to get done.
So when is the build, like
when are we done touching it?
Rice: Yeah. I don't know.
That's a question that I would like
to involve other people in, like Oliver.
Offscreen Voice: So you know,
what is happening at this point?
Franzke: A lot, a lot is happening.
Yeah, we kind of just switched into,
I guess what's often called finaling mode
where it's a lot of, I'm basically
going away from working on tasks
and more towards fixing
issues in the game.
Just so that we can maybe get a stable
version that can be released eventually.
Romero: That's a crash.
Yeah, you can press "space"
to skip the cut scenes.
So in this particular case, for some,
you just skip the cut scene and crash.
Yeah, we've skipped that cut scene,
I want to say thousands of times,
you know, collectively.
And now it decides to
crash for some reason.
That's really how
most bugs are found.
You're not trying to
do something, it happens.
What I've learned is that the nature
of the adventure game is that it's,
everything is very handcrafted, right?
You want to control every step of
the way because it's all story driven.
And because of that, you have
so many little points where it just,
there's a bad graphic
or the audio's off
or characters look weird
doing a particular action.
And because they want a very
specific type of sort of experience,
like to look a certain way
and sound a certain way,
you just end up with a lot of little bugs
in between all the big functional stuff.
So functionally, I mean, it's not
too complex, you know, point and click.
I'd say our save load system
is probably the most complicated
because save load's
always complicated anyway.
And at this point it's just polish.
Little graphics things, animation,
there's a lot of missing audio, stuff like that.
So this is the Broken Age database.
This is the list of all bugs.
This particular issue is going to be
for Oliver, which means it's a system bug.
And that's it.
Once you have all the detail,
the title, the steps, any attachments,
if you need them.
In this case we don't.
Submit the bug and off it goes.
Franzke: The QA team is very, very good
at like describing exactly how they got to
this and they even say sometimes oh,
this doesn't happen all the time.
So there's a problem in this particular
scene where the characters occasionally
will kind of, you see the jitter?
See, see how this
kind of like jitters? So OK.
So at first, the first thing I do, I will
actually look at the scene and you know,
try to see the problem like this.
Like oh yeah, obviously
that's something going on.
Then we have certain tools
in the game that we can use
to kind of just trying to figure out
what's, what's happening.
I can actually pause the game in the
auto-debugger that we wrote for the game.
And I'm going to, you know,
basically step through frame
by frame in this particular case.
And then I very often will
just look at, OK, so first of all,
do those numbers line up?
Because like, you know, the camera,
animation has to be at the exact same frame,
then the characters.
And I already see like,
you know, this set of frames, 732
and this is like at the frame 734.
So like weird,
why is this happening.
And then I basically will have to
go into visual studio where they'll,
you know, the code is for
the game, like animation control.
A lot of what I do is actually just
understanding what is going on.
Like that takes 95 percent of the time.
Once you know what's going on,
very often the fix is pretty easy,
but you know, since there's so
much code and so much things,
so many things going
on at the same time,
the understanding what is actually
happening is usually the way, way, way more
difficult part of actually
implementing a fix for it.
But yeah, I mean, that's like
in a nutshell what's going on.
Romero: And then on our end,
I just try to get to the tasks.
Like we have a lot of bug regressions
right now, just 'cause they're fixing quicker
than we can check them to make,
to verify that they're fixed.
So we always have just a backlog of
bugs we need to get through on that end.
And new bugs.
Like I said, don't stop.
So at this point you can't
afford to ignore any bug.
So you see it, you report it.
Yeah, every time you hear a little
groan or something coming from that end,
that's probably every new bug.
Franzke: I think animation is
winning the bug count right now.
And it probably will be until the end.
So a lot of it is just, you know,
animation polish and stuff like that.
I think they probably have
like twice as many bugs,
any of the other like departments.
Roberts: Yeah, and this
is all animation bugs.
So it's something like 130.
Essentially right now the red
ones are unfinished cut scenes.
And so that's what we're
striving to do by tomorrow.
They're set by priority.
And it doesn't,
it doesn't show it here,
but there's Pri-1, Pri-2,
right down to 4, I think.
Four would be like, it'd be
nice to have, but not essential.
And 3 is like we should fix it,
otherwise it'll look crappy.
And 2 being it is going to look really
bad and unfinished if we don't do this.
And 1 being a breaker, like it
actually just breaks the game.
Gardner: When you get
into bug fixing phase,
a lot of time animators
will be like oh, I want to,
like this is the animation
that we should be polishing,
but instead I'm polishing this animation
because this is reported as a bug.
It's stuff that I'm like, that should
be fixed and that should be fixed.
Nobody cares.
Like, I'm like, like
it's like high fantasy.
Like I'm really into it,
but like not everybody else is.
Roberts: What I'm really trying
to do is not get freaked out about,
about things right now,
because the holidays are coming up and I just want to relax and rebuild my energy.
And then come back strong.
We could be panicking right now and we probably should be panicking,
but I'm not going to do that.
I'm Zen right now.
I'm just going to, I'm just going to turn off
and then when I come back on the second,
that's, it'll be time to freak out for me.
Franzke: Again, I think the problem is to some degree,
it feels like the release day is far away, but it's really not.
Because it's like, oh, it's next year, right?
That's, you know, once you say that,
we're going to release the game next year, that feels like, oh,
that's so far away we don't really need to worry about it too much.
But I think in terms of working weeks that we have until the game ships is like
two or two and a half.
So it's really not that much time,
given the amount of issues that are being reported.
It's somewhat scary for sure.
So yeah, it's like a lot of people do tend to work, you know, late hours now,
starting now but then,
you know, also people
leave for Christmas break and stuff like that.
And so it's kind of a weird kind of thing going on.
Franzke: Say something or are we just standing here?
Schafer: Yeah, we're all going to stand.
Kipnis: What are we saying?
Schafer: Happy holidays, I think we say.
That's what the Christmas card says.
Well, I am going to say something.
Rice: And then we'll all say "happy holidays".
Schafer: This is all going in and out.
Hello, adventure gamers from
everyone on the Broken Age team.
We just wanted to say happy holidays.
Happy holidays? Happy holidays.
Hey. Get back to work.
Finish it, finish it.
Ryken: We had one little
portion of the tree showing,
so we had two little
ornaments that we put on it.
Their mind will fill in the rest, right?
It'll be like, hey, great job.
[Music]
Schafer: OK, hello, hello, everybody!
It's so nice to see you all.
Everyone here?
Everybody ready to go?
Hello, Happy New Year to you all.
This is the first meeting since
the new year began, right?
Yeah, yeah, welcome back.
I'm so glad some of you
survived the holidays and driving
and you all decided to come
work here for another year.
Speaking of that,
Bagel's actually been here 13 years.
[Applause]
Schafer: No, no.
No clapping, he's not here.
Sorry, Bagel, you're not here.
Yeah, you can clap.
He's actually coming up to visit.
Does anyone know when
he's coming out to visit?
He's coming here on,
Offscreen Voice: On his fourteenth year.
Schafer: And he'll be
here for two weeks?
Offscreen Voice: Until the 31st.
Schafer: OK, awesome.
So then you can clap for him then.
Let's talk about Red's for a second,
just 'cause it's launching next Tuesday.
To backers.
We are shipping this thing to backers.
And then on the 28th it's going to
go out to the regular rest of the world.
But yeah, this is exciting.
We have, we're all working
on the Bugzilla right now.
Everyone knows what they're doing
pretty much, so why are having these days?
I guess just to cheer everyone up.
Hey, you guys!
We're going to ship a game.
Rice: Now I think let's talk
about lockdown and stuff like that.
Schafer: And that.
So lock it down, people.
Rice: Oliver, you want
to talk about lockdown?
Franzke: Sure.
Lockdown, let's do it.
It's good. Right.
I mean everybody's
still working and I,
I mean I see like lots of
things still happening this week.
However, I'm, I am going to get
the release kind of branch ready.
Basically I'm going to manually
integrate changes into the,
like nothing goes into the branch
without, you know, me looking at it,
make sure that it's like, there
are no risky changes going in.
And like the amount of risk is going
to be reduced over time, for sure.
Just to make sure that the
build is as stable as possible.
So just like how we do
in the past for build days.
Like we basically going to just try to play
through the game and individual changes
that need to go in for the 14th,
they will be manually integrated.
Schafer: Talk to Oliver directly.
And you'll make an angry face.
Franzke: I will make angry face.
Schafer: Show me the face you
have to see if you want to add, yeah.
You'll have to look at that face
if you want to add anything
to the game after Thursday.
Franzke: Right now Linux
is driving me insane, but I'm sure,
she'll do all good.
But other than that it
looks pretty stable recently
and I would like to
keep it that way for sure.
Schafer: OK, great.
Any other questions?
All right.
Go check Bugzilla.
See you guys later.
[Music]
Crook: We're doing pretty good.
We're at final stretch
for the backer build.
So this will be a Beta build.
So it needs to be, not
completely bug-free, but mostly.
Last night I got home about 1:00.
I get home about 1:00 and then
I couldn't sleep for about two,
I just at in bed for two hours,
just like thinking about today
and what we had to get
done and it's just like, just stupid.
I got to, you know;
see my kids and my wife.
So yeah, I have an aunt that's visiting
right now, I haven't seen her yet.
She's been here for like four days and
I haven't, I literally haven't seen her yet.
Crook: Yeah. Camden's
getting hit probably the worst
because cut scenes come in,
you know, really late in the game.
Yeah, I think Camden has
stayed here a couple nights.
Stoddard: I'm having to
revisit a lot of things.
Things get redesigned or they get
polished and timing has to move around,
which is cool.
But there's a lot.
[Explosion sound]
OK. That's fine.
This is a hard, hard crunch
but it's more about getting it right.
And I've been on other crunches
where it wasn't about that,
it was about we got it wrong
and now we have to fix it.
I'm just here because I
know if Double Fine makes it
and really, really makes this
happen, it's going to be amazing.
It's going to be an amazing company.
I mean, it's already good, but
we're just like struggling for years.
And I think a lot of people here kind
of hang on because like they know,
they know Tim, they know,
they know the management,
they know the vision and
if it hits, it'll be really good.
It'll be really good.
So we're just hanging in.
Schafer: We are launching
Red's tomorrow, crazy time.
All of our backers.
[Applause].
Thank you to our
team for working so hard.
We are going to the backers tomorrow
and the rest of the general population,
future backers, if
you will, on the 28th.
Rice: Ah, we're about to launch a game.
In eight minutes.
I feel like, I feel like I'm kind of even
in the same boat as backers,
which is that's this, a really
surreal thing that's happening.
I don't know.
It's been a long time
in the making, you know,
it's two years almost now since
we launched the Kickstarter and yeah.
Sometimes it just felt like it
was never going to get here and
now it's here and you know,
this is something that really shouldn't exist.
Like it's crazy that this exists
and was able to be made this way
and that the game that we've
made is something that's coming out.
You know, I grew up playing
Tim's old adventure games, young,
like in elementary school.
And I feel like they were kind of the
games that showed me that games
could be like an art or could be
something different or something bigger.
And you know, the fact
that I'm here now,
like working on this
game and putting this out
is really a dream and the weirdest
thing that's ever happened.
And the best thing that's
ever happened to me.
So it's exciting.
Schafer: All right. I've got to call
my mom and say happy birthday.
Rice: What?
Schafer: I got to call my
mom and say happy birthday.
Rice: Oh, yeah. Do that.
Schafer: We're releasing our game today.
Yeah, well, it's,
it should go out at 10:00,
which is now so it's
going to be out there.
And Dad can help you download it.
OK, happy birthday, mom.
Rice: The game is up.
Preorders are up.
Schafer: Whoohoo! Rice: Yeah.
Schafer: All right, next game.
Rice: Yeah, we're going
to take everybody out.
So there's going to be a team
lunch today, probably drinks later, too.
I'm going out for drinks,
so I hope people will join me.
But yeah, we're going to
take everybody out for lunch
and thank them for all the hard work
and just take a nice breather
before diving back into Two Act.
Schafer: So thanks, everybody.
[Clinking glasses]
[Music]
Schafer: Hey it's Nathan Bagel Stapely!
[Applause]
[Music]
Schafer: This is downloading,
start playing now.
Let's hope you did a good job, Tim.
Me and my two girls
sitting on my lap, can't wait.
Sounds like I'd buy that for a dollar.
Played 30 minutes, very happy so far.
Thanks to you and the Double Fine team.
Rice: Yay!
Schafer: It's like send
any little bit of feedback.
OK, I need some more proof
that people are playing it.
Rice: Tim, there's Twitch streams.
Schafer: Well, I don't
want to watch that.
Well, maybe I do.
Oh, man. This is weird.
He's going to pick
avalanche, no, foreign body.
Foreign body, hull. Train.
Foreign body, oh! Avalanche!
That's good. Very good, avalanche.
Now I'm totally into watching that.
Schafer: What if he just said
something really crappy right now.
Computer Voice: All right.
Looks like that'll be it, guys.
Thanks a lot for watching
and if anyone who is watching
is involved in making this in any
shape or form, then congratulations.
I think this is a winner.
[Music]
Game Character:
I'm going to sit here forever.
Offscreen Voice:
But I don't know I need those yet.
Schafer: Because you
fell through the clouds.
Offscreen Voice: I don't know why
my character knows that she needs them,
'cause she hasn't heard any...
Schafer: She's just interested in shoes.
Offscreen Voice: No, that's not true.
Schafer: And she
fell through the clouds.
Offscreen Voice: The other guys
in there said that I needed shoes.
Schafer: Yeah.
Offscreen Voice: I don't know if I clicked
on that dialogue option, though.
Game Character: What
are you doing down here?
Vella: I'm an offering
for the Maidens Feast.
Schafer: She fell through the clouds.
Obviously she knows
she needs cloud shoes.
You're playing it wrong.
Game Character: Kind of shabby
looking for a Maidens Feast.