Cameraman: How are we going to
continue making this documentary
without spoiling anything?
Schafer: I don't know.
People know now if they've, hopefully
they're not watching this episode
before they finish Act One.
You really shouldn't watch this episode.
Should we you shoot that now?
Hi. I'm Tim Schafer.
Please don't watch this episode until
you finish Act One of Broken Age.
Offscreen Voice: Backers that play it,
or are you more nervous
about the money,
like how much it's going to sell?
Schafer: No. I mean, I feel
like it's tense about the money
because we want it to do well,
because I have big plans for Act Two.
And if we don't do well,
Justin will be like,
look, look, we can't,
we got to, you know.
Because basically, just spending our
own money from here on out.
And probably like a few months back.
So if no one buys the game tomorrow,
maybe Act Two will be a
much smaller than Act One.
I hope one person buys it.
If no one buys it, it's
going to be really awkward.
But I guess that's a good clear,
I can say that to the backers.
Look, nobody bought it,
except for you guys.
I'm sorry.
But it serves me right for
investing our own money in a game.
I should have just
played with their money.
[Music]
Schafer: We are
launching Red's tomorrow.
Crazy times.
All of our backers.
Thank you to our team
for working so hard.
We are going to the backers tomorrow
and the rest of the general population,
future backers, if you will on the 28th.
Rice: The game is up.
Preorders are up.
Schafer: Whoohoo! Rice: Yeah.
Schafer: All right, next game.
Rice: I will send the press release.
One of the reviewers
said he didn't go to bed.
Finished the game last night.
Remo: Finished it last night?
Rice: Yeah. Remo: Wow.
Rice: Yeah, I sent the codes at like...
Remo: Did he say how long it took him?
Rice: 4:00 or 5:00 p.m. Remo: Oh, right.
Rice: So I mean, I guess there's time.
But yeah, he just didn't stop.
That's kind of awesome.
Schafer: Man, this is weird.
People are playing Broken Age.
Seven people watching
him and I'm one of them.
I don't want them to
know this is what I do.
I've never done this before.
We've never been able to do
this before and have live streams,
like after Grim Fandango.
Remo: People are already
posting screenshots.
Bailey: I'm still waiting.
I'm just curious who's going to
be the first one to like post a review.
Remo: Yeah, right.
Rice: Tim, did you hear that?
Schafer: What?
Rice: Digital Trends posted an article,
"Why We're Breaking the Broken Age Embargo."
And how they're going to review it.
Schafer: Well, what
embargo are they breaking?
Rice: The review embargo.
They're going to put a review up.
Schafer: They're just announcing
they're going to break it?
Rice: Yeah.
Schafer: Why?
Rice: Because they paid for
the game and they're a backer.
And they're getting it
because they paid for it.
Schafer: But we, but they're not,
they're in the Beta...
Rice: They haven't reviewed it yet,
but Digital Trends, I know.
They emailed me about this yesterday
and that's what I told them.
Remo: Technically no one signed anything
so there's nothing we can actually
do about it now. Rice: Yeah.
Schafer: What do you think about that?
Bailey: I'm sorry?
Rice: Yeah, I don't think there's
anything we can about it.
Bailey: Well, unless we
have something in writing.
Remo: No, we don't. Embargoes
are not really enforceable.
Bailey: Exactly.
It's a professional...
Remo: I know, I know. It's a courtesy.
A professional courtesy, yeah.
Schafer: Well, maybe he didn't agree to
anything but he knows he's being a shit.
Schafer: It's like people don't
realize that everything's embargo.
Like every review they read
has usually been embargoed,
because your game's coming out and
people want the press for the game
to come up on launch day or
around that time people can buy it.
'Cause if it comes out before, then
all that energy, people see that article,
they can't go buy it.
So anyway.
You want your, you want to
time your press to that day,
but different reporters can
come in at different times
and they're like hey,
I want to, you know,
just because this guy
came in a week early,
does that mean his review
gets to go up a week earlier?
So you say it's embargoed,
so that all the press
has a fair chance of getting their story,
not getting scooped or whatever.
And they also have time
with the build to do a thoughtful build
instead of racing to
like getting it out early.
But we were going out to backers
and 90,000 people had the build
and I think most of the
regular backers were like,
OK, yeah, this is private information.
I won't spoil it for people
who can't buy it yet.
And the press understood it.
But there's kind of this grey area
of people between backers and press,
like a, kind of like a blogger,
you know, who's a backer,
who's like, hey, I paid money for this.
This guy's amazed to see
consumers suggest the press
should stick their heads in the sand
because Double Fine asked them to nicely.
For the evening crowd, the
Broken Age embargo's a bit of a joke.
Has anyone else contacted you
from actual news outlet? Rice: IGN.
Schafer: Do they want to review
it or just, what'd they say?
Rice: Yeah, it was just yesterday.
It's like I just want to be
clear on what's expected.
He says like I feel like
there's so many people
that are going to be having the game.
Like if other people start
running their reviews,
we're going to feel like we're
going to have to run ours.
That's basically what they said.
Schafer: Why don't we
just let the people
who are not being jerks
about it break the embargo?
Rice: We can't do that.
Schafer: And that would scoop all the
people who are being jerks about it.
Why, we can't do that?
Rice: I don't know how to enforce that.
Schafer: Just pick the ones
that are being nice about it
and just tell them they can.
Then one day later tell everyone else.
Rice: Yeah. I think that only
serves to inflate the issue,
because then they think
the embargo is still there
and then it's being broken
and then it's a mess.
So I think we have to,
Schafer: It's kind of a mess, though, I think now.
Rice: Well, then, that's the case and
I think we have to talk about lifting it.
And then I'm fine like,
I've been saving the list of people
I've emailed all the review stuff
so it would really be like a two second
Kickstarter update and emailing them all,
if you want to just totally lift things.
Schafer: Maybe we could just
open it in a couple days, kind of.
Rice: Just sit on it
for a second and see.
Schafer: Yeah. Rice: OK.
Schafer: God, that embargo's a disaster.
Schafer: And so because like one or two
people were threatening to like break it,
that all of a sudden made everybody
else who wasn't breaking it like a chump.
And I didn't want them, you know,
to feel, so we just like, look, OK.
We take back our request
that no one's, go ahead.
Post all the reviews and stuff.
So a bunch of our reviews went up
when people couldn't buy the game.
So that was kind,
it took away a lot of our,
like our press hit for the
launch day, which is too bad.
But it seemed like it was, it would,
we just couldn't, it was out of control.
There was just like 90,000 people,
even if like 80,000 of them
are totally like, yeah, it's cool.
But if like just a few
took one or two breaks,
then the whole thing just falls apart.
Schafer: All our backers are so cool,
but the backers who are in
the press feel a little differently.
They feel they have
the option to not be cool.
It's an awkward situation.
Next time we wouldn't, I think actually
have private forums for that reason.
Schafer: I mean, I feel in
end that I just don't,
I just don't want to have this fight
any more about private stuff and all.
It just puts, I mean,
being in this antagonist relationship
with the press is just not comfortable,
'cause you need them and they're
usually really good friends of ours.
I'm just getting mad at them one by one
for breaking the faith
of the backer agreement.
It's annoying.
Bailey: You know, one third
of our, of all the articles
that were written about Broken
Age were about the embargo.
And then another third were about us
going from early access
changing it to a regular release.
And then one third were
about the game. Yeah. So.
Rice: If we're saying backer Beta's
the 14th and public release is the 28th,
that would give the press builds
like the 12th or something.
And embargo them,
Bailey: This is an interesting one,
because I think this is the next one
that could lead to a PR blowup.
Bailey: Yeah. I was not
in favor of the embargo.
Rice: But preorders
are there like you said.
So people can still at least
go and get the preorder.
Bailey: So the preorders are,
they're less than we expected.
They are, we were hoping
that they'd come in higher.
If I had to project off the
preorders we received so far,
that would be a kind of bleak outlook
as far as how many we'd actually sell,
you know, for the
lifetime of Broken Age.
But I'm basing everything off if
different historicals for other games
that Tim has sold and none of those
have had this kind of Kickstarter story.
So this is definitely unique.
I don't think it's time
for us to panic right now,
but it puts a whole lot more emphasis
and importance on January 28th
when it comes out for real.
'Cause I think it will do well in the long-run,
but it's like how long is that run.
The other piece that I think
is kind of silver-lining
in all this is the reviews
are coming in really good.
You know, I foresee that the game's
going to have a great word-of-mouth buzz.
Most of Tim's games actually do.
And they have a,
it has a very long tail.
There're games, what
people call "evergreen games",
they keep on selling at a certain,
certain level and they just keep on,
which keeps on accumulating over the years,
which is different than most games.
Most games have that huge spike,
that hump, that six-weeks hump.
Tim's are different.
So that's one good thing to take
into account with all the good reviews
and all the social media and the
good word of mouth we're having.
You know, it's like we
can't get to a place
where we could sell
this game quick enough,
because that's where we're really going
to be able to see and project, you know,
what the success of
the game's going to be.
Rice: So the other thing
Tim was talking about is just that
now that we have to move the
embargo up and reviews are out now,
the idea of flipping the
switch on Steam earlier.
Schafer: Releasing it a, a week earlier.
Like next Tuesday.
Schafer: Sure, whatever.
and like, you know,
Schafer: Well, that's the question.
I mean, and there's, I mean
there's a legitimate business reason,
I think about it just
because it's out there,
it's getting a lot
of attention right now
and there's a lot of press
I'm going to do in the next week.
And it'd be nice if people, I mean can
go pre-purchase it, but they can't buy it.
Rice: It'd be nice to have a story
about the game being pushed forward.
Franzke: I voiced my
concern about this plan.
I mean technically it does
make like, like just looking at how
the long the things take, just
doesn't really make all that much sense.
Franzke: And you know,
I explained like that.
That we can certainly do it
but it will be very unadvisable,
especially considering that time
when that was first proposed.
We still had big problems with crashes
and people not being able
to play the game at all.
So that was my main
worry, that you know,
we were still like trying to find
the really big issues and so.
So we didn't feel like it
was ready to ship it then.
But I think now, basically I don't
think anything will have changed
if we final release it on the
planned day we had initially,
just because technically time-wise
it doesn't really work out
any other way, anyways.
Schafer: But it's good.
So now the official reviews,
now they are rolling in.
The great thing is that
they're all really great.
I mean, that Polygon one was
nine out of ten, which is great.
I mean, I would give it a ten,
but I'll accept a nine.
Polygon Review: Broken Age
may be unfinished,
but it's also delightful,
beautiful, utterly charming
and you really should
play it right this second.
Stapley: No, it's cool.
It's awesome that it sounded like,
that we all made an awesome thing now.
Like this is the cool part, you know.
Like we made this awesome thing
and now it's out in the
world for everybody to look at.
Rice: Yeah, I guess.
Stapley: OK. How many reviews are there now.
Crook: But it feels good.
And people seem to be
really responding to the game.
The reviews have been really good.
And even comments about animation,
which you don't get that often.
It seems like in games a lot of times,
maybe you will a couple of times.
But there's been several other reviews
that have mentioned the animation,
that they really,
that they really liked it.
And that's, that's rewarding.
Oh, yeah. Yeah.
I saw a nine today; that's nice.
But you know, I actually,
I feel kind of bad I don't really,
I try not to read a lot of the reviews
because the bad ones do
kind of make me, put me down.
You know, they kind of, you know,
when you're kind of on this
high that you've released it
and then suddenly, even though if
there's like six good reviews
and one bad one, that
bad one kind of affects me.
So I try not to read a lot of
the comments until a little bit later on.
Heatseeker Review: Broken Age gets by
on the strength of its storytelling.
The puzzles aren't particularly complex
or compelling with the exception
of a certain vomiting tree.
And serve as a reason to
explore the environments.
I can't say I recommend this to people
who don't already have
a fondness for this genre.
Compared to modern entries in the
genre like those from Telltale Games,
it may seem a little
simple or even boring.
Schafer: This is actually just
new posts, for new posts today.
Oh God. The guy wants a refund.
It's like, ah. This is a jerk.
I'm just going to say it.
This is a jerk.
Thanks for backing, jerk.
Franzke: You know, it's
unrealistic to expect that people
will be able to please
everybody, obviously.
Unfortunately very often the people
who are the most dissatisfied
are also the loudest ones,
you know, which can be difficult,
especially if you're pouring a
lot of effort and a lot of work
and a lot of your like,
like "soul's" the wrong word,
but like a lot of your personal
kind of effort into the game.
Like to see somebody come in
and like just completely smash it.
I did the mistake and I should know
better after so many years in games.
I think I went in Kotaku where they
had an article about the "Retro Mode".
And like one of the comments, and you
should never do that if you work in games.
Never read the comments.
Actually, generally don't
read any internet comments.
I scroll down and somebody
was like, this just look shit.
Like this is, you know,
here, here's a comparison
to a hand painted,
hand painted sprites, versus down-res
It's like, yes, obviously.
And then backers immediately jumped in
"Well they just put it in as a little add on"
Still the person was not
satisfied with that at all.
And then he's like, well, if you
were a backer you would see that,
you know, they just put in during
the weekend as a little side project.
I'm not a backer but this is shit.
I'm not going to buy this.
It gets, [throws hands up, exasperated].
Having said all that, overall
I think people are very happy.
I've got a lot of Tweets from people
who are super happy with the project.
On the forums people
are very happy, you know.
We saw someplace where some people
like really, really enjoying the game.
And like, you know, it's good
to see super-positive reactions
of somebody just like laughing
about all the jokes in the game.
And just generally like finding the
game very beautiful and stuff like that.
So it's good.
Web Streamer: Fuck yeah!
Web Streamer: I don't know!  Which one!
What do I pick!
Oohh.
Shay: This must be where Marek sleeps.
Web Streamer: So he keeps
the costume on while he sleeps.
That's funny.
Man, this is a genius
game, genius story.
Schafer: I'm super happy that no one
seems to have guessed
the big spoiler at the end of it.
I really thought that
was going to get out.
And actually long ago on
the forums, one guy guessed it.
And no one followed up on it.
Like no one, he just said his
little thing, hey, what if this is the case?
And no one answered him.
I was like, oh man.
I feel, oh God.
You know, I hate that guy for guessing it,
but I'm really, it's worth something.
We should send him some chocolate.
But everyone else has just had the exact
like experience that I was hoping for,
which is that they were
really like, oh my God!
I didn't see that coming, that's crazy.
Web Streamer: It's Shay!
Shay was controlling Mog Chothra.
Web Streamer: Uhhh, Shay?
Web Streamer: What the heck?
What the heck?
That's Shay!
Schafer: But they all seemed
to really be enjoying the ending.
And so I'm really happy with that.
And I'm really happy with people's
response to like the story, the characters.
And a lot of people, I think, will
actually appreciate the difficulty level
in the game once we get out of
the most hardcore part of the audience.
I think they'll like that,
that it flows more as opposed to
hitting a series of really,
really hard stops, for most people.
Schafer: I mean, you can tell
they already anticipated that.
After play-testing the first part,
I was like, I think this is a little easy,
but I think rather than just throwing
a monkey wrench, Monkey Island joke,
in there, I'm really focusing on Act
Two and making Act Two a little more,
instead of things being one step,
having them be a little more complex.
So I'm way ahead of them,
way ahead of them on that.
Petty: You know, I think,
yeah, it's interesting.
Like the, I don't,
I don't think I read anything
that I felt was unfair and it
all seemed pretty balanced.
There were, I think, you know,
there's some comments about
length, maybe a couple of them.
And that's kind of difficult,
because you know, I mean,
this was the same on Stacking.
You know, you can, you can burn
through an adventure game and,
and that can really shorten
your play experience.
But I don't know if that's the best
way to evaluate that particular game.
You know, it's not a game that has a
mechanic that just like is endlessly playable.
So it's a little, I don't know,
you know, it's just, it's just something
that happens with adventure games
that, I've seen that come up.
I don't necessarily disagree with it,
but I guess I don't know what
to say about it, you know.
But I think, you know, in some other stuff
is stuff that we discussed early on
that I've seen like, you know,
the lack of a verb coin or a verb page.
And I think that's just a choice Tim,
and I think the correct choice
Tim made early on, you know.
I don't think there's probably people
played Machinarium that also was like,
this would be better if I could have
a look and examine and verb link.
But I don't really feel like
the experience needed it
in any way and I don't really feel
like Broken Age needs it in anyway.
And I don't really feel like
that's where we puzzle depth,
mechanical depth anyways.
So you know, I mean, I wouldn't
oppose it if someone really, really, like
we had started the game and we really,
really wanted to take that approach.
But I just like the idea of you
know, I think Tim's initial vision
for the game would be like, well,
what if adventure games just kept going?
And we just were keeping it working.
We wouldn't keep making
the exact same thing.
We'd try and mess with the
formula and advance things
and I think that's what
we tried to do with visuals.
We didn't want to
make retro visuals, right.
We wanted to make visuals
that were 2D and charming,
but also took advantage of modern
methodologies and technologies and resolutions.
And I think the approach to the
game play is consistent with that.
And this is a choice.
You know, and some people will
want that exact Monkey Island moment
and some people are like, thank God,
the puzzles aren't that confusing, you know.
It's hard, it's hard to get the right.
Petty: So what I would like to do is
next week, since Bagel's out for two weeks
and I wanted him to come out at
this time so we could kick off Act Two.
So I would like to kind of, at the
very least, we'll see who has time.
At the very least Bagel
and Levi and myself
to start concept jamming next
week on early Act Two stuff.
And Tim hasn't delivered the
final design or dialogue yet,
but I already know
some of high level stuff
and then hopefully we
can get him to kind of,
I can kind of like mention all that
and he can kind of correct me
where he's changed things
and just get us going.
So there's definitely a new,
at least one new area
that has no presence at all in
the current act that we have to design.
And we had some very
early stuff on it from before,
but we haven't thought
about it in 18 months.
So we'll probably start there.
Stapley: So are these the only new,
this is like pretty much all we have
to worry, really worry about, right?
I mean, those only new things?
Petty: Well, this is the new
stuff we know about for sure.
So I thought we'd start there. OK.
So the thing that Tim, like
he's going to be here after lunch,
we can him some more questions
but the thing that we know for sure
is that we need a monster lands area.
It's probably also a good
chance for us to think about
where we want to go with,
you know, as we're developing him,
if we want to go anyplace
different with Marek.
Here's another concept
that we can think about.
Is we talked about, OK,
what Alex's is.
And originally Tim kept
saying, well, it's, oh,
this'll be a copy of
Mog Chothra to save time.
And I was saying, well, that's not
really going to save us much time.
I mean, it'll save a week or
so of production time, but...
Stapley: It's got to
be like older version.
Petty: Right. Like it's been buried.
It's not going to look the same.
I'd love to see it like
a previous generation.
Because when we
were starting to draw like,
I don't know, maybe, like some
of these older ones or whatever,
like remember we
had all those ideas like,
oh, it's got diamond-shape
eyes instead of hex eyes.
Ryken: Yeah, just
like changes with times.
400 years, like, oh yeah, but then
he came around to hexes again.
And then it went away
for another 100 years.
Petty: We added two
sides to our windows.
Stapley: That's awesome.
That's always the best.
Like in Star Wars,
you're like, well, that's R2D2,
but it's a fucking red
R2D2 and it's like different.
Awesome. I always love that.
Petty: Well plus it would be cool,
too, like this one doesn't have,
it's been buried for however long
so it doesn't have to look
as purely organic, you know.
Like we're not, we're no longer trying
to make people believe it's just a monster.
So being able to see some combination
of the mechanical and the monster...
Ryken: Yeah, like the outer hull is just
like ripped away and most of the parts.
Stapley: But it'll still be the same
like rig kind of set up, right?
Petty: I mean, it could
be whatever we want.
Bog Chothra.
Stapley: Bog Chothra?
Bog, I like that one.
I like Bog.
Ryken: Just Bob.
Stapley: Bob Chothra? Awesome.
That would be fucking sweet.
Stapley: All right. Should we
call Scott and get pumped?
Stapley: Yeah! Look, whoo!
Hey, bro, get us pumped up!
Get us pumped up!
We're all like, boo, drawing is stupid.
He still in bed?
Campbell: Chilling on the couch.
Stapley: Oh, man.
Campbell: I was just, I was
just watching Triplets of Belleville.
Stapley: Oh, sweet, dude.
Campbell: What are you guys,
what are you guys doing?
Stapley: We're doing an art jam, dude.
We're doing an art jam and
nobody's pumped up and like,
like nobody fucking
is as psyched as you.
You got to get us psyched.
You know, when you and Peter are
here, you guys are like, ooh, ooh, ooh!
So come on, bro, do it, go for it.
Ryken: We need some art cheerleading.
Campbell: Get psyched, man.
What are you guys
working on? Tell me about it.
Stapley: All right, check it out.
Rice: What are you doing?
Stapley: Monster lands.
Uh oh, look who it is.
What, tall man.
Petty: Scott!
Stapley: Yeah, we're all
getting pumped. OK, cool.
This is one monster, man.
Schafer: Who are you talking to?
Hi! Scott Campbell!
Hi! Everybody's at the art jam.
Stapley: I'm excited to hear
about what we're going to do,
because, 'cause I know
that we all like, this is like,
not really trial and error but
I got pretty much trial and error.
You get closer to the end, everything
started working really smoothly.
So you know, it's going to be
way better for sure, you know,
'cause we learned so much.
But I'm, I'm actually excited to see
how we take all the things
that we learned, trial and error-wise
and try to get it, you know,
see what happens with the next,
how organized we are, what we learned.
Schafer: OK.
Stapley: Those
are the new things.
Schafer: Monster lands and the gate
Stapley: And there's only the
pollution inside like the kingdom.
Schafer: Don't film his armpits.
Stapley: Oh God, are they like, oh God!
Fuck. It's horrible.
Hey, bro.
Schafer: Aren't you glad
you're not here right now?
It would be nice to get the main
characters some different outfits,
just to make the game feel...
Petty: So would she put on a space suit?
Schafer: I see her with the radiation
suit and I don't know necessarily if he,
I can't think of, I haven't
thought of a puzzle.
What?
Stapley: He could be in a cake dress.
Petty: We should do a transgender thing
where he starts dressing like a girl,
'cause he gets the maiden,
leftover maiden's outfits
and she dresses like a boy.
Schafer: I mean, he could put
a druid cloak or he could,
but he could put on
a preener outfit.
remember we have those artworks,
you had him masquerade
as a preener for a while.
He could possibly have to do that.
I just think it would be
more fun for the player
to have them look really different.
Petty: He needs like a
traveling cloak or something.
Piece it together. Yeah.
[Music]
Franzke: Other than
doing some concept artwork,
nobody has to get started working
on the second act anyways,
so a lot of us are still working
on bug fixes for this release.
And it's, you know, it's incremental
update to the backer release.
So you know, I'm really optimistic that
this is all like minor fixes to be put in.
But we're pretty solid, solid release.
Peck : We are
investigating an issue with
the track pad on Linux for
laptops with track pads.
There's a little issue there.
A little oversensitive, you might say.
Franzke: You make a change and like,
oh, it works on Windows
and then you go into Linux.
Aaah! Gosh, it's broken.
What the hell is going on?
Franzke: It was good to a
have Beta release for sure,
to kind of find a lot of issues
and all the things we ran into,
we were not unprepared
for, but we didn't expect.
Like a lot of Window compatibility
issue than we expected, for example.
And you know, that's
why I have those guys here,
like we had a lot of
issues with compatibility,
so we ordered a lot of
graphics cards just to kind of,
trying to reproduce some of the
issues that users were running into.
Franzke: Oh, this is what
compatibility is all about.
Finding really, really old hardware
and putting in your machine
and see what happens.
Franzke: You know,
where here in the studio
we didn't really have any
problems running the game
and like our external
QA partner
didn't have any problem
running the game,
but then as soon as we, you know,
we launched it on, you know,
on the day for the backers,
like immediately people came back,
oh, the game is crashing or sending
out a black screen and stuff like that.
That's always like, crap.
If we would not have done it like that,
we would have eventually run
into this issues so you know,
on the 28th we would
have released the game
and people would have had
big problems with it and like,
while crashes are not great,
but at least acceptable during a Beta,
like once the game is out there,
you know, it becomes very less acceptable.
Franzke: This VGA out.
Haven't seen that in a while.
I don't know if it's even still possible.
Franzke: I had, I think
two crashes on Windows 98.
I mean, I was surprised
that you managed to
download Steam on that machine, I guess.
But yeah, unfortunately the game
does not run on Windows 98
and I don't think it's part of
the minimum requirement.
But yeah, that was, that was certainly
very funny and surprising for sure.
Franzke: I knock on the
graphics card right here.
Romero: And for right now we're
in shooting crashes and blockers
and people's progress is lost,
saved and corrupted stuff like that.
I mean, for now it's like the
forum is the bug list pretty much,
'cause there's so much coming in.
So before I was in, you know,
I was looking through our bugs
and now I'm looking
through all these bugs.
Now they're the testers.
They're reporting the bugs to us.
We're merely the conduit through which,
you know, we get the bugs to developer.
Lui: It's nice, I think,
for the team to have an overview
of how the overall progress is going.
So it's nice to be able to see,
like look at the chart and be like,
oh, we are constantly going down.
And there are spikes, like this spike
over there is when Tim played through
the game twice and submitted
about fifteen pages of bug fixes.
Schafer: Should realize
that it's gotta be done this week.
So if there's anything that
I really care about getting fixed,
I have to make a big
stink about it right now.
But making big stinks
is what I'm all about.
The camera's here and then
when I click, ah, the camera moves.
So annoying.
Vella's first step makes camera twitch.
At the end of the game,
there's just a million bugs
with things flashing or
twitching for one frame.
Drives me nuts.
When she gives him the cupcake,
that's where the cupcake appears
floating in midair for one frame.
Yep. The average player
can't say what happened,
but they'll just get
this weird twitchy feeling
when they're playing
the game of like, aaah,
something was just, it's like,
just a feeling of it not being polished.
But I can see, like OK, that
camera was wrong for one frame.
Sometimes I can't even
tell if I saw a flash.
Like at the end of that cutscene,
I swear I saw a flash.
I'm trying to fix everything.
You can't fix everything.
The mouse sensitivity
is weird, though.
Peck: Myself, I've been, I got
a couple of small little crashes in the UI,
stuff like that, that I've been fixing.
And but yeah, mostly like,
these are my bugs right now.
They all fit on one span of the window,
so it's like, things are going well.
Schafer: How many
bugs are left in Bugzilla?
Is it really a sizeable amount still?
Crook: Yeah. I mean these are all,
they're all, they're, most of them are minor.
Schafer: Who's making all these bugs?
Crook: I mean they're just minor
but we know the game's coming
out again, you know, as the final.
So, so we just want to
make it as good as we can.
We're going to be, most of
us will roll off on Monday,
onto other things for a while.
And come back.
Schafer: OK, great.
Crook: We're going to have to
assess at the end of the month,
we got to figure out how much
work is ready to just start doing.
Crook: Sorry. So yeah.
Which, you know, some of the script
is written but there's still more to go.
So I'm not sure how much work
there will be, just for the first,
you know, couple weeks.
So we got to keep people busy, though.
We had three of our animators
actually go off the project now,
so they've moved onto other projects.
Roberts: I'm leaving Broken Age.
Because I'm moving onto
another unannounced project.
And they'll be, the rest of the Broken
Age team that's left on that project,
they're going to continue
on Broken Age Part Two.
So yeah, the nature of
this new project is such
that I don't see myself going over
and helping out on Act Two at all.
But you know, that's famous
last words, so it could happen.
I would love to, at
least animate something,
but we are getting pretty busy
around here with other things
so yeah, that, that
I can't see happening.
Offscreen Voice:
Was it nice while it lasted?
Roberts: It was, yeah, yeah.
It was a nice, I wasn't really
expecting to work on this project at all,
so it was kind of a nice surprise.
And it was something
that I wanted to work on.
Of course, you know, everyone here
wanted to, well, most people here,
I can't say everyone,
but most people here
wanted to, you know,
at least put their
hands on this because,
just because it made
history for you know,
not to sound too grandiose about
it, but that's what it did, right?
I mean, there is history
that was made here.
And so everyone that saw that,
you know, thinks wow, yeah,
that's something I at least want
to put something in there.
So OK. Goodbye, Broken Age.
Goodbye 2HB. Goodbye, Maya.
Goodbye Double Fine.
Schafer: So we'll launch the
game tomorrow and hopefully
if we're not all here fixing bugs,
we'll get to go out and have another,
we'll go back to Red's, I hope.
If it's still standing.
And take the team out for drinks.
And before they all roll off,
temporarily, onto other projects,
I'd like to have them all hang out.
Go have a drink and celebrate.
'Cause it's weird, it's like, you wish
these launches were super-clean,
like everyone could just
say, everything was great!
So hopefully, I mean, time
usually just washes away
all the smaller things that happened,
like that embargo thing and all
that other stuff will be forgotten.
And people will just remember how
we didn't have mouse sensitivity
when we launched and now we do.
No, that won't be the thing. Maybe.
Rice: It's Elijah Wood's birthday today.
Bailey: Oh wow.
Rice: So this is a good birthday present, right?
Bailey: Yeah.
Rice: Tim, call Elijah and wish
and wish him a happy birthday.
Schafer: Call him? Rice: Yeah,
like you do with your mom.
Schafer: Hey, Elijah!
Happy birthday. Oh, shoot.
[Phone rings]
Bailey: Yeah. It's interesting, though.
You think about Tim, like he's been
working on this game for two years.
It's now being commercially
released but so much goes into,
you know, the lead up to this.
And I guess I could understand.
It's a little anti-climactic
when you sit here
and you just kind of like refresh
the webpage and look at numbers.
The interesting thing about price, though,
is you know, we can charge 29 bucks
and because I used to
actually work with, you know,
at a publisher who did, you
know, significant retail presence,
I know the PNLs and like,
literally our profit margin
and the profit margin we
have for like a $59 box product,
are the same thing, because with
the box product you got to like,
you got preprint the stuff.
You got all the materials, you got to
ship it and you got to store it, you know.
The extra store will take their cut.
There will be price protection involved.
There's a huge amount of
expense that goes into it.
That like, yeah.
Profit margins are equal.
So we just got a lot,
we got rid of a lot of waste.
Oh, there it is.
Rice: All right, Justin. We're live.
Bailey: I see it.
Rice: I'm going to push the update.
Bailey: Good. Do it.
Bailey: And it's interesting, 'cause they'd
like, when you get in a top position,
it's probably at least a
hundred, a hundred thousand,
a hundred fifty thousand dollars.
But it actually could be way north
of that and I'd have no idea,
because you're number one, right?
So you could be very, very high up.
But that would be, that would
be an amazing day for us,
we could, we get in that top position.
Schafer: Sitting at my desk, looking at
a picture of me sitting at my desk.
[Hums to self]
Bailey: It's about an hour
and twenty minutes delayed.
Bailey: Yeah. That will be when
we actually see something.
I'll know at 11:00, 11:30
I'll have like the first indication.
I think the hour of celebration
or reckoning or both has come.
Schafer: No, it's not Raz.
I don't see any boobs
or penises on anything.
Choy: You have to look more closely.
Are you guys doing a standup?
Schafer: We are going to do
standups. Standups? Rice: Yeah.
Schafer: Whoever's left, whoever's left
on the team, come on to standups.
We're now live for everybody in the
world to buy the game on Steam.
That's it. That's all I
had to say today.
OK. So Part Two.
It's like a back massage.
Bailey: Oh yeah, it's pretty good.
That's not bad.
It's not, it's not as good now.
Schafer: It feels nice, yeah.
Schafer: So if the sales aren't good,
I'll immediately smash your head with this
so that you won't ever feel
the pain of seeing bad sales.
Bailey: That's good. Deal.
All right, we doing this?
Let's do, let's first just look
at the, let's see, Top Ten List.
Schafer: I'm not going to look.
Bailey: Not looking at Top Ten List?
Schafer: I don't care.
I'm not going to look.
Oh, oh! Look at that! Schafer: Holy cow!
Bailey: You're number
two on new releases.
That has no component to sales.
But top sellers, we are number four.
All right. Whoa!
Oh, this is refreshed, the new releases.
Still number four. OK, cool. Sweet!
Fifty thousand, five ninety-nine.
That is 2,000 units on Steam.
Schafer: Hm?
Bailey: That's 2,000 units on Steam.
Yeah, this is good.
This will, this will be good.
If we get over 100K today,
I think that's a, it's a very good day
and I expect that European
sales usually hit overnight.
So I would expect that to double.
Schafer: Double today. Bailey: Yeah.
Schafer: By the end of the day.
Bailey: Between now
and the end of the day.
Probably more than double.
This'll probably be like,
I would say like 125 to 150,
which means that would take us over
nine million for Double Fine lifetime revenue.
Schafer: Hm.
Bailey: It should be very, very cool.
And I actually expect, I do
expect the trend of the game to,
to stay, we'll have a spike right now,
but I think it'll actually be pretty
steady after that, so that's good.
Schafer: OK. Now pretend the
cameras are off now. Bailey: Now pretend?
Schafer: Tell me what you really think.
Bailey: It's, it is what I expected.
Schafer: OK. All right. Exciting. Cool.
Now I don't want anyone to look at it.
I guess I'll go deisgn
Act Two. Bailey: Yeah.
Offscreen Voice: It's
not earth shattering.
Bailey: It's not earth shattering, but it's
on track to do what we need it to do,
you know, to get the
game finished this year.
The only unfortunate part
about this whole thing is that
I was looking at
all of our news broadcasts
and basically, you know,
basic, all the news,
all the exposure went out when
the backers got it, like two weeks ago.
And people didn't have a
chance to literally like, you know,
hey, I'll, I'll buy it now
and I can play it now.
You know, that's hard to, as like a,
you know, value proposition for consumer,
it's hard to see everybody
talking about this and be like,
oh, I can pay for it and
still not get to play it.
But it'll hopefully come out in the wash.
Rice: It was the last,
I think it was very last bar.
Schafer: I think we can confirm now
that we chose the right code name.
It didn't sound like the right code
name, but now look at it; Red's.
[Music]
Schafer: Yeah. Let's talk about that.
We shipped Red's last week.
I don't know if you guys noticed that.
We shipped the game, it was awesome.
Yah, Red's.
[Applause].
It has, everybody
claps just for shipping it.
I think I've gotten claps
out of you guys for like...
Schafer: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
And next week we're shipping Red's.
Next week it'll mean two
weeks since we shipped Red's.
It has, it has made about $800,000
so far on the old Steam thing, which is fun.
And so that is an interesting number,
because it was kind of a relief in
one hand because we were like,
get a lot of possibilities here, one of
them is that we don't make any money.
No one buys the game,
we can't make Part Two.
But I think we, luckily, because that would
have been an easy update, though.
We would have called
all the haters on Twitter
and just been like, you
guys were totally right.
I'm a huge a-hole and we're
not going to do Part Two.
But that doesn't seem
to be a risk anymore.
We are also kind of hoping like,
what if it made so much money
that we didn't ever have
to make games anymore?
We could just hang around and
play games all day in the office.
Schafer: And we also don't make Act Two.
Yeah, either way Act Two is like.
Yeah, I mean, that's not a big enough
number that we're going to be immediately,
completely independent
of publishers this year,
like it was a secret back
in my head, kind of hope.
Where all my hopes are
in the back of my head.
Any other questions?
Schafer: It's just under
20,000, I think. So, so far.
Schafer: We are. Yeah, so that's
just to finish the whole Red's update.
What the team is working on now is
a lot of, instead of diving into Part Two,
is actually platform work.
You get it out on more platforms to sell
it on like IOS and the other platforms.
Schafer: Sooner than we had
previously thought we were going to do it.
Skillman: So it would be
Act One available on iOS.
Schafer: Yeah. OK. Let's talk about PR.
PR. What happened in
the world of PR last week?
Rice: Well, like you said
we launched Broken Age.
So it's been a lot of, yay! Yay!
[Applause].
Yeah. So it's been trying to keep
that conversation going in
the public as much as possible.
So those are ongoing
kind of conversations.
But yeah, now we're kind
of shifting focus to AF stuff
and getting everything ready
to announce and launch that thing.
Schafer: Yeah, OK, that's it.
I think all of you would agree with
me that Chris Remo's a big jerk.
I think, yeah.
[Scattered applause]
And furthermore we were all talking
about it and decided we didn't like him.
So I don't want that to influence you
at all, but I think we need to have,
Chris Remo is moving onto
hang out with his friends,
which is bad news for all of
his, whatever you guys are.
But, I've been saving that one all week.
So, but you're still here right now so,
what happened last week in the world
of the community of Double Fine?
Remo: An important
thing for our community
is that we launched
Broken Age [applause].
That actually has been a cool thing
to see because I'm seeing a lot of stuff
from people who have never even
necessarily played adventure games before.
Schafer: I love all those people.
Remo: Yeah. I mean there's, it's
actually been kind of awesome to see,
because a lot of them, you know,
like with adventure game fans,
people come to, people come
to it with like preconceptions
and like all the, you know, the history
that they have with the genre.
And that's cool
because that's the people
that the game was
inspired by in the first place.
But it's also really cool to see
all the reactions from people
who don't have those preconceptions,
because they'll be like, yeah,
so I was playing this thing
and like I didn't know what it
was and it seemed pretty cool.
You just kind of walk around
and like cool stuff happens.
And like it was actually really awesome.
And that kind of thing
is surprisingly cool to read.
So I've been trying to
keep up with that stuff,
just around the web and it's
been really inspiring and awesome.
Schafer: Anything else?
Mr. Remo? Anything? Anything else.
Remo: I will miss you guys a lot.
I really loved working here a
lot and I'm bummed to be leaving.
Schafer: Well, we'll
miss you, wish you well
and we still think you're a big jerk.
Who agrees with me?
[Applause]
[Music]
Offscreen Voice: [singing] I guess
he's not a monster, but he's so far away.
Shay, we're meant to
be for longer than forever.
Offscreen Voice: Who cares about Shay?
I have evil deeds to do.
I used to be good like
everyone else and Shay, but no!
I am actually evil.
Offscreen Voice: [singing]
for longer than forever.
As constant as the stars.
I close my eyes and I am where you are.