Schafer: Mmm, my new notebook.
did you notice I brought my
old and my new notebooks?
Can you believe I filled this up?
Remember? This old notebook.
It's all full.
Now there's the design for
the last shot in the game.
Can't show you,
you guys always use those.
So yeah, this is the new notebook.
And this is kind of a
disaster first, because this,
I didn't notice until I started it, it's
wide ruled, instead of college rule.
And this game is
definitely college level.
But I decided actually this will make
me feel like we got a lot more work done,
'cause my free writing
will fill up more pages.
Yeah, I purposely got white
so it'd feel pristine and fresh.
It's smaller
This is like totally
like a baby notebook.
It does! It makes me
look stupid, doesn't it?
But then again, I'm getting
older so it's hard to see stuff.
New notebook.
[Music]
Schafer: Yeah. Let's talk about stuff.
We shipped Red's last week.
I don't know if you guys noticed
that, we shipped a game.
It was awesome.
Yay, Red's.
[Applause]
It has, it has, it has made about
$800,000 so far on the old Steam thing,
which is fun.
And that's not a big enough
number that we're going to be
immediately completely independent
of publishers this year,
like was a secret, back
of my head kind of hope.
Where all my hopes are
in the back of my head.
It's a little, it's a little tricky financially
because, pretty much, you know,
I think conservatively
we would estimate that
we've made most of the money
that we're going to make off of it.
We might make more when we release
Part Two, but it's not going to be equal.
It's not going to be like
the equal amount of sales.
So we're working on something that is,
we're usually working on something like,
oh, when this, when we release it,
it'll make a bunch of money for us
and that'll pay for more
stuff and so we already got,
or kind of got that
money in advance twice.
Offscreen Voice: So you're making a bigger,
more complex game that you
know isn't going to sell as well?
Schafer: Yeah. Yep. Just from love.
This time it's just for love.
That's our slogan.
The money is gone, now
we're just running on love.
No, I mean, the first
part made enough money.
It definitely made its numbers.
I mean, it was, we went through
these phases of like let's, let's estimate,
you know, conservatively,
because it's an adventure game
and you know, we had a conservative
estimate for it, how much it would sell.
Schafer: Everyone think in your head,
how many units this game is going to sell.
How many do you
think it's going to sell?
Rice: A million.
Schafer: A million?
How many you think's going to sell?
Bailey: 150,000 year one.
Schafer: What do you say?
Stamos: I was going to say 200,
but I was thinking more lifetime.
Schafer: So let's say it was 300.
And then somewhere along the line we
got really excited about people's response
to it and excited by the game
itself and how much we liked it.
And you can see this, you know,
part of us were like, hey now,
if this does really, really well,
it might change a lot of stuff for us.
Stoddard: A lot of people here kind of
hang on because like, they know,
they know Tim, they know,
they know the management,
they know the vision and if
it hits, it'll, it'll be really good.
It'll be really good.
So we're just hanging in.
Schafer: And you could
see that in like Camden.
I think Camden was like a lot of
people were, kind of hoping for it.
And it didn't sell that much.
It didn't sell so much that it changed
our whole business plan for the year.
It sold what we kind
of estimated originally.
Schafer: So far it's made about 1.6 million
dollars on Steam, which is awesome.
And it's, by, that's about
70,000 people purchased it;
about 80,000 were the backers.
So that's about 150,000 units out there.
Schafer: And so that's, I don't want be
too sad about it [inaudible 00:04:41].
Just a little part of me
was like, what if, you know,
it's always part of you that
hopes what if something really,
like a big, you know, outlier
thing is just crazy, hits.
It just unexpectedly,
like our Kickstarter.
Once you have an experience like that,
it's hard to go back to the normal world
where things sell what you expect them to.
Bailey: One thing I am a little
interested in, I'm not, not sure,
is that, you know, we just don't have,
we're not doing any marketing.
We're not spending
any money on marketing.
And one thing I'm just looking
at is to get around that, you know,
we do a lot of press
presence, a lot of social media.
We rely upon features on the distributors,
in this case with Steam and Valve.
But it's like what, how much
does banner ads help?
And you know, those other
traditional forms of marketing.
And it is something I'd like
to look at in the future,
'cause that will be the
one thing I think publishers
have done different
than we haven't done.
I think, any of our fans want us
to be successful commercially.
This whole thing is
for naught if, you know,
if we don't come out of it able to be
more independent and then, you know,
be able to create more
creative works independently.
So you know, I think we need
to take that into consideration
when we come up with
our, our plans for Act Two.
Maybe we're really lucky to
have split the game in two,
because then it gets some more chances.
And then we have more platforms coming
up, so yeah, I think it will be good.
Schafer: We are. Yeah, so that's
just to finish the whole Red's update.
What the team is working on now is
a lot of, instead of diving into Part Two,
is actually platform work.
You get it out on more platforms, to sell
it on like IOS and the other platforms.
Schafer: Sooner than we had previously
thought we were going to do it.
Schafer: The sales of the game make it
look like the people who bought the game
are people who played
adventure games before.
It seems like we found those people.
But we haven't quite
gotten yet to all the people
who've never played
adventure games before.
Rice: The idea was while we were waiting
for design and writing for Act Two stuff,
that we can try and jump on some
of these platform work to fill time.
And potentially even move forward
some of those platform releases.
Kipnis: Hi, we have
some questions for you.
Rice: We do have a
pressing question for you.
Schafer: There's a lot of work
that Oliver has to get done
before the iPad version can come out.
But that's a version I'm waiting for.
Well, all of them,
waiting for all of them.
Hansen: From a studio standpoint
the most important thing
is still the platform work,
because we want to make sure that we
can get the ports out as soon as possible.
Franzke: Right.
Franzke: And yeah, it's
been going pretty well.
It's just, you know, it's a lot of work,
just kind of looking at those platforms
and seeing kind of how is
the game performing on that
and what other kind
of very specific issues.
Schafer: It's awesome.
So I get to keep this, right?
Franzke: Also just generally us
getting the infrastructure in place to,
to kind of launch games
on those platforms.
Very often, you know,
different storefronts require,
have different requirements when
it comes how you deliver the product.
You know, it's very different delivering
something to Google Play store
versus the iOS app store versus the
Mac app store and things like that.
So there'll a whole bunch of infrastructure
things that we need to put in place.
And so I've been working on those a lot.
So as you can, there's still
some stuff that's broken.
For example, some invalid textures
here and there that shouldn't be there.
I need to investigate what's going on.
You should be able to play through
the game from the beginning to end,
which is huge.
But as you can see, you know, the game,
the game runs and I would even have sound.
[Sound from iPad]
Franzke: Oh, great. All right.
Offscreen Voice: I mean, traditionally,
like port houses handle moving
stuff to different platforms.
So like why do it internally and
not just hand it off to someone?
Franzke: Because the intrinsic
goal for an external port house
is different than what
our intrinsic goal is.
For a port house, it's like,
well, our contract says
we have to get it done for this
platform, for this amount of money.
So we will employ any hack that
we can think of to make this work.
Like, we'll, like essentially
you're throwing out any,
any kind of way of like clean software
development is the first thing that goes.
And that's OK as a developer,
if it's a product that's done and
you're never going to touch it again
and you get the code back and
you just archive it and that's it.
But if it's something that you
will have to work with in the future,
you don't want to do that.
Franzke: I don't know.
Criticism makes me always smile.
Franzke: We'll find out.
Let's hope so, right?
Schafer: I made it for the
hardcore fans, only the hardcore fans.
I was only thinking of the hardcore fans
and I hate everyone
who's not a hardcore fan.
Someone came up to me at PAX and
was like, hey, I really like Broken Age.
It seemed really short, though.
It seemed like they cared
more about getting Elijah Wood
than putting money into puzzles.
It's like, first of all,
who are you saying "they"?
That's me.
And that's not how the
money worked on the project.
Go and, oh why am I talking to you?
Schafer: [High pitched voice]
I was disappointed in your game.
I just wanted you to know.
Schafer: You have a good point.
I should quit the games industry.
Schafer: Yay! You fans.
I am excited about all the
things you're asking me about.
I am really, I am excited
about coming on the iPad.
I'm hoping people who have
never played adventure games
will give it a shot
and like it and play it.
But we didn't, you know,
dumb the game down for them.
We just made it the
way we wanted to make it.
Offscreen Voice: How much time
do you have left to work on this?
'Cause it seems like people are
starting to roll back into Broken Age.
Franzke: Yes. Yeah.
I mean, this is the other thing that's
always been happening right now.
We're kind of also working on starting
to work on Act Two, which is nice.
Schafer: Let's talk about Red's.
Remember Red's, it's not done yet.
Part One is up.
Part Two we got to do now.
Schafer: That was crazy.
I've never, would never have done anything
like that where we shipped something
and then immediately,
except for like Kinect Party.
But I've never had to go back
into a game after finishing it.
Usually like, I finish the game and
I immediately like look away from it
and just walk off into the
desert and never look at it again.
Until like ten years later
or something like that.
Schafer: Well, we're so
used to like shipping a game
and then mentally your brain
starts to heal and close off,
like, it's like you would
like, like you have a baby.
You know how it is when
you guys have a baby, right?
You like, and then your body starts,
all right, let's pretend that never happened.
Let's just heal up, umm.
But no. It's like, there's twins.
There's another one coming.
Rice: Yay, twins.
Schafer: And so, normally I
would just be like, OK, that's done.
You know, what's next?
But it's like, oh yeah,
there's a whole other part of
the meaty part of the story
that we have to get into.
Like explaining all the crazy
stuff that happened in Act One.
Schafer: And Lee, you're still on,
you're still working on it or you're?
Petty: You seem surprised.
Schafer: I just know you're in demand.
Petty: You're in the office?
Petty: Here's all Act
Two's threads I started.
So these are all some of the
concepts works we've been doing.
So you can see some of them are
revisiting characters or like changes
to recurring characters or scene
modifications from Act One, new props.
Or here's, here's like a
puzzles one, you know.
Curtis is now into metal
working so he had all these,
he needed a table in his room.
So we were trying to figure
out the positioning of the table
and what they needed to do
and Tim was like, yeah, that looks too
useful with all those tongs on there.
Get rid of the tongs.
And hey, those guys are too far apart.
They can't be in a cut scene together.
So I'm like, oh,
what I'm hearing is like,
yeah, that's great but now
they're blocking the molds.
So put them here and here.
So we're kind of like,
I'm trying to just work through
as much as that as fast as possible
without having to program anything.
And I mentioned story beats
so Bagel's did a lot of these early
on as he kind of went through that.
Yeah, so a lot of this
stuff is just like, you know,
we're both kind of working on different
aspects of the same thing, you know.
Just kind of like print a breakdown,
what the characters might be doing.
I was trying to breakdown what changes to
the space and puzzles would have on that.
Schafer: Right now on the project I think
our animators are all out in the field,
free-ranging across
the company, helping out.
But our programmers are still on
and we're going to meet today
with anyone who's still around
to talk about the puzzles for
Act Two and get that kicked off.
Schafer: Welcome, everybody.
Thank you for coming and
still being on the Red's team,
even though we shipped some of it.
Kipnis: Unlike some people.
Petty: Yeah, I'm like,
Schafer: What is wrong with the artists?
Johnny-come-lately's.
Petty: That's not everybody at all.
Schafer: Johnny-leave-early's.
Kipnis: Johnny-leave-early's.
Schafer: Those people who do
what we've asked them to do
Schafer: So we could get this
design all straightened away
and start implementing it,
Franzke: We're done?
Schafer: And then we're done, right?
I don't even know if there's a schedule.
We have a schedule?
But we'll probably have a better
schedule after we get this design all,
actually tasked away.
Petty: Well, yeah.
I mean, I think the high level picture
hasn't really changed in a long time.
You know, even before
we finished Act One,
I think the high level
picture was still the same.
Yeah, it's like story beats
from a long time ago.
And he and I have talked
about it on a high level.
So I don't think that's changed,
but a lot of the very specific puzzles
or cut scenes haven't
been designed or written yet.
And some of that has changed
since Act One, you know.
So I think Tim took the feedback of a
lot of people wanting
a more challenging game.
Schafer: So how much harder are we
going to make the second half of the game?
Franzke: Much harder.
Schafer: Much harder?
Schafer: Every once in a
while I design something,
like there's no way anyone
would ever get, OK, let's put that in.
Kipnis: You want hard?
We'll give you hard.
Franzke: We're going to give you hard.
Schafer: Well, it did seem trying to
reconcile people complaining about
the difficulty with how
it felt in play-testing
when like people weren't
getting out of the train thing.
And like, 'cause it
was a reaction to like
how miserable people appeared
to be when they were stuck.
Kipnis: Yeah, someone, someone made
a post on the forum that was really astute
about how a lot of the difficulty that the
old adventure games had was obfuscation.
Like the fact that you had like ten verbs
and you had like 20,000 items made it
seem a lot harder than if it was, you know,
a more limited choice or whatever.
Franzke: And no Internet.
Kipnis: Yeah, and no Internet, exactly.
Franzke: No, seriously.
Schafer: Yeah.
and no real play testing.
Some play-testing, but not like we did.
We've kind of gone for
like slicker, slicker inventory.
And we did that over the course
of those adventure games, too.
Like Throttle had like
a very small inventory
and of course people said
that was too easy and short.
There you go.
Schafer: I mean, would we want to add
another row to the inventory because of that?
Would we want to have
a double stack inventory?
Like Vella shrinks down and
then Shay can carry her around?
And you can open her up
and get her inventory. Whoa.
I'm trying to just, just general good
design stuff is watching out for things
where you find a solution
before you find a problem.
And you know, I mean I was
trying to find those in Act One, too.
But some things you
just never, are not clear.
Well, let me fly through this and
then we can just highlight some things
to come back to later.
Well, there's some like challenges
I'm trying to achieve with the second act,
like the interaction
between Shay and Vella.
Maybe not in direct interaction,
but more relevance of the
switching back and forth,
making that more relevant.
Even if it's just information that
passes back and forth in your brain.
And I'm really thinking about how to
wrap up the character arcs in the end,
'cause mostly with adventure
games you have a story
but you tend to think about the progress
of the story as being the puzzles.
And I solve a whole bunch of puzzles and
then they win, do you know what I mean?
Whereas if you're writing a
movie you'd be thinking about
the total ups and downs these
characters are going through.
And so I'm focusing a lot more on that,
'cause I really want it to be satisfying,
how the characters end up in the end.
Not just they achieved all their small
goals and add it to one big goal,
but they actually had a moment of
you know, some real lows and highs
and that the ending actually meant
something to the characters.
Hopefully.
But it's easy to get distracted by
the mechanics of solving puzzles
and think that the story
is kind of resolving.
And the "A" plot does
resolve in adventure games.
Like your action plot resolves because
the character achieves their goals,
but the "B" plot's like the emotional
plot often, it's kind of left.
Where it's summed up
by the two characters
kissing at the end
or something like that.
But to have actually sum up in a
meaningful way for the characters
is something I have to do.
Schafer: The game?
Schafer: May? No.
I really am trying everything to make
sure the game comes out this year.
And then people always go what?
And then I say, the
first act took two years.
And so if the second act can take
less than one year, it's a miracle.
And that's what we're doing.
Rice: If the directive is we want
to ship by the end of the year,
I think we've talked a lot about like
things that would need to happen
to make that doable,
to like where if we timeboxed
a scheduled to December,
we'd still have to do some
stuff to pull it in a little bit.
I think that's the conversation
that we need to have, I guess.
'Cause if not, like it's
going to be very easy
to just keep pushing stuff
back like we did on Act One.
Schafer: Well, the two big reasons,
two of the big reasons are, or three,
there's like backer
expectations because they,
a lot of people thought it was going to
come out like two months after Act One.
So that message thing that we
kind of have to get out to people.
Like a couple people I've talked to,
it's like I hope it's coming out this year,
so there's like that.
There is financial, just that Justin
has been working with December
in all his financial planning, you know.
So that's a pretty hard thing.
Rice: Yeah, both for getting profit
in and for spending on the project.
Schafer: Yeah.
And for me, just the possibility
of actually being up for awards
because we shipped
the first half this year.
So we're either going to
be not eligible for 2014 awards
or really coming out in
January or March of 2015,
when everyone will forget about it
by the time the '15 awards come out.
So there's that.
Rice: I think those are all the right
reasons and all the reasons that I feel like
everyone I've talked to about this
wants to really make December happen,
but I think that it's, it's just going
in knowing that that would mean like,
doing whatever it takes
to make that happen.
And sacrificing in some ways.
Petty: It's possible. It's possible.
You know, most video game
productions are a series of bottlenecks.
And trying to get everything
unblocked with minimal bottlenecks
is what's going to
make or break December.
Although the other problem with
December is there's a lot of unknowns
as it comes to puzzle
playability and testing.
So we can take certain steps, like we
can try and work through earlier versions
or script early versions and test them,
but you know, ultimately
that's the fun factor
and that's a little hard to
know how that's going to hit.
And when you don't leave
yourself a lot of iteration time,
it may not be enough
and you don't really know.
Schafer: I think we can do December.
To me it's like an infinity far away.
I always think we can do anything.
That's why my games are sometimes late.
Schafer: It's really just the best game
that we can make and we feel like
we can actually make without crashing
the company into the ground.
And they also just want
to finish it because it's,
while it's fresh in people's minds.
And I do want to get the team
back and there's a pressure to
keep them on other projects because
they have these publisher milestones.
And publisher milestones are always
scarier than internal milestones,
because there's no
outside force threatening to
not pay you if you
don't meet the milestones.
So we have to be that
threatening outside force.
Can you make some phone calls from
outside the building with a funny voice?
Hansen: I can.
Schafer: And be like,
we won't pay you guys
if you don't meet your
milestones on this project.
Hansen: I'm pretty sure
they're going to figure out that it's me.
Schafer: Well, that's the
other big factor, right.
Is we went to this smaller team,
which I think from a budget standpoint
was a good idea,
'cause you were writing.
Bagel and I could do some
early concept work and stuff.
If we were working from a no,
this is the target deadline,
that is not a good way to work.
If it's a, this is our target budget
and so we're lowering the
berm while we figure stuff out.
But if we were like, no, this is an
unmovable time here in December,
then we should have,
I mean this is in hindsight,
but we probably should have
tried to get more of the team
and start full production like
right after AF or something.
Hansen: Yeah, but we couldn't have.
There wasn't enough design
to execute on at that point.
Petty: Perhaps.
But I mean, I'm just, you know,
that's, I think it's just
one of the other factors,
I think, is that it felt good to
have a small team for a while,
while we sort of like could
digest some of these things
and Oliver was working on a platform.
But it did sort of put this maybe
end date a little bit in jeopardy.
Team Member: That's very true.
Schafer: So maybe Oliver's
stuff will make so much money
we can have more time to make Act Two.
Rice: It sounds like we're not going
to have more time, though, right?
It sounds like we could have more money
to throw at the problem and put...
Schafer: Oh yeah. Maybe that will make
more, we'll buy some more people.
Franzke: Yeah. It works pretty well.
I'm overall, like pretty happy
with how it turned out.
The load times aren't terrible.
You know, we were able to get a
lot of visual fidelity out of the game.
You know, essentially making
it look as good as on PC,
which I'm pretty happy about.
So if I go on the app store.
What is cool, is like obviously if you
go to games, it's right there, Broken Age.
It's also in Best New
Games, which is nice.
And that seems to be trending
pretty well also in the charts.
So I would say overall, so far it's
been a really successful launch.
Schafer: Last night I spent unknown
hours playing through Broken Age
and I'm so glad I did but I didn't
know I was going to end unfinished.
Uh oh.
We don't really call it
Part One on the app store.
I should say Part, should I say,
does this guy say Part Two coming soon.
Should I say "soon"?
If children love this as much as
Day of the Tentacle or Psychonauts,
then please mark me as
fuddy-duddy and ignore me.
OK, where do I do that?
It was like no game I've ever played.
It doesn't glitch or crash.
The story is great and
I can't wait for Act Two.
Two stars.
Not as advertised.
This game says ages 9 through 11
and that's about all I think would be fun for.
Oh, and the fake train wreck?
Why are we doing this
over and over again?
The kid actually says he'd
rather jump off a cliff
than do it again or something like that.
That's how I feel as well.
Please refund.
There's no way this
game is worth the price.
I think he' stuck on the train.
So maybe that wasn't too easy after all.
Anyway. Overall it's really good.
On the iPad.
Schafer: Very happy with the iPad launch.
I'm good.
Franzke: I think we will know in a
few days, kind of from some of our
third-party tools that send us
information about app sales.
But yeah, fingers crossed.
Bailey: So moving on, Broken Age did
decent sales on iPhone.
Stamos: iPad.
Bailey: iPad, sorry.
Decent enough that we're
looking into doing iPhone
and potentially android tablets with it.
So that was good.
It's meeting forecasts.
It's not like a runaway hit,
but it's, you know, it's good.
It's decent cash flow.
So the numbers right now are
about 100,000 for, you know, four days.
So expect for the actual feature week,
while I'd say editor's choice,
it'll probably be around 150,000
and then it'll probably go down about
one-fourth of that for the next week,
while it's as a
previous editor's choice.
So yeah, decent, decent numbers.
Bailey: So it was received well.
It looks like it's, it's, it's doing what
our expectations were sales-wise.
Offscreen Voice: Expectations?
Bailey: Yeah, I mean you
can expect, you know,
about 100 to $150,000 is
what I expect out of a week
for an iOS game that's a
content-based game. Yeah.
Schafer: I think he was telling me
they performed to his expectations.
They met his sales forecast,
but of course forecasts are
always pretty conservative.
So he's always secretly hoping
that his sales forecasts are wrong.
Bailey: My expectation, just to be
clear, though, they're more about,
my expectations are more
reflective of the current market
on like iTunes for premium based games.
And like paid content based games.
So it's less of a reflection about the game
and more a reflection about the market.
Schafer: We were at number
four, now we're at number ten.
We might not be number ten anymore,
but it was fun to be number
four for a long time.
Well, we finally got pushed off ten.
Let's see how far
down we are. Twenty-two.
This looks dirty.
Beaten by "Frozen Karaoke".
Schafer: Yeah, I mean, I'm happy
with the performance on iPad,
but I don't think it made a lot of
extra money that's going to allow us
to like hire another programmer
and throw him at the team.
So I don't think it's going to
change the schedule, unfortunately.
We can always hope.
I keep promising that I will stop
hoping for those kind of things,
but it's hard not to think
about like, what if it was a big hit,
then we could totally hire
a programmer to help finish it.
But I don't know.
But I'm just happy it made
enough that we can stay in business.
Bailey: It's just there's no
magic bullet, basically.
So you know, it's, everything's a
grind, especially in the game industry.
Like, you know, you have to have an
amazing press and get the feature spots
and get huge VO and have
amazing polish and then do OK.
But if you didn't have any
of that stuff, you'd do horrible.
So the, yeah. The hit.
The hit has been, has
been elusive, for sure.
[Music]
Schafer: What did you guys think of it?
Offscreen Voice: What's that notepad
that says, "the end" on it, right there.
Schafer: Oh. This is how
things are going to end.
This is the guy who guessed
that Shay's ship was Mog Chothra.
I'm super happy that no one seemed
to have guessed the big spoiler
at the end of it.
I really thought that
was going to get out.
And actually long ago on
the forum one guy guessed it.
And no one followed up on it.
Like no one, he just said his little
thing, hey, what if this is the case?
No one answered him.
I was like, oh man.
Schafer: By the way, since I was
the guy who guessed that, by the way,
here's how I figured out how
it, how this, why I'm so smart.
And then here's how what I
think is going to happen in Act Two.
Offscreen Voice: He's done it for you.
Schafer: Yeah. What if I
get a bunch of ideas from him.
Might be bad.
People send me stuff as if
I have time to read anything.