Rice: Last week was, I think,
the Kickstarter update went out.
So that went over really well
and there's a lot of comments about
how we all looked
really sad in that episode.
Schafer: Cheer up, you guys!
Petty: There were a couple
random cuts of me going;
that had nothing to do
with what was being said.
Rice: It just meant that a lot of people
came out of the woodwork that were like,
don't be sad, we love the game.
And don't listen to the haters.
Kipnis: Wait, wait.
Can you send this link to us?
Rice: Yeah. If you looked at
forum threads, the main forum threads.
Schafer: What did you do last week?
Fish: Face it, baby.
You're hooked on me.
It's even funnier in the game, you guys.
Rice: Spoiler.
Schafer: Spoilers.
[Music]
Schafer: I really am trying everything to
make sure the game comes out this year.
Rice: It's just going in
knowing that that would mean like
doing whatever it takes
to make that happen.
And sacrificing in some ways.
Schafer: I think we can do December.
To me, it's like an infinity far away.
Schafer: There's like
backer expectations.
There is a financial.
And for me, just the possibility
of actually being up for awards.
It's really just the best game
that we can make and we feel like
we can actually make without
crashing the company into the ground.
Rice: And so I guess
on the screen right now
is the current timeline
for production on Act Two.
This is what we're working towards
and this was the attempt
to get to a December launch.
So like even this is stuff that is a
real challenge and a lot of people feel,
on the team, it's going to take everything,
everyone firing like on all cylinders.
Everything falling
into the right places.
But seems doable with a push.
And so that is the other challenge,
is that all of this requires like
our team coming back and working
in full, having writing ready to go.
Schafer: On Broken Age?
OK, Broken Age.
We have people coming back.
Ray's coming back.
Crook: Tomorrow.
Schafer: You're typing something.
You're on Facebook over there.
Crook: Just with my eyes.
Schafer: Facebooking.
Ray's coming back tomorrow.
And Rusty's been back.
Anna's been wiring up actual
puzzles in Act Two, right?
Crook: Here we go.
Offscreen Voice: Been a while?
Crook: Deja vu. That's good.
It's good to be back on, back
in the world of Shay and Vella.
So I took, took a little time off
away from it, not off Double Fine,
but just away from the Broken Age and
helped out on a couple of other projects.
And that was great, because
it was just totally different
and just a new, it was a nice break.
Schafer: Wow, the team is big again.
Look at that.
And Oliver's working.
Franzke: We're implementing puzzles
and scenes are getting drawn
and like sample scripts are getting
written, so it's, it's pretty good.
We got Ben back now as well on
the project, which is good, exactly.
Peck: Wow. That was a roller coaster,
like now we're going to have to do the
whole thing over again in less time.
Kipnis: Yeah, I guess at this
point it's one of these things
where we know that we'll
be able to do the game.
The matter will be to the
standard that we have in Act One,
like that's not a risk however.
That's not a concern that we have.
But we just like, now it's like OK,
can we do this in a few months?
And we'll see.
Hansen: Yeah, we worked through a lot
of the kinks that we experienced during
the Act One, so it's really just
about pure execution at this point.
Petty: This wouldn't stay here,
but if you had like everything on,
so they kind of don't overlap each other
but they all add up
versus like this stuff.
Schafer: Cool. That's neat.
Petty: Since it's the only
thing that's really changed,
hopefully it becomes like the player
knows it's a focal point, you know.
They know they need to keep
going back, 'cause it's different.
Peck: I'm pretty excited about how
much of the tech we already have in place
and we can just like
hit the ground running on
just writing up the game
play and stuff like that.
Crook: So that maybe makes
it a little less exciting, in a way,
just because it's not new.
As far as figuring things out, but
it also makes you less nervous,
you know, 'cause we know, OK, it worked.
And you know, there's a
few things we want to change.
Crook: We really need to
work on the flip book interface.
It's not very intuitive.
Another thing.
Is there any way, Oliver, I know
we've mentioned this in the past,
but faster exporting of
anims from Maya? Yeah.
It's just, you know, it's just these,
this, we have a lot of big scenes.
Tim writes long scenes and
they, and you make one change,
you test it like, ahh, OK, that's good.
Then you got to re-export again,
that's another ten, fifteen minutes.
Franzke: I mean, one thing
I'm interested to investigate
is whether we could launch
Maya in batch mode somehow
and like execute a script on it.
Petty: I would if we have a
network machine that does it.
Just like when, you know,
in Brutal Legend we eventually
stopped doing local exports of the movie
and started having the
build machine to do it, yeah.
It would also help if
we didn't have, you know,
seven year old machines
with only 4 gigs of RAM.
So it could be fixed by,
you know, I don't know.
Crook: Greg. Buy all new computers.
Crook: So it'll, it'll just
make workflow easier.
I think it'll save us a
lot of time in bug fixing.
Petty: You know, I noticed that
there are a lot of animation bugs
as the production went on.
And some of those, a lot of those
boil down to like sorting issues.
Crook: Basically one piece of
geometry didn't know whether it
should sort in front or in back
of another piece of geometry.
Petty: The way we've done sorting
to support all the platforms is limited
and they spend a lot
of time cleaning that up.
Like if we knew that we were only
making it for a high-end console ever,
we'd probably have
had different solutions
that would have removed some of
the burden off the animators or artists,
but you know, when you're developing
a new engine and you're supporting
a really wide array of
platforms, you can't really do that.
Or at least it's harder.
Franzke: Yeah, gosh.
Petty: What do you think, Oliver?
This is way more fun
that fixing compatibility errors.
Rice: Yep. So I mean, Ben,
you're on some stuff now
and I guess a lot of this
would be coming your way.
Franzke: How do you
feel about crunching?
Petty: I mean it's always a balance
for every engine I've been on,
'cause all the games I've worked on I've
never used commercial licensed engines.
They've always been developed in-house.
So there's always this balance
between getting the game done
and adding tools to make
making the game more effective.
And it's really hard to know
where that balance should be.
Petty: I guess I just wanted to
mention that there's a ball of work
potentially to like fix some
of the workflows that got broken
and also improve some things
that I never got a chance to improve,
to try and also make the content
production of Act Two as efficient as possible.
Franzke: Like, this, this,
this schedule to some degree
also relies in effect
just like in Act One
we actually have some
manpower available to fix
and even possibly improve the
workflow, which is right now really bad,
because it just bi-rotted all alway because
nobody had time to really look at it.
Like opening scenes takes insane
amount of time, nobody really knows why.
I don't have time to look into it.
Nobody has, Anna needs to work.
We only have two programmers.
Rice: If we're worried about December,
that seems like that's going to be
something that makes
it even more challenging.
Petty: Just something to throw
in the bucket with the rest of it.
Petty: And so we're, we're going to a
more traditional production cycle now,
trying to actually build the
very specific game assets,
not just design them, you know.
Preproduction way.
And we're finishing our
first sprint of Act Two.
[Music]
Schafer: This is the first time we've
played through since we started Act Two.
Kipnis: Although I need to make
sure that the sound is actually working.
Last time on Broken Age.
Schafer: Are we going to have that?
Oh my God. OK. Here we go.
This better not fucking end here!
It better not be the end!
I paid $15 for, what?
Pull on, OK.
Ohmygod is it going to go
right into it? Awesome.
That's so nice and smooth.
So when you play through
the game, the only thing is like,
do you think we should still put
the text up, like "end of Act One"?
Kipnis: No, no, no.
It should just go right in.
Schafer: You guys seem to have already
come to an agreement about this one.
Kipnis: I mean we could,
but it wouldn't be as...
Schafer: Should I pick the girl?
Kipnis: No. Don't do it.
Petty: It'd be a very
short play through.
Schafer: It's like, oh no! Horrible bug.
Kipnis: He needs a runs.
Petty: You know what I realized,
too, is Shay's in all these scenes.
He feels a bit small in all of them.
He's the correct scale, but he's actually,
he's so much smaller feeling than Vella.
Their height is about the same,
but because she has the
bigger hair and a wider face.
Like he looks small talking to the same
characters as if you, like when you just,
and I've doubled, triple checked
the scale and it's all correct.
It just,
Kipnis: I wonder if we should make him bigger.
Petty: Well, it'd throw off
all the stuff at this point.
Schafer: So I assume,
I think Lydia is awkward.
She came 'cause I think she thinks this
is like, yeah, a surprise going away party.
She's coming, is this where, is
this where the cake is, you guys?
Is this where we're
having the big going away?
This is Lydia's last play-through
before she goes to...
That's Oculus. That's my
gesture for Oculus.
Facehugger.
Anyone have any last words for Lydia?
Petty: Thank you for all
your hard work, Lydia.
[Applause]
Kipnis: All your v-effects
in Act One were amazing
and we hope we get somebody anywhere
near as good as you for Act Two.
Crook: Yeah. Yeah, that was unfortunate.
Good old Lydia.
The turnover here is very, is not high.
It's actually, it's not high at all.
And I think sometimes we're lucky to
have people for as long as we do.
And it is a little scary, like we were
talking about effects today, a little bit.
Then I was, you know, and then
in the back of your head, like wait.
Who's going to do these?
I know Lee was doing a little
bit of effects work the other day,
but he's not going to have time
to like, be the effects person.
So I'm just going to have to trust
that they can find somebody.
'Cause we do have, we have
a couple other effects artists,
but they're on other projects.
So we're going to have
to find somebody new
that can come in and try and match
that style and we will, we will.
And so, so we'll find
somebody that can do it.
So I'm not freaking
out, but I don't know.
She was great.
Schafer: OK. But it's awesome.
See those puzzles coming together.
Kipnis: Yeah.
Schafer: We'll be done by December!
Rice: Exactly.
Petty: It's nice that you know when...
Schafer: This is where everyone
jumps out and is like, yeah!
Schafer: People were worried
about it being done in December,
earlier and then the writing is taking
even a little bit longer than we thought.
So I bet people were even more worried
about it being done in December.
Schafer: But we did
not quite finish the work,
the milestone and
when we started the milestone
we're like, from now
on if we don't finish milestones
we're just going to cut stuff
and when we don't finish them.
And the milestone,
so I guess we're just going to
have to cut half of those puzzles.
So we're going to go
back to that meeting we had
where we said that we're going
to cut stuff and be like, OK, listen.
It's not totally reasonable to just
cut stuff that doesn't get done.
We're going to just have
to make up for it somehow.
Petty: The intent was never to
be, oh, we didn't finish that puzzle.
We're just not doing it.
It was, it was that we didn't
want to leave a wake of unfinished,
half-implemented puzzles
for a variety of reasons
and one was you can't play-test a
half-implemented puzzle meaningfully.
And we wanted to play-test
sooner to help ameliorate
the amount of like play-tested
adjustments at the end
when we have less flexibility,
'cause the dialogue's recorded
and we're running out of time.
So I mean, it's all those reasons
why we're trying to do that.
But what actually wound up
happening for a couple reasons
was that we didn't
hit those two puzzles.
So we're effectively, I don't know, a
week or so behind already on the schedule
in our first two-week sprint.
And it's going to continue, like
we'll continue to get further behind
unless we can close
out puzzles on that sprint.
And I don't see
anything that changes that.
Right now, for example, there's really
only one puzzle that's finished writing.
We can't finish the hull patch
puzzle chain, because it's missing writing.
We can't finish the hexapal
wiring, we can't finish radiation suit.
So that still means we're behind.
Schafer: ok.
Hansen: Would that allow us to potentially
catch up, if we got the writing in time?
Schafer: So I bet I'm
maybe the last person
who thinks we can get it
done in December, probably.
You can kind of sense when you're
in a position where everyone kind of thinks
you're not going to make the deadline,
but they just haven't told you yet.
So I'm going to go ahead and
pretend I haven't heard it yet until they,
it's just too much time has
gone by, they can't tell me.
Then they won't tell me.
And then we'll make it on time, see?
That's how I operate.
Kind of mind games.
Hansen: There're two different
scenarios that we can do pretty much.
Well, one is we don't ship in December.
I mean, that's probably the
one we don't want to go for.
And the other one,
basically eats into Beta periods
so that we won't have a true Beta.
We would actually have
animations and v-effects
and a lot of the audio stuff
coming in late, like into Beta.
And there's a lot of
risk involved in doing that.
So that was something
that we were trying to avoid.
Rice: Then it's like getting the writing
done so we can have a VO session in time
to where we get the files back
soon enough to get our animators
pumping through that from Super Genius,
but also so it's not late,
too late to where we're
screwing audio and the effects guys.
So there's just kind
of a balance in there.
Hansen: We presented Tim with a
really aggressive schedule for delivering
the writing that we needed in
order to keep the team on schedule.
And it was requiring him
to work at a faster pace
than he's ever written on
the projects up to this point.
It's a challenge for everybody,
but it all starts with the writings.
Annable: So Tim, did you
see the email that I sent you
where I said I just
did this little exercise.
Schafer: Yeah, I deleted
that one immediately.
It was terrifying.
That was the one where you were like...
it looks he spent a year
writing this first one, so...
Annable: No, no. And it's, no.
'Cause you didn't take a year;
you spent like 13 weeks and
to me, you know, we don't,
we don't really succeed when
we say hey, Tim, write faster.
It's kind of an impossible thing to do.
So for me, I just don't see
December as a, as a reality.
Rice: So I don't know if
we want to make a call now
or if we want to say let's
try to write the rest of the game
in four and a half weeks
and still squeeze it in.
Annable: I just worry
about the quality then.
I mean, because even if he,
Tim, even if you locked yourself away
and wrote for a month, you know,
I mean that's a lot of pressure.
Schafer: Mmhmm.
Annable: I mean, Tim, do you
think you can do that?
Schafer: Again I don't
see a lot of choice.
Annable: I mean, it'll be a
gnarly schedule for everybody.
Hansen: All right. So why don't
we create those scenarios
and then we can share the, once this
group, and we can talk about it from there.
Schafer: Well, I better get writing.
Rice: Yeah.
Annable: All right. Whoohoo!
You can do it, Tim. You can do it.
Schafer: OK.
Annable: OK.
Schafer: All right.
Thanks for talking.
I wish I had more easy
solutions for everybody.
Annable: Bye, guys. Schafer: Bye.
Rice: Hi, Malena. OK.
I'm getting Bagel, too.
We'll see if he comes.
Tim is not coming today, you guys.
Kipnis: Why not?
Rice: He is in his office with a big
sticker that says "Do Not Disturb".
Melena says.
So he's writing.
No, he's actually, he's been killing it.
He's been cranking
through stuff really quick.
I think he sees the deadlines looming
and is staying really on top of stuff.
So I think if he keeps going
at this pace, then yeah,
we're going to have a good shot at it.
Yeah, he's doing his best
and it's coming in really nice.
It's solid now, so it's good to see.
Schafer: As long as we can survive
'til the end of the project, it'll be great.
I guess I gotta finish
my dialog before...
You guys get to talk to me ever again.
Schafer: Out. Out!
Just kidding.
Come in any time you want to.
Is that a good enough ending?
I'll do like this.
I guess it's just another day in games.
Schafer: Right, right?
I can close my door and I can put a
Post-it note on it and I can even lock it.
But just walking around the
office, people will be like, ah,
I need you to talk, I need to
talk to you about this thing.
And then that thing
spins into another thing.
And someone wants to talk
about another thing.
So many projects going on, so
many deals that I probably should be
helping with and you know, they
justifiably need some input or something.
But I just have to
get this writing done.
I just have to get this writing done.
So everything else
in the company's got to,
got to operate on its
own for a little while.
Schafer: We're here at
the Noe Valley Public Library.
My house is a few blocks down that way.
I've come to libraries ever
since trying to design Full Throttle.
I remember going down to the Sausalito
Library and sitting there and designing.
Sitting there with my
notebook, same exact thing.
And Grim I went
to the library a lot.
I actually did a lot
of research in the library,
just 'cause the Internet was
not full of stuff as it is now.
It's also nice to get out of the office.
It's a change of scenery.
I used to think like, on Full Throttle,
I went to the library and I
got so much done on the first day.
I was like, this is great,
this is my new secret.
And then I went down the next
day and I didn't get any work done.
It was like, what's going on?
And I got a lot of
work done in the office.
And then sometimes I get a
lot of work done in my home.
And sometimes I think
there's no one answer.
You just have to keep moving
around and shuffling around.
And I think in the end it really
in some ways doesn't matter.
You just have to like work at it every
day and some days you get nothing done,
some days you get a lot done.
But you have to do it every day.
[Music]
Schafer: Yeah, it's
coming along really fast.
I mean, they really are
working twice as fast as Act One.
And we don't have everyone
that we had in Act One.
Remember in Act One we had
like JP and Brandon, all these people.
This one's been on the gameplay side
just like Anna and Ben cranking away on it.
[Music]
Rice: There's certain puzzles
we should make sure to hit first.
Petty: I think we should hit the
stuff that we played the least first,
which is the radiation suit puzzle.
I would do that one first.
Rice: Cool.
Schafer: Sprint kickoff.
I missed the play-through
but I heard it was good.
Rice: The play-through was awesome.
Did anybody have anything
they wanted to say about it?
Schafer: It was particularly
awesome because I wasn't here.
Like everyone's like,
it seems so relaxed.
Petty: That was like a plus.
Schafer: Why is it so chill here?
I don't know what's going on.
Petty: I mean,
I think it was pretty solid.
I mean, the puzzles were, they became
clear in the play-through that the puzzles
were a lot more complex than
the first act, which was cool.
Game Tester: This is a good puzzle.
I have no idea what's going on.
It's going to be hard.
You need a pen there, Ben?
Peck: Yeah, I got one.
Petty: Because there are more
steps in them and the puzzles,
a lot of them aren't just say
using an object in a place,
but there's some trial and
error things you can manipulate
and see different results.
I think the separate puzzle chains
kind of weave in and out of each other.
So I think that,
that's where some of the,
I think some people would
describe that as difficulty,
which is true but I think
it's also just the appearance.
And, and actual
complexity that was maybe
missing from some of the
puzzles in the first act.
And part of that was by
design, both to ramp it up.
But also, you know, Tim, I think
in both cases from a story standpoint
or from a theme standpoint,
the character's kind
of start constrained
and therefore the
player's kind of constrained.
And they kind of break
out of that constraint.
And that means that it was just a
little more, there wasn't much opportunity
for the puzzles to kind of weave
back and forth through each other.
Kipnis: So what are
your thoughts, you guys?
Rice: It's fucking awesome. So good.
Kipnis: It's really long.
Peck: Yeah.
Rice: It's super fun.
Peck: I really love that last puzzle.
Rice: Yeah.
I think it's just like for my level
it feels like what we're hoping,
which is like much less
linear and spread out
and you're having to really
kind of retrace your steps a lot.
Petty: So I just realized
a flaw, though, right.
Like if you are playing the girl
and you take her all the way
to the end of her chain, and you
haven't seen the [spoiler-bleep]
'cause they're not part
of, we have to make sure
they're part of her critical
puzzle that you have to see them.
Because I'm thinking about this now.
You finished him and you
didn't hear [spoiler-bleep],
which is what she will need
to solve the [spoiler-bleep]
because it's not critical path.
And there's no way to go back to
it, 'cause you're in a scrolling thing.
Rice: And yeah, same with him,
same with her where if you've gone
all the way through and saw it
and just didn't notice it and then
now you don't remember the pattern.
Petty: Well, and this one is specifically,
you have to be able to go and test it.
And once we put you in this
mode, you can never go back.
Peck: Yeah.
Petty: So I'm not sure how we solve that.
Rice: That's a good question for Tim.
Schafer: Oh, this is, I feel like this might
be a horrible thing I don't want to think about.
Petty: Yeah, we're not
really sure what to do about this.
Schafer: It's just, you have
that, it works in play-test.
Petty: No!
Rice: It doesn't work.
Schafer: Now we've made it so
that you, Vella and Shay need each other,
like you need things from both
areas to work in the other areas.
And we did that on purpose, but
then we forget, well, we didn't forget.
We just failed to remember that
you can play one character completely
and then like in the first act,
you could play all of Shay and
then go play all of Vella or vice versa.
And since we made them interdependent,
we thought that wasn't a problem.
But if you shut down
this whole character
and go into that looping animation
that means their act is done,
you can't find the things
you need to solve this one.
So we're just going to leave
that in the unfixable state.
People will be just be like,
how far did you get in Broken Age
before you couldn't play anymore?
And there'll be like a leader board.
More challenge.
No more hand holding.
I just haven't figured out
a solution to that yet.
It's not going to be pretty.
Schafer: Instead of going into
the end state where looping,
if you haven't solved one of those
puzzles, they go into these other states.
Basically stalling.
Rice: At that point it does feel
like it's kind of closing people off
and a bit handhold-y.
I don't know. Yeah.
Schafer: OK, So we acknowledge that
that is a horrible problem for Ben to solve.
Petty: That we're
trying to introduce some,
more than just story relationships
between the separate characters.
And since we've only really
taken Shay's second act to Alpha,
the exact solution for
how to kind of play on those
and that gameplay impact
isn't really obvious
until we develop more
of Vella's side of things.
Rice: I'm really happy with
Alpha on the section we just did.
And I don't know, the rest
of development is super tight
if we're still trying to get December.
And I think that everybody
really wants to make it happen
so I think that if we can keep
pushing forward it should be,
at least we got a shot right now.
I think a lot of it's going
to come down to like
this next month and a
half is really important.
In three, four weeks we'll
see where the writing is
and hopefully if things look good
we can rally behind it and
push to make it happen.
Crook: I don't know. December.
What are we in, October?
November, yeah, no.
That's not going to happen.
As far as I can tell.
But we do not, I have
not heard another date.
That's the only date I've heard,
but I just think that there's,
there's too much work, I think.
As far as I can tell, there's
way too much work,
but that's kind of up to the
producers to figure that out.
[Music]
Schafer: The puzzles are
great, the writing is late.
But I've been getting some
more done, so everybody shut up.
Rice: Like we're just not moving at the
pace that that timeline has us moving at.
And now that we're getting
more and more writing,
we're having a better idea
of what it's looking like, too.
But yeah, I think that the conversation
of December is still conversation
that's happening and one that needs
to probably be had further, soon.
'Cause this is another sprint of like
pushing stuff off into the
next sprint as we have been.
Kipnis: The problem with Vella's side
is that there are a lot of like
mechanical or physical puzzles
that are like, I don't know if it's
going to communicate what we want.
Like I don't know if it's going
to work exactly like how we expect.
I just, I worry about the deadline.
Rice: I think it's true, I just
don't know if it's going to be able to,
if it's going to be able to affect
the timing or the VO sessions and stuff.
'Cause otherwise we're pushing
it off to where Camden seemed to get
dropped with a bunch of stuff and...
Petty: That sounds like
the perfect solution to me.
Rice: Well, and Ray
and the animators are just,
yeah, going to be looking for stuff.
Crook: Effects artist...
Schafer: Push him a little
farther until he gets grumpy..
Petty: Oh the effects
artist we're going to hire.
Schafer: Still trying to make December.
I mean a lot of it's hard for
people to commit to something
being done on a certain date
if a lot of things are unknown.
Like we don't know what
the final act is going to look like.
And like I can see it, but if they
don't know exactly what all the assets
are going to be, it's hard for them
to say it will be done by December.
But I still feel good about it.
Schafer: I, I think
I found it and brought it in
and left it as a gift for my producers.
Just to give them something I could
never actually give them in real life.
I mean, if we're not done in December,
we'd definitely be done in January,
that's the thing.
So it just seems like so
close, like why miss it.
Schafer: I finally finished
the Act Two girl dialogue,
so the spaceship dialogue is done,
which is exciting for me
personally, thank you, Anna.
Yeah, it's between us.
It's really important.
So now I'm just writing, I just to have
to write the finale, which looks like this.
Had a lot of spoilers right there.
Don't film that part.
Schafer: I got to finish.
I'm so close to being done
with the dialogue for the game,
which would be a
huge milestone in my life,
'cause all I can think about
is dialogue for this game.
There's a lot of dialogue in this game.
Offscreen Voice: So
why are you standing up?
Schafer: I'm standing up
'cause I had my gall bladder out.
I'm trying to act cool so
people don't know that I had it out,
but I don't like to sit down,
'cause if I fold the part where they
cut me open and take it out, it kind of hurts.
But that was on Friday.
And now it's Monday, I'm fine.
It's no big deal, gall
bladders are stupid, overrated.
Offscreen Voice: Is that
because of the juice diet?
Schafer: No one knows if it was
because of the juice diet or not.
Like some people, the
doctor said it's just genetic
and you're just prone to having
gall bladders, gall bladder stones, gallstones.
But my wife is sure it's the juice diet.
Offscreen Voice: So no more juice?
Schafer: I don't know.
This has been a long project.
I've been through many bodily
changes through this project.
Stress. It's probably just
stress, games gonna kill me.
Oh, my tush is going to hurt.
I'm going to sit. I have to sit down.
That pen's a goner, 'cause
I can't go down there and get it.
[Music]
Schafer: Last week we went
to PAX, that was awesome.
We didn't do a bunch of Broken Age
stuff 'cause Broken Age is all stealth,
Since we're showing
the other games.
Rice: A lot of people
asked about it, though.
Schafer: A lot of people asked about it,
a lot of people said they loved Part One.
Rice: Exactly.
Schafer: And that was nice.
Rice: I actually had a lot of
people say don't make it harder.
That was like the
comment and feedback I got.
Schafer: Shit.
Kipnis: Well, it's too late now.
Rice: Yeah, they're all talking
about how they like to play with their kids
and how it's a too great experience.
So, something to keep in mind.
Petty: It's a generational game.
[Garbled noises]
Rice: Creepy.