Ray: It'll be all right, Tim.
Hansen: It's all right.
We'll figure this out.
Tim: Are you saying I shouldn't do it?
Hansen: Don't do it. Don't do it.
Ray: We'll make it work.
Tim: You're just mad
because if I did this
it would not solve the
problem for you guys.
Hansen: It just makes it worse actually.
Ray: Yeah.
Hansen: That's right.
It makes it easier for you.
Ray: There're still pickup lines that
haven't been written, aren't there?
[Music]
Tim: I really am trying everything to
make sure the game comes out this year.
Ray: December. What are
we in, October, November?
Yeah, I know that's not gonna happen.
Tim: I gotta finish.
I'm so close to being
done with the dialogue
for the game which would be
a huge milestone in my life
because all I can think about
is the dialogue for this game.
There's a lot of dialogue in this game.
Okay, we're gonna start.
Weeklies, here we are,
back on the project.
Hey, guess what. I finished
all the dialogue for the game.
It's awesome. Yay!
[Clapping]
That's a relief.
Crook: Finally.
Schafer: Well, I mean you didn't have to
put it that way, but yeah, yeah, finally.
Crook: Someone had to say it!
I know I was going on my calendar today
and there's a big recurring appointment
for Reds writing and
I went and I deleted it.
Oh, my God, this is exciting.
I'm never gonna write again.
Never write again. Never write again.
So actually I'm playing
through the game right now
and I'm making notes of
what dialogue I need to write.
Other than that I'm totally done.
[Music]
And then Tim nobly finished
the last of the dialogue
and everyone was happy forever, the end.
And that's the end of that chapter.
Does anybody have any questions?
Broken Age, broken Age.
That's our rousing chant, broken age.
Bye.
Peck: What's new, man?
We have gotten a butt
ton of writing from Tim.
Crook: It's really good writing.
And the performances that
we've gotten back are really good
and so that kind of
puts the pressure on you
as an animator that you want to do that
writing and those performances justice.
So that's, that's pressure,
but good pressure.
It feels like things
are moving smoothly.
It feels that way.
Anna: We're like
finishing in record time.
We're actually ahead of schedule in
a lot of ways which is like, you know,
pretty rare for us because
usually we're pretty slammed.
Lee: Yes, I can show you some mockups
that we're working on in Vella, yeah, yeah.
This scene here is where Vella starts.
Players have already seen
this, you know, the split screen
at the very end of the game, and this
is kind of what that scene continues as.
And then this is the first puzzle
you see here is her skill here.
So this is a fairly elaborate
puzzle that the player has to hit,
and so a lot of this is just
breakdowns of how it all works.
So we have the Hex Pals are returning.
Of course. I love the Hex Pals
so I'm hoping to do
more with them this time.
I think the Hex Pals and the
Spoon, that stuff was all the big hits,
like the surprise, like everyone
loved these little side characters.
We have now heard a lot
more feedback on that first act
than you ever would if you
were just gonna release it at once
because it's been out in the
wild and people have lived with it.
We've lived it for a while so
we have more perspective on it.
Maybe that means the
choices we're making for Act 2
are just a little bit better formed
than they would've been if it was just,
you know, one big push.
And then just a lot of scenes in Act 2,
I can  walk you around some
of those if you want to see.
I can show you some
with the spaceship stuff.
So we've tried to go
through and make it look like
you're driving by the countryside
and damage some of the rooms.
Schafer: Exciting, really going places.
Petty: If you go in that doorway
on the left there's some ambience there.
Schafer: It's too bad we have puzzles in both
those places because it'd be funny to see
a room that was there
before and then just isn't there,
like so the door is open
like to the avalanche area.
No, we need that one.
Or to the like the friendship
circle where something just opens
and then it just like
[explosive noise] just space in there.
It could just be you open it
and it's just the shards of a room
and there's just a bunch
of yarn pals hanging on.
Aaahh!
They're just stuck out there.
Petty: I was thinking that
for any of the rooms like that,
that we should have the doors
and then continue on in animation state
where they can't quite close or open.
They're just kinda...
Schafer: They're closing
over a severed human foot.
Peck: There's some cool game
play that's like nonstandard stuff
where like you're
floating in zero gravity
and so like you play
around with the physics of that.
So this is one of those instances
where we were in a brainstorm meeting
and we were like what if
the whole ship just like rotated
because it's taking off, right?
And everyone was like, oh shit.
Offscreen: Once you solve that and
you get up here and the doors open,
that's when we do the;
and then we cut to the old scene
and now you're floating above it.
You're like, how do I get down there?
Schafer: So she
could be spinning.
So there could be a timing thing
that you have to do a certain thing
which is aim a certain direction.
Petty: We could have like the
boy's magnetic boots stuck on the hole,
you know, if we wanted
to use those somehow.
Schafer: And you just
like want to drift over to it
and grab it and use it to like.
Petty: Oh, wait,
there's a scarf on the suit.
So if you could take
the scarf off the floating suit.
Peck: Not exactly
your typical adventure game.
Walk to "A" to "B".
Crap, I missed it. It's a timing puzzle.
You have to like line up the
rotations of these two things.
Damn it. I missed it again.
I anticipate a lot of
amazing play testing feedback
from this with people
being like fuck that mini game.
We've also had to think
outside the box in terms of like,
especially because we're reusing
environments so we can't just make
a new environment that
supports really difficult puzzles.
We have to use the
environments we've already made.
And so yeah, we
consciously wanted to try and,
try and do things that
we hadn't done before.
Let's have a puzzle that
goes across multiple scenes.
Let's like rotate the ship.
Let's play with the fact
that we're on a spaceship.
We're in space.
Maybe there's no gravity.
There's this really weird
plot device that we have in Act 1
where like the mom could magically
manipulate everything on the ship.
What if Vella could gain
access to that system?
Like, that's a really
cool idea to pursue.
And like a lot of really great puzzle
ideas came out of that kind of,
that kind of thinking.
Kipnis: It's just like
ways to interact with the ship
or to see the same space
in a completely original context.
Schafer: And the
team is starting to wire out
the first few puzzles for
Vella on the spaceship now.
That's mostly what was going on.
Reds. Unless I forgot something.
Anyone want to do anything else?
Okay, now I have to go the bad
and not fun part of the meeting
where I have some bad
news to tell you about,
someone else leaving the
company which is never very fun.
Isa is leaving and oh,
man, come on up here, Isa.
Stamos: So I just want to let you
know I'll be cheering Double Fine on,
and I've loved my time here.
[Applause]
Schafer: Luckily we have Matt
Hanson who was our right-hand man,
and he's stepping right into the role
of being the VP of product development
so he's doing that job which
means he probably has less time
to do producer type stuff on Broken Age.
Yeah, I might
technically be short a producer.
I hadn't thought about
that. Now I'm terrified.
I'm never gonna
make December. We'll see.
That'll delay them in making that schedule
that says we can't make December so that
way I can hopefully get the game done
before anyone realizes it's impossible.
I think we're
gonna make December.
We'll never make December.
Shut up. Shut up.
Ow, that really hurts.
Peck: That's like
above my pay grade, dude.
Russell: Like, what do I think?
Just for me or the whole game?
Offscreen: The whole game I guess.
Malena and I think
it's gonna be March.
I'm not sure who thought ever
December was really gonna be it.
Offscreen: Tim.
Russell: Yeah.
Kipnis: Yeah, I don't, I don't actually
know the release date at this point.
I think it's gonna be largely
driven by how long it takes
for all of the animations to be final
because the animators are gonna be
slammed pretty hard since some of the voice
is getting into the
game so late unfortunately.
Schafer: Yeah, some of the VO talent
has been harder to get
in the studio than others,
and so you have a couple
big characters that have yet to be
recorded and that
holds up all the cut scenes.
We're looking at cut
scene layouts together
so that Ray can know
whether they're ready to go.
What's a layout, Ray?
Crook: A layout is a first pass
of the scene with the characters
all in their sort of place and
with the dialogue timed out.
Schafer: The rough cameras,
the timing, but none of the animation.
Crook: Yeah, none of the animation.
Schafer: Whipped Cream Hill fail.
Crook: She gets it too.
Schafer: Who did that one?
Crook: Miyuki.
Schafer: Is it the same?
Crook: It's the exact same rig, yeah.
I think it's funny that
it's exactly the same.
Schafer: If we can just repeat the
same, she can have a whole different;
I can't even think of a word.
Crook: I think the joke's funny because it is the same.
Schafer: Mm-hmm.
Crook: If you want something different.
Schafer: No, it's good.
And then we're just finishing
up on the Alpha and the G-2 act
and then we've got to do the finale.
Petty: It's a whole area, new characters.
It's probably a lot of cut scene work.
It's probably a ton of animation.
When it's not really a 3-D world and
you have to stage things specifically
and you don't want to
paint a million scenes,
a lot of it really comes down to exactly
what is going on in the
writing and the puzzles.
Schafer: Even though we haven't been
storyboarding a lot in the process,
like this would be
an important one to do
because I know Peter's already
talking about musical score
and that London, I mean that Melbourne
Symphony Orchestra gig is gonna come up.
And I think this would be a great
place to have special music
and not use existing cues and stuff.
So hopefully we can
actually storyboard it,
timing it out in the animatic
and commit to that, lock that,
and then have them build a score
to that while we're making it.
Do you want to go shot by shot then?
Okay, so that's the opening
shot, just like here's the situation.
It's happened.
And then we cut into an interior
shot and I was thinking interior
because I was hoping we'd just fake it
and it shows a bunch of red smoke because
like they're in the room that's the
hottest so it's like smoke is coming up.
Crook: So yeah, so this is the
animatic with Lee's storyboards.
It's very actiony, very dramatic.
It'll require some really good performance
from whoever ends up animating it.
To really just sit down and have a
big, juicy acting scene, for me that's,
I get the most enjoyment out of that
because that's when your
personality can come out in a way.
Yeah, it's gonna be a lot of work.
It should be.
Finales should always be a lot
of work because it's 3-1/2 minutes.
So that might not sound like a lot,
but that's actually,
that's a really long scene.
It's a really long scene.
Because if we're really locking
the timing down, which is kind of scary.
Petty: Yeah, I'm not sure why we'd
have to have the music scored
before we get the dialogue
unless the deadlines are such that.
Crook: I think the music scores,
because they're gonna be scoring
Grim at the same time, right?
Isn't that was this whole idea is?
Petty: Oh, is it?
Crook: I think that's what the deal is
because they only want
to book the orchestra once.
Crook: Isn't the idea they're
gonna book the orchestra once
and they're gonna do Grim
and this at the same time?
Crook: We were talking about whether
we could take it to the next level or not
which would be maya animatic.
Petty: We certainly can, but
there's a ridiculous amount of work
right now for all this other stuff.
And so it's just a matter of
where we're putting; I can't.
I have the storyboard.
I can't really describe
all this to Bagel
and then have him storyboard it
remotely so I have to storyboard it.
No, I mean, it can be done.
It's just; I think it just gets down to
the conversation we always sort of have
and don't have an
answer for which is date.
Petty: Well, it's the only
thing that a hard deadline.
Yeah, and then I've been working
with Vic on the all timeline stuff too.
Yeah, I think we're trying to put
together like a whole new pass on it
and we've talked with most of the
leads and everything already about stuff.
So probably within the next week
or so we'll have a, ooh, bless you.
Probably in the next week or so we'll
have a new full timeline to share.
I think it's pretty safe to say at this
point already that it's not December;
like we've already talked about
that with pretty much everybody.
Schafer: Not me.
Rice: Yeah, we've talked
about it multiple times.
Tim: Yeah, totally ambushed
me with that December thing.
Well, they've all been talking
about how they don't feel like we're gonna
make December and we probably
aren't, but I haven't seen any date.
You know, it's like it's all hunches.
It's all people's
hunches versus hunches,
but they're supposed to
be doing a waterfall schedule
which is like all the
dependencies linked out
and that will show us
ending a certain month.
And hopefully it's not April.
But it's almost like if you believe
it's going to be March then it will be March.
And if you're trying to hit
December it'll be hopefully January.
But if everyone's just like
we're not even trying to make December
then we'll slip even worse.
So it's hard to kind of keep a sense of
urgency on the project when you feel like;
because we're spending
our own money on it now
so it's not like a publisher milestone,
like the milestone's due in December
and everyone just
always takes that seriously.
And when we have something
that's an internal milestone
or a milestone that only
Double Fine is holding you accountable for,
people are like, well, we've
got an extra week and stuff.
And that's a hard, a hard thing
to instill that sense of like
taking a milestone seriously even
when it's just us because it's more money.
Every week that it goes
it costs more money.
And it's longer the backers will
have to wait and it's, you know,
the longer that we have to put
off other things we want to do.
So I still push for getting
it done as soon as possible.
Rice: Yeah, there's a lot of work left.
It's probably not gonna be December,
but we're figuring out when it would be.
It looks like the thing we're
thinking, we're hoping for December,
is we've got two more
weeks on Act 2 stuff,
and then the finale stuff
we're thinking is like six
for like a really solid safe Alpha.
And with all the like holiday stuff in
before the end of the year and everything,
that kind of takes us almost
exactly to the end of the year.
Then you have the
matter of closing it out
is what we're trying to
figure out now, so okay.
Annable: I could've told
you like a day back in July
it wasn't gonna happen for December.
Schafer: I'm gonna wait till
I see all the numbers.
Now it's at, well, we're really
close to when it should be wrapping up
if it's gonna be done in December.
We should have the voice in,
and we don't have the final three characters in.
We're doing that next week.
On Reds I am going down to help
with the VO recording which is happening
Wednesday, Thursday, Wednesday,
Thursday, Friday of this week.
That's for Vella.
Brown: I don't feel confident
about that at this point.
I'll be honest.
I'm more comfortable
saying what I really think
because I don't want
to say it on camera.
I'll just be totally blunt.
And I'll try to get us
out of the studio time
that we've purchased
for the next four days.
I'm working on it.
Crook: So Tim flew down to
record dialogue, Vella in particular,
and she had a family emergency.
And so that kind of
messes everything up.
I mean, it's not her fault.
People have family emergencies.
But it definitely kind of went
into panic mode a little bit.
Schafer: Do you see I made
a tiny gun to shoot myself?
It looks effective on camera.
Crook: There you go. That's better.
Open your mouth.
It'll be all right, Tim.
Hansen: It's all right.
We'll figure this out.
Russell: Vella, for her part of
Act 2 is in almost every cut scene
so there's very few cut scenes
that she's actually not in.
And if Malena has us
up to date as of today,
everything that's red
hasn't been recorded yet.
And you can guess who this might be.
This is Vella.
This is why we were
kind of freaking out.
That's part of the reason
why I made that document,
just to figure out,
okay, what can we do?
What can we sort of do and may
have to reanimate a little bit later?
And what's just, we just
have to have the voice?
Otherwise it's just gonna be tough.
Crook: So anyway we're gonna
animate to some scratch.
We're gonna not animate
some scenes with Vella.
It's gonna be a mixture of things.
We're gonna be juggling a little bit
and then hopefully the first week of December
that's what we've been promised.
The first week of December we'll
get the recordings done for Vella.
Tim: Which is really frustrating
because we're so late with that
dialogue and keep being even later.
It was nothing something
we wanted to do.
Annable: Waiting for her, at a
certain point it really, really hurts us
and I feel like we're already beyond,
like way beyond where we
need to be for her recording.
Crook: We'd have to kind of maybe
push everybody off of the project onto some other
projects because you don't want
to be sitting around burning through money, right?
We have to be working
on something all the time.
I mean, it all rides on
that December, right?
It rides on the recording
actually happening in December.
Annable: And so if she's not available
I think we need to have a second actor
cast who is also on hold for the same days
that we're putting Masasa
on hold when she returns.
And if Masasa is unavailable
then we have to go into the
studio with that backup person.
Schafer: A lot of people on the team
are saying we should recast,
should recast Vella with an actress
that we know we can get and be ready.
I'd be fine with it but now it just bugs
me to think of Vella having two voices
because there's no such
thing as a real sound-alike.
You can sound kind of like it, but I think
Masasa has a real unique voice
and I think players would just know.
They would play the first act
and then the second act
would have a different actress,
and it would be that way forever.
It would always be that way.
Annable: It sucks, but I
don't want an actor to be
responsible for causing so
much chaos to our schedule.
Schafer: So changing
Vella feels horrible to me
so I'm fighting for keeping
the original actress,
and I'm hoping she will
come through for me.
I'm going into L.A. again
to see if the magical gopher will come
out of its hole and record some dialogue.
We don't know what's gonna happen.
But I just go down and
we see if she shows up.
Rice: And Tim is reporting right now?
Has anyone heard?
Has he sent an email yet?
Crook: We know she showed up.
Rice: She did? Okay.
She's there. Awesome.
Crook: So that's a good step.
Schafer: Back to the booths.
Moyo: A really big explosion.
I like it when she
schemes.
Moyo: Hey, President Ugly.
Is that a dig or is
that actually his name?
Schafer: It's totally a dig.
You're pretty casual,
like, hey, what's up?
Moyo: Everybody thanks you.
[Music]
Hansen: So this meeting
is to talk about the schedule
for finishing the rest of Act 2.
So I've met with Vic and Malena and
Greg to talk through the remaining work
and to put it all on a timeline to
see when the thing's finishing.
This should be fairly accurate
because you're updated
this just recently, right?
Romero: This is every
discussion we've had,
every wonderful change to
our plans that's come up.
It's all on there.
Schafer: We thought it was going
to be April so this is actually good news.
Hansen: It's April to release the
game because it takes 3 weeks to manufacture.
But this is when development
will be done which is...
Petty: Manufacture?
Hansen: Yep, so we're gonna do physical disks.
Petty: Oh, that's right so it has to
be simultaneous now, right?
Hansen: That's part of the deal.
Bailey: So we did a deal with Nordic
which is yet to be released, but that's cool.
So our deal with Nordic is that they're
gonna handle retail distribution of the
game in Europe but also here.
So they have some relationships
with retailers like Best Buy
and other really huge big box stores,
and it'd be really exciting to see
Broken Age show up there.
The way it's actually working out
is once we're done with the PC
version we can ship it over to them
and they have a very quick, just a
few week turnaround which is exciting.
And during that time we're working
on the other platforms to get them ready.
So like, you know, when you bought it,
whoever's bought it on whatever platform,
the hope is everybody can
experience the conclusion together.
So that's the goal. We'll
see how close we get.
Hansen: So as you can
see this takes us basically
to the end of the year
to get the game to Alpha.
And then we would transition on to beta
work when we return from the holidays.
And then we have six weeks of bug
fixing and polish work at the end.
This is traditionally how long we've
needed for all of our projects.
There might be some room to pull that in
but I do think that the game
needs that much time
in order to address all of the play test
feedback, bug fixing and polish work.
Schafer: Have you gone over any
of this with Justin yet?
Hansen: Only the end date.
Schafer: What kind of face did he make
when you talked to him about the end date?
Did he smile?
Hansen: No.
Petty: So somewhere between
constipation and Defcon 4. Hansen: Yeah.
Schafer: He also only smiles
when things are really bad.
Hansen: It was not a
happy face. I'll say that.
Schafer: That's the thing.
The information, I'm just
wondering is what;
financially can we go to
this date or can't we?
Because before we were
talking about December
and he was kind of like we can't go
beyond that because of financial reasons.
And so that's what I would
like to hear from him
is what happens if we go to this date.
Hansen: Anything else? Tim,
do you have anything else?
Schafer: Some inspiring
words of wisdom. No.
Hey, guys, how's it going?
I'm getting a strong sense
people are trying to
give me the message that it's
a risk to hit December.
It's gonna be tight to make December.
That's just me reading
between the lines of that meeting.
Anyway it's gonna be over
soon one way or the other.
[Music]
Peck: You getting this?
This is good shit.