Schafer: Oh, Brad is out. Okay.
Hello everybody.
Hi. It's good to see you.
Hello. Thank you for coming.
So, uh, it's Monday,
and Friday was terrible.
Uh, all of you were here.
I want to just think everyone
for, uh, showing so much class
going through
that difficult day.
You guys all, um, uh,
held together nicely.
It was a rough day
on everybody
and, um, I think you showed
a lot of compassion
for the people who are leaving
and also understanding
for those of us
who had to make that decision,
and it really helped us
get through it.
And we will--we are getting through it, and it's, um...
Now we have a bunch of games
we gotta make and stuff to do.
Um, we are still
helping the people
who need letters of reference,
letters of recommendation,
stuff like that.
Help--doing what we can
to get them set up
with new engagements.
Um, but other than that,
we here are still
working on these games.
Did you want to talk
about the layoffs?
-Is that part of the documentary?
Talk about the layoffs.
I'm gonna have a drink.
Can I drink on camera?
If the kids are watchin' this,
kids, don't drink.
A week ago,
we had a project canceled,
an unannounced project
from a publisher
that really liked the game.
We had just done
our vertical slice
and then gave us
great feedback on it
and they said it was great
and they really liked it.
And then the next call
was they're canceling it
for higher-up reasons.
Well, that was a big project
that was funding
a lot of people.
And--and then another
one of our publishers
from another project is
having financial problems
and can't pay us.
Bailey: You know, it's public news
now that Majesco is, um...
Pardon me.
Not timed there.
Majesco has made
a public statement that
their, you know,
continued ability to perform
as--as a going concern is
at stake and, of course,
we did Costume Quest 2 with them
and the payments were
not complete for that.
So we're actually--
we're owed money
by Majesco that
we're not getting paid.
And then, of course
Costume Quest 2, um,
because of that statement,
you can infer
that it's not being
marketed properly
and it's not being
distributed to its fullest extent
that you would expect from
a publisher, because there--
you know, the means and
the people there to do that
just don't exist anymore.
Um, so it's kind of
a perfect storm.
It was a bad week
to put it mildly.
So, glad that week's over.
If that publisher
hadn't canceled it,
you know,
things would have been--
were looking really good
for the studio.
Um, I think things are still
looking really good
for the studio,
but only because
we took quick action.
Schafer: So we had to let go
of 12 people.
Some of them, uh, had been here
for a short period of time
and some of them had been
here for a long period of time,
over ten years.
So that was really hard.
Stoddard: What do you want to know,
how I feel about them and--
Off camera: Yeah, yeah, how was it?
I mean you--
Stoddard: It was horrible.
-Yeah.
It was really horrible. Um...
I mean, I understand
why it happened,
but, like, we--the audio team
was super tight, uh,
and now there's two of us instead of four.
Um, it was a heavy hit.
The day of the layoffs
were just brutal.
Kipnis: Uh, well, I will say
that the layoffs--
I wasn't actually at the
office when it happened, so...
And, um, at first,
like, I--I got--
I got text messages about it
and it was, uh...
it was really tough
to--to hear about it, um,
and it--it was tough to, like,
not be here to say goodbye
to some of those people
that I've worked with
for years and years
and, like, you know,
I'm gonna miss a lot.
I don't know what else to say.
Crook: And you always feel a little
bit guilty when you're still here,
you know,
and other people aren't,
um, and it hurts morale
quite a bit, um,
but...
but I know that it--I know
that it was not taken lightly.
Hansen: It was the hardest
day of my life.
I never thought we would be
in that situation,
but project cancelations
happen and, you know,
sometimes you can absorb it
and sometimes you can't.
So Tim and I almost
avoided each other
just 'cause we knew that we had
to meet and talk about that.
And I didn't want to,
and he didn't want to either.
There was no, like,
oh, yeah, it's so easy,
it's person X, Y, and Z.
It's like every single one
of those people are--
they're huge contributors
to all these games we've made.
They're the people we hang
out with after work and so--
And, you know, and it's tough
for Double Fine in general,
because historically, I mean,
we even said this
in the media in the past,
we don't do layoffs
and that sort of thing.
It was--it was
a tough decision for sure.
Russell: A lot of us just stayed
afterwards in the room,
after we were told,
and just talked about
the history of the company,
and just, we were like,
we couldn't believe
this happened to us,
but you know,
in the game industry
and in any entertainment industry,
it's--it's the norm.
We're the exception,
so in that respect I--
I--I feel lucky,
and we'll survive, a little bit
smaller, a little leaner,
but we'll make it.
[Music]
Schafer: So basically we are
powering forward on our, um,
uh, remaining titles
that we're working on.
Those are the stories
I really wanted
to make the documentary about
but we could never
do that, like,
those publisher games,
to see, like, what it's like,
all those meetings where
they're saying,
"This game is so great,
we can't wait to see it."
And then the meeting where they
actually said it's canceled,
we have to cancel it,
but I hope you still make it
'cause I really want to play it.
That was an actual quote
from the guy,
he was like,
"If you make it
I really want to play it."
It's like, "Oh, thanks,
that makes up
for me laying off 12 people.
That--I totally feel good now
that you want to play this game
that you just killed."
But, um, since I'm mostly fueled
by angriness and bitterness,
then I'm stronger than ever right now.
You know, whatever works.
[Music]
[Chatter]
Schafer: Oh god, is that thing still here?
Mitchell: It's way funnier now.
Muir: It was just sad.
Mitchell: Yeah.
Muir: It wasn't bad.
Mitchell: No.
Schafer: That one that you
found under the sink?
Muir: It's really good.
It's like, uh...
Mitchell: It's gooey, though.
Muir: Chipotle.
Schafer: Is everyone here?
[Murmuring]
Hello, everybody! Hello.
And thank you for coming back
to work here again
for another year.
It's awesome to see you
all here.
Welcome back.
Nice to see you all.
Rice: Yeah, man.
2015.
Schafer: 2015. Wait a second.
Does that mean
we didn't finish in December?
Rice: Yeah.
Comin' on three years.
Schafer: Three--no kidding?
It's like Rip Van Winkle.
All I remember is
the Kickstarter,
and then I woke up
and it's three years later.
Crook: And we all have big, long--and
we all have big, long beards.
Schafer: Yeah, we're just here
with beards.
Ray, where did all that money go, what?
I guess we should
ship this game.
But the game was awesome.
Um, but, um, but we--
I think I'm trying to this week
still keep play testing,
especially the problem areas
in the game
where people get
hung up the most
and catch any
remaining dialogue.
There's probably some object
interactions or examine lines
that are still missing
that I would love to catch.
Please keep talking
and don't be freaked out
that we're not answering you,
'cause we'd just like
to hear what you're thinking.
Miller: All right.
I'm already baffled.
Vella: Is this one?
Miller: This must be
incredibly fun to watch.
Schafer: We're not even here.
Miller: What's that?
You're not paying attention?
Schafer: Yeah, I'm doing my taxes
over here.
Miller: I think I'll switch to Shay
'cause I can't figure this out.
Schafer: I mean, it's--it--that--
the first puzzle,
it's, like, one of the first
puzzles that Vella has,
and you have to do something
and get this visual feedback,
and you have to mess with it
a lot and get some more feedback
to kind of figure out
the patterns.
Um, and then it's
just a problem of, like,
have we kind of inceptioned?
Is that a verb?
Put the idea in
the player's head
of what they want to do enough.
'Cause sometimes
you just mess with the game
and you just kind of bang on it
and you--woo, you solved it,
you don't really know
how you solved it.
And that to me is almost
a worst-case scenario.
That's almost worse than
getting stuck forever, you know?
Like, getting--
'cause being stuck forever,
if you finally solve it
you feel great.
But if you solve it in accident, you're like,
I don't know what just happened, you move on
and you kind of get
this kind of bored feeling.
And it's really easy to just
accidently put
this one line in
that makes everybody just
know what to do immediately.
So it's--it's like a lot of--
'cause time--time is short
and we don't have much--
we don't have much time left,
and to solve these problems,
to make sure that everyone
gets through the game,
it's really tempting
to just kind of, like,
short circuit all the puzzles and make sure
that everybody
can get through them.
But you have to kind of
take a lot of time
to actually really look,
um, carefully at, like,
each mental leap
the player is making.
[Off camera] If people were saying
the first one was too easy
and you're taking out
a lot of the hints,
I mean, are you afraid you went
too far in the other direction?
-It seems like there's a lot--
Schafer: Well, I'm hoping--
I'm hoping we went way too far.
Rice: But yeah, like Tim said,
in general I think
we're gonna keep play testing
in hopes that
anything that we find
that is a problem
down the road
could be changed.
Crook: Are we gonna have--
with--with Ben leaving,
are we having any other--
another GP coming on
or are we gonna be able
to just absorb?
Peck: Um, well, it's my second to
last day here at Double Fine.
And, uh, just trying to, like,
put a bow on as many things
as I could
before leaving.
The place I'm going to
is quite a bit--
it's like a larger company so...
I'm--yeah,
I'm gonna miss the...
like, the small little scenes
at the lunch table
or, like, company meetings
and stuff like that
where, like, it's okay
to make a dick joke
or, like, it's okay to...
to just kind of be yourself
a bit.
Um...
I'm hoping I can kind of take
a little bit of that for--
like, with me wherever
I go, you know?
I feel bad I'm not gonna
be there for, like,
when the shit inevitably
hits the fan, you know,
and the game needs
to be finaled.
Kipnis: That jerk.
No, I mean, it sucks.
It sucks. I mean, Ben--Ben contributed a lot
to the--to the game
and, you know, we're--
we're having to kind of
figure out some stuff in the code
that he wrote when he could
have been here to help us out.
I mean, it sucks, but, um,
we'll just have to finish
without him, you know?
Crook: I mean, I will say, you know,
we've had to transition
because, um, Lee left
the project
and, um, that was--
that was scary, um,
because he--he seemed to know
what was going on
with everything.
And so I think Anna's
had to take on a lot
of some of the responsibilities
that Lee had, um,
as far as puzzle chains
and--and how those are
all put together
and--and the logic.
Um, so I'm sure that's
been stressful for her.
[Offscreen] Do you regret not getting to
see Broken Age through to the end?
Petty: Yeah, you know,
I'm trying to think.
I think this is the only time
I haven't stayed on a project
all the way through.
It was a lot of those, um,
small decisions
right at the end of the project
that have a big impact
on the game
'cause all the content's there
and it's all connected.
And sometimes just
pushing and pulling a few things
can--it, um, can
really help the game,
and it's nice to be
part of that.
But, uh, I don't think
I'll be part of that
for Act 2 anyways, but--
I think I'm--I'm excited
for Act 2 to come out,
because I think Act 1 had
a lot of great things about it
but it was incomplete,
and, you know,
you can sort of see the whole arc
or play the whole game,
might get a better sense
of whether
that was successful or not.
But hopefully I've helped
set that up, um,
to be a--to be
a great experience.
Schafer: But we don't need anybody.
Broken Age team.
We don't--
we don't need nobody.
We'll finish it ourselves.
So where are we supposed to be right now,
Alpha on the finale?
Rice: Yeah. You wanna look at the...
Schafer: When is beta on B2 and G2?
Is that there?
Rice: Yeah, so we'll show you
the timeline as it is right now.
Um, but Matt and Vic and I,
and Malena
are gonna meet
this afternoon now, uh,
and want to get
a lot more clarity
into just closing out
the project,
but also, like,
these beta sprints
and--and things like that
as well.
Hansen: Right now there's a tendency
for people to gravitate towards
whatever is the, you know,
maybe the most interesting work,
and that's not--
might not be the most, uh,
highest priority work.
We just need to do some load
balancing and some estimates
as far as, like,
how long is it gonna take
to get this shit done,
'cause people--
if people don't tell us that,
we might be fucked already
and we don't even know it.
Rice: Um, but, yes, Ray,
you're correct.
The, um, the right reaction
to this is,
it's a lot to do in two--
in two months and change.
Crook: Yeah.
Rice: So, um, I think
that's why we wanted to
make sure that these dates
get in front of everybody's
eyes and that people
are looking at it differently.
Hansen: Is it reasonable?
I mean, or are you--
or you're like,
I don't know, man,
'cause your gut checks
are usually pretty good.
Crook: Wow.
Yeah, but I think it's--
I think it'd be all right.
Do you think the GPs
are gonna be--I mean,
'cause there was a time where
there were gonna be
four of them.
Now there's two of them.
Rice: We're getting all the
box stuff ready to go
and actually manufacturing
in, like, February, um,
to where discs would
be pressed in mid-March.
Kipnis: Yeah, and the game--does
the game run on the PS4?
Franzke: Nope.
Kipnis: Yeah.
And--and I think it's really important to have a,
"Okay, Tim, this is it,
like, you can't..."
Hansen: Yeah.
Kipnis: Like, absolute content complete
from, like, Tim content
complete maybe.
Hansen: Last call for alcohol.
Kipnis: Yeah, last call.
Let's just call it that,
last call.
It's really hard to,
as a creator,
to turn yourself off.
What I want to do is
be able to account for that
and I want Tim to be able
to do that.
I want him to be able to, like,
"Oh, God, this is it,
that's right,
I can't add anymore after this."
And I want him to be able
to, like, have that time
and account for it
in our--in our milestone,
like, timeline and stuff.
Because I want him to be, like,
happy with what we come up with.
Because we know
his creative process,
it's important for us to
schedule it appropriately.
Rice: Yeah, um...
Kipnis: Yeah, I didn't realize,
like, how soon the beta was.
Jesus Christ.
Rice: Yeah, and I don't know, Matt,
like, right now every--
there's a lot of hands on Grim,
but, like, obviously that's
just a near-term problem
that's being solved soon.
But after that, um, yeah,
I don't know
what kind of, uh, strings
we can pull with people
on other teams, um, as needed.
Hansen: They can't. I mean, we
have milestones. We won't get paid.
If we don't get paid
then the studio shuts down.
Rice: That's what I thought.
So I was just making sure
that that was the case.
Hansen: I'm just gonna be totally
blunt with you guys,
but you can't touch
(redacted).
Kipnis: Yeah.
Hansen: I'm sorry.
Franzke: Yeah.
All right.
Rice: Cool.
Franzke: Let's make this happen, huh?
Rice: Yeah.
All right.
Like, you guys are the
right people to ask about this.
Like what--what does gut say
about the timeline?
It's basically two months
till pencils down.
Inversin: I'm not totally scared just
yet, but I might be terrified.
We'll see.
[Offscreen] Did you get to learn
anything from Lydia
when she was still here?
Panya: No.
She had a lot of
the Act 1 shader stuff,
so, like, her signature's
over everything
so I can pick up where
she left off in that sense.
Uh, but she's not here for me
to kind of ask questions.
Scheduling with effects
is always kind of scary,
'cause there's always this,
you know,
four-week window
at the end for polish,
and, of course everybody
wants to polish at the end,
even design wants to polish,
and that trickles down.
Animations get tweaked
at the end,
and then visual effects
and sound effects
are the last two guys to
kind of get, uh, to touch it.
So as long as everyone
knows that the sound effects
and the visual effects guys are
last and they give some buffer,
then we shouldn't be too,
uh, too screwed.
Stoddard: I want to make sure
German gets hit
because we have
to re-volume graph
and re-special effects process
all of the German recording
for Act 1 and Act 2,
and that's a tall order.
Rice: Yeah, and it's getting
delivered beginning of February, right,
and then don't we--is the plan
to have outsourcer on it
that should take,
like, three weeks?
Stoddard: We--yeah.
Hansen: We have Ashley coming in.
Stoddard: Yeah.
Hansen: And she'll be, uh, helping...
-...specifically for this work.
Rice: Yeah.
Schafer: I would like to ask you
to join me in welcoming
Ashley Coull to Double Fine.
There she is over there.
Ashley.
Coull: You know, a contract.
It's a short amount of time
and, you know, there--
there's no--there's no guarantee,
and it was a staggering amount
of work as well,
but, uh, the opportunity
to be here
and be a part of
this community, uh,
Camden even pulled me out--
pulled me out of work one day,
and I think he got about halfway
through the sentence of, "Hey,
so there's this contract thing,"
and I was like, "Yes."
And he was like, "I--uh,
yeah," and I was like, "Yeah."
Um, and that's kind of how--how
the balls got--got rolling,
I guess.
Schafer: Because we have German VO
in the game, which is awesome,
and it sounds crazy.
I started playing it.
I mean, I don't mean
crazy, I mean
in a language
that is not my own.
-German Vella: Hallo?
Schafer: There we go.
[Coughing]
That's a German cough, obviously.
[Disproving sigh]
[Laughter]
I really like the German version. I'm gonna
play through the whole thing
in German.
Stoddard: Yeah, that was--
that was a--
the was a big, big thing,
so she's just--
she's kicking ass,
Paul is kicking ass.
He really is stepping up.
I mean, it's like kind of
both their moments to step up.
O'Rourke: I mean, it's always enjoyable.
Tim's writing
is hilarious most of the time
and it's really good to just--
like, usually when I'm editing--
I don't want to talk bad about,
like, sports games or anything,
but if I had to edit, like,
Madden dialogue all day,
probably kill myself.
But going through Tim's stuff
is actually pretty enjoyable.
Um, I gave him a huge cut scene
the other day.
Dude, here's a big moment,
go do it,
come back when it's done.
And he came back
and it was damn near perfect.
Like he nailed it, so I'm like, okay,
I'm not worried anymore.
The layoffs were not good, um...
It's definitely--
This--this company
is under stress.
Everybody is being super pro
and they're making good product,
but, like, it's--
it's heavy duty right now.
And I'm just really happy to
see this team kind of gel,
uh, you know, in the trenches
and really get it.
Me?
(speaking in German)
[Offscreen] What was that?
Franzke: I--what?
[Laughter]
Coull: Uh, I said I'm editing
all the German lines.
Franzke: Can I read--
can I read this?
[Laughter]
Franzke: Oh.
Rice: We've gone through this now
with all the leads, yeah,
but, um, yeah, now we wanted
to present it it to you.
The next week is--
Schafer: Last set call.
Rice: Huh?
Schafer: Tim last call...
Rice: Yeah, we'll get to that.
So like, tomorrow the hope
is during stand-ups
to, like, relay this whole
thing to the entire team,
not just the leads.
And I feel like
we gotta kinda give, like,
a bit of a sense of urgency
and just, like,
that kind of thing.
But I feel like it's also trying
to put people's fears to rest,
which would--I think one of
the big ones is that,
like, we're gonna continue
to iterate on the game...
-...and things like that.
Schafer: So terrify them with
the deadlines and put
all their fears to rest.
Rice: And then hopefully,
uh, just pep rally,
pump people up?
Schafer: If we use the words
"dig deep" at any point, I'm just--
Hansen: Will you say it?
Schafer: No.
Rice: No.
Schafer: There's always a point
where someone talks about digging deep,
and I just--
I don't want to say that.
So we all gotta dig deep,
you guys.
Hansen: All right.
Rice: Yeah, I pro--
I think I might put the dates
on the whiteboard again, too,
just so everyone can look
at them all the time.
Schafer: If they view that,
they'll film it.
Rice: Yeah, red, white, and blue.
Romero: That's encouraging.
Broken Age, fuck yeah.
Schafer: Does that help?
Romero: Tim last call.
Is that a milestone?
Rice: Fuck yes.
Romero: Okay.
We submit to ratings boards
on the fourth?
Rice: Yeah, I think it's that--
Kipnis: When do we
know what line...?
Crook: Tim said he would try
to call him. When he said
you're hitting the line,
it's okay.
Maybe I just gotta
try to find one that...
Rice: Ready? So we've been meeting
production team with the leads
to come up with
closing plan stuff.
So next Friday we have
our next Sony milestone,
which Oliver is working on.
I think the big thing is
PlayStation 4 running.
Schafer: Is there anything on there
new or shocking to anyone?
Crook: It's all shocking,
but nothing's new.
There's nothing new.
Schafer: There is a lot of stuff to do
in a short amount of time,
but there's no big unknowns
to me, at least, on it.
There's no design yet to do,
dialogue yet to write,
and big ques--
things that could
explode into--
I mean, like, it seems like it's
a known amount of work now
that can't expand,
and, um, and it's clear
that it can't slip
because you can see
the commitments that are on it.
As far as I'm concerned,
like, everything is just no--
everything just has to be
pushed through the machinery,
and that's the easy part,
except for it's hard.
No, we're--we're the dream team,
all here together.
For some reason,
to me it's always relaxing
when it's finite
even if it is tight
because you know when
it's gonna be over.
These next three weeks are
really where the game goes
from being good
to great mostly.
So, um, it's gonna
be exciting
and, uh, if we have
to order food,
we'll order food.
Crook: Food.
Boston Market?
Schafer: No.
Crook: Promise Boston Market, I'll--
Schafer: Wait, you want Boston--
Crook: I'll work late if you--
No, I'm just kidding.
Kipnis: Wow.
Crook: Just kidding.
Schafer: If you've gotta lure
a man away from his family,
make it
Boston Market.
Crook: Yeah.
Schafer: It's like there's
love in that meal.
Kipnis: That's--that's what
Caroline did for us
during Psychonauts.
Remember that?
Rice: Boston Market?
Kipnis: Boston Market,
like, every night.
Crook: Yep.
Kipnis: And, uh, and I gained--
I gained, like, 15 pounds
during during crunch.
Schafer: That's to keep you in your seat.
[Music]
Schafer: Uh, on "Reds," we did a
whole play-through of the team
of the finale of the game
to figure out
how to push that
towards, um, completion.
We are also starting
on the PS4 version.
Hansen: So we have a milestone
on the 23rd,
and that's to have it, like,
"playable," um,
on that platform, so--
But it looks like that's
come along really well,
so good job, Oliver.
Schafer: Look at it playing on the PS4.
[Offscreen] How's the port process
been going in general?
Franzke: It's good.
We essentially added
PlayStation 4
and PlayStation Vita
to a list of platforms,
but kept the ship date the same,
um, so that makes things
a bit more interesting.
I love working on consoles,
but it's a very different
kind of challenge, like,
for example, the Vita is
very memory constrained,
um, so that, you know,
it's--it's a very tight
memory budget for--for the game,
and if you're just leaking
some memory somewhere,
like, you're gonna have
a bad time later on,
so there are, like, a lot
of really interesting things
you need to take
into consideration.
Or can you compress the data
in some way and stuff like that.
And I think the end--
the end will be tough,
for sure, shipping.
Like, so, for--for consoles, um,
what you have to do
in order to release games
is you have to go to something
that's called certifications.
The next milestone is
on the 20th, which is--
like, it's very ominously
called, like, beta
which is supposed to be
TRC complete,
uh, essentially for Sony
so there's a lot of stuff that
needs to happen before that.
Those are all
the requirements you need
for shipping a game
on a--on a Sony platform.
Schafer: I'm sure we're TRC complete.
Franzke: Oh, yeah, no problem.
Um, so they will
essentially, like, run a game
and make sure that every one
of those requirements is met.
[Offscreen] How does stuff like
Assassin's Creed happen?
Oliver: Uh, I'd rather
not comment on that.
It's really sad, because
I'm pretty sure all the people
who worked on the game,
you know,
didn't want to release
something that's substandard.
Um, so very often, it's--it's--
actually really sad
for the developers,
but there's a lot
of, like, pressure
from various departments
to make the game happen essentially.
Are you feeling some form
of pressure like that now?
Well, I mean, but if you--
if you don't have a publisher
who's, like, does what,
uh, needs to happen,
but as you can see,
everything is so tightly packed,
uh, that there's really no time
to slip any of those milestones.
Franzke: Yes, please.
-Okay.
See, crunch has
already started.
Schafer: Yeah, we're getting
near the end where
some nights people
are working late
and we're ordering food,
and, um...
and hopefully that won't be
too long till it's over.
And people who are
staying late now, it's 'cause
they want to make sure
the game is really good.
[Music]
I know the biggest hurdle
is just the amount
of work there is to do.
Uh, we have to do a whole bunch
of cut scenes.
Still have to go in.
Crook: Camden there was
the issue with, uh,
Bob Chothra
coming out of the mountain
that we were gonna--
did you talk to Tim
about that and Peter?
I don't know about--
I'm in that scene still.
We're making some changes,
so I just--
Stoddard: Okay.
Schafer: Just saying that
gave Ray a headache.
Offscreen: How is the ending
cut scene coming along,
since that was sort of, uh--
that had to be--
the music had to be done,
so that was kind of locked.
Schafer: Yeah, yeah, 'cause we kind
of locked it, but I feel good
about the pacing of that,
just based on the music.
Um, and it was so big we had to
split it between two animators,
Miyuki and Chris Lam.
So Miyuki was doing
the first half
and Chris was doing
the second half.
And then we're gonna
stitch it back together.
Oh, I like that.
That's a good idea.
Crook: Yeah, that was really good.
That's cute.
Richardson: Like, uh, so
many characters, and...
and it's kind of a big thing, right?
It's ending,
end of the game,
so that's kind of exciting,
but still goin' like,
"Ooh, that's
a lot of things to do."
Crook: Maybe not the happy eyes?
Lam: No.
Schafer: Yeah, like, the delirious eyes,
like yay, he's more like...
Hm.
"You run, I got this."
Crook: All right.
Schafer: "Save yourself."
Thumb's up.
Crook: Yeah, he got that on film.
We might need to...
Schafer: This ping pong ball, his face.
Lam: The parts that I have to do
that are kind of those,
you know, resolution moments,
they're gonna be
a little challenging but--
to get the expressions
on the characters right
so that you know
that they're thinking,
they're not just staring into
dead space and stuff like that.
Crook: Think you got enough info there?
Okay.
Lam: Yes.
Crook: The plan is to just take it
to that, um, shippable stage.
And then, uh, that will allow
all the effects and the sound
to get put in, um, 'cause all
the timing will be locked down.
So the--the plan is that
they'll go back to it, uh,
to do some polish, um,
after we get all the content in.
Schafer: Is this a good time
to look at it?
It would be a good time
to look at it, yes.
It doesn't--sometimes it
seems like in that whole thing,
there's not a shot that shows--
that really shows
the entire scene.
Schafer: But, I mean,
you know what's left
and you know what's right.
Crook: Yeah, like, this is
the only shot we have.
Rice: That's the shot
that shows most--
Crook: What--uh, I don't know.
I just kept thinking that, like--
You could almost do--
Rice: if it's a flip book,
you could almost--you could have
other people that we don't know
that are on the sides
from both villages.
Crook: All these people, like here.
Schafer: But where do they come from?
Crook: Well, they came from...
Rice: From the monster lands town,
like, there's a big battle
going on.
They've come to gawk.
Crook: That's fine.
I mean, if you're--
But we--but we can't--
we don't want...
-...to animate more people.
Stoddard: Yeah, yeah, I know.
Rice: But that's what you're saying.
Schafer: It's really important
not to add features to the game
at this point Ray.
I like the melting
you're adding.
I wouldn't jump to
that melting platform.
Crook: Yeah, that's true.
She has no shoes.
Camden: She's tough. She's a baker.
Crook: She walks on coals.
Schafer: She doesn't use
oven mitts anymore.
Oh, that's good.
That's perfect.
So I think this would be--
this needs something here.
Inversin: It--it has something, not
in this scene, but there is--
I can--I can move it into that scene also if you want.
Schafer: 'Cause it seemed like
he was backing up from nothing.
Inversin: So, like, it's in there, too,
so I can add it to the other one.
Schafer: I just think it--think it
could be, like, half as much?
Crook: That looks really cool.
Schafer: It kind of explains
why he jumps now.
That's perfect. I think that's
perfect as far as the rain goes.
-Awesome.
-Yeah.
-Then we're done.
That was easy.
Boop boop. Yeah,
that was really good.
Thanks.
Oh, crying for us.
Crook: Yeah.
[Music]
Rice: But we're finally now getting
down to-- to final days, I guess.
[Music]
Crook: But, yeah, we're all a little
on edge, a little stressed out,
but, um, it'll be okay.
Hansen: Anna's here almost
constantly, and, you know, I can--
I see the light at the end
of the tunnel.
We love these games,
but, you know,
we all kind of need
to take a break.
And people need
to get some sleep, too.
It's been a rough few months.
Crook: I mean, we're gonna be
pushing to the very end.
[Off screen] Like that guy there.
Crook: Oh yeah he is.
I think he didn't go home
last night.
But apparently he has, like,
a little bed over there.
So I'm just like,
that's not a good thing.
Stoddard: I don't want
to romanticize it.
I know--I know
that Tim wants to show
how the sausage gets made,
and this has been--
this has been hard.
Schafer: We're also getting
kind of griefed
by, um, certain
fringe organizations
and attack groups organized,
and, uh, that was a bummer.
And then we had the layoffs
which were a huge bummer.
And, um, a bunch of bad news.
Rice: There is, like, a group
of people that are hoping
that we won't succeed
for some weird reason,
um, or that are at least
heavily scrutinizing us.
And it definitely has been
something that's been
weighing on a lot of people.
Franzke: The endless thing of,
like, people, like, oh, well,
maybe they shouldn't have
taken the--the money
and only make half the game.
Well, you know,
all I can say to that
is, like,
if you would be,
like, we're sitting here,
you know, working our asses
off to make this game.
Kipnis: And, like, you do,
you question yourself.
Like, yeah, maybe we--
what the fuck,
maybe we don't know
what the--what we're doing.
Who knows?
But you just have to trust
and know, like,
this is actually--
game development
is not an easy thing.
Schafer: And now we're gonna
ship Broken Age,
and that's all gonna be great.
So, um, it's a relief
to get out of that--
out of that period.
[Offscreen] What's going on right now
at this stage of the project?
Romero: So where we are is,
we're less than a month out
from our first submission,
which is the, um,
where you submit to Sony
and we release
the mastering for the PC,
physical copies
that we're doing with Nordic.
So the 20th is the big day
where just everything
has to sort of
be done by that point.
Rice: Uh, yes, I've been working on
some Nordic stuff, too,
along with Vic. Um...
We got the box prints
from them and they just
look a little bit dark
so we're doing, like,
another round on those
before they actually start printing them in bulk.
Uh, but hopefully
that'll happen soon.
Schafer: But we don't get a sample
before they make a zillion of them?
Rice: No, unfortunately.
Schafer: Exciting.
Rice: Yeah.
Schafer: That's exciting.
This is just one of Cory's
mock-ups of the box.
This is the box.
This is--the disc's not
gonna look like that.
I wanted the disc to be
the O from Broken Age.
This is gonna be like the O,
and that's the box.
And we're first looking at it, we're like, this is cool
'cause it shows the split thing,
but it really overemphasizes Vella over Shay,
'cause Shay's upside down
so he's, like, easier to ignore.
It was like,
wouldn't it be crazy
if we could print Vella and Shay
on a separate clear slipcover,
and then you could slide it off
and turn it around
and slide it back down
and then Shay would be
in Vella's world and vice versa,
Which, no spoilers, but that's
some foreshadowing there.
And it would be so neat.
It would be like Led Zeppelin.
Rice: We'll nail it.
It'll be great.
-Um...
Kipnis: Wow.
Romero: So right now the big tasks
are-- or the big areas are bugs.
O'Rourke: Yeah, we're in
Starship Troopers mode basically,
just killing all the bugs.
Schafer: Taking showers
together or what are you--
Coull: No.
Schafer: I'm sorry, that's...
not the first thing
I think about.
O'Rouke: There's the
daily shower scene
in the audio room.
Kipnis: I'm a little bit concerned
about our deadline.
Like, right here it says
A and B bugs only.
Like, that's not likely
gonna happen,
especially since
we have brand new cut scenes.
Schafer: Starting now or next week?
Kipnis: Next week.
Uh, that's likely not happening
because we have a bunch of
new, um, cut scenes coming.
Content is still coming in
and we can't actually do that
until all content
is in the game.
Schafer: What's this
selective bug fixing?
Almost sounds more open-ended
than A and B
'cause we select to do a C.
Right, that's how that works?
Kipnis: Nope.
Rice: I don't think so.
Kipnis: But if you play the game
all the way through, um,
from Act 1,
that Act 1 is very clean,
and we have to make Act 2
look that clean,
and that's a lot
of C-bug fixing.
And so, like, we can't
suddenly switch
to A and Bs only next week.
Like, it's just not--
it's gonna be
basically like a, I don't know,
not a very clean game, I guess.
Romero: Uh, Act 2 is interesting
because we're not just doing PC,
Mac, and Linux digital,
um, we're doing physical,
when--and really that goes back
to the old school way,
which is you get to the point
in the project
where you're gonna
ship a physical disc,
you have to cut off bug fixing.
You have to be certain that
the build you're shipping
is the one,
because someone's gonna,
in theory,
buy the box and get the game,
and that has to have all the,
you know, be bug-free as--
as bug-free as possible
and as solid as possible,
so they'll just have the disc and
the game that's on there.
That's it.
Kipnis: I don't have
confidence at the moment
that we have--we're really
at the bug count that we are.
Or, like, I--I expect that
the bugs will increase tremendously,
or should, because I think
they are in there.
Romero: They're still there.
Kipnis: Yeah.
Franzke: It's still gonna be good,
like, I mean, this game
has been out for such a long time, I think
it's gonna be stable
and it's gonna be good,
but there's always, like,
so much more
that we would have liked to do
and, like, we're now
at a point where
that's just not
gonna be possible.
We need to, you know,
make sure that
the game is stable.
You know, you look--
you look at your bug database
and you list some issues
that you have in there
and it's, like, a lot,
and it's like, how are we gonna
be able to--to finish that?
We'll have to probably do
some bug triaging next week
to just see kind of, okay, well,
all of these issues
that are in the bug database
right now,
which one are we realistically
gonna be able to even do now?
And then they have to--
there will
have to be
some hard decisions.
It's like, okay, well, we can
only do one or the other,
so which one of these issues,
polish items is more important
to you?
And then we're gonna do that
but not the other.
And it's just the nature
of the beast.
[Music]
Hansen: Resources in 12.
Schafer: That would be great.
Uh, and yeah,
we'll have to re--
and I mean, obviously,
analyze the bugs every day
and how they're tracking.
Are all the GPs back
from sickness?
Hansen: No, Anna's still out.
Stoddard: Two down.
Hansen: But--
Schafer: She's gonna be out today, too?
Hansen: She's trying to get
some medicine that'll
allow her to work this week,
so she's that bad.
Schafer: Holy cow.
Crook: She was working
really late hours.
I think she was probably--
Her immune system was already
pretty vulnerable,
and, um, and she--she
got whatever, I don't know.
I hope--I don't know,
she hasn't said.
She went to the doctor.
Hopefully it's not pneumonia
or something, but, um,
hopefully she'll be back with us on Monday.
But--but we know that
the most important thing for her
is just to get better.
You know,
it's just a video game.
You know, she's, you know,
her health is
the most important thing,
so, um, so that's why
it's been great.
Everyone has just jumped in
to try and help out,
and nobody blames anybody
for anything.
-It's just one of those things.
Boehle: I'll probably just filter,
like, Anna's open or new bugs,
like, priority two and higher,
and then if there's anything
UI related,
I'll just grab those and--
Franzke: Right.
Yeah, I think we have to.
I mean, it's just kind of--
sounds like Anna's
hit pretty hard.
Hansen: But it's still difficult
because, you know,
there's a lot of ownership
over the code,
so Anna will be able to get
something done a lot faster
than anybody else just 'cause
she's so familiar
with all the inner workings of
how this stuff is all hooked up.
That makes it more difficult, for sure,
'cause all the pressure's
on her right now.
Rice: I guess at least through
the week and then,
I just--I guess I wonder
when we're gonna get
to other platform work,
but for now it's obvious.
It seems like this is
until we're locking stuff down.
Franzke: I mean, like, whenever
there's an actual
pre-cert issue
coming in from Sony,
I'm jumping on it right away
because I want to get them,
like, fixed as soon as possible.
But so far it's been
pretty good.
I think actually
not that many bugs
been reported from pre-certs.
Rice: So, yeah, whathaveibeenworkingon?
We have a couple things.
Today we set up a bug triage meeting
with all of the leads.
So, um, producers
and leads and Tim,
are gonna kind of read through
everything in the bug database,
reevaluating where we are
with that.
So that'll be happening
this afternoon.
Schafer: Hey, everybody, hello.
Rice: Hi.
Schafer: This is probably the
last meeting of the project, right?
Rice: Um...
Probably not.
Schafer: We're so close.
Rice: Big one, though.
Rice: It's a big one.
Franzke: Apart from the meeting
where we get
all the royalty checks?
Schafer: Yeah, that's after.
That's after.
We have to ship it first, Oliver.
But yeah, so we're gonna
look over the bug database
and see if we can get rid
of some bugs.
Rice: I think the hope is really
just trying to get an idea
of which ones
we definitely need to fix
and which ones
might be okay to drop.
And this is specifically for
the date in two weeks from now,
which is like pressing it
to the disc for PC.
So I guess it's, like, what are we
gonna not feel comfortable
having fixed before
that disc is pressed.
And how bad is the situation right now?
'Cause I'm hearing things like
the bugs aren't gonna be fixed
by the ship date and all that.
I mean, from Vic's last email,
it sounds like we're tracking
about half the speed
um, that we would need to be
for fixing these 250.
Um, I guess it's just, like,
what's the line we can draw
where we're comfortable that it's a solid build
that's not gonna crash
that gives a good experience.
And, yeah, maybe there's,
like, some polish stuff
that would have been
nice to be in there
but at least it's in
versions that get patched.
Hansen: I mean, every game that ships
ships with bugs, period.
They're--I mean,
it's just unavoidable.
You can keep testing a game forever.
It's just you have
to get to the point
where you feel like
you found things that are--
you know, that most people
are likely to run into
and you've addressed
all that stuff.
Rice: Then, like, there's
certain cut scenes
when you interact with things
in the spinning mode where
she'll then just not be spinning
all of a sudden and talking,
then it'll go back into
spinning, like--
Schafer: I haven't seen that.
Rice: You haven't seen that?
Schafer: Okay, we should find those.
Rice: I just saw it, like,
last night, so...
Crook: Oh, okay.
Schafer: What stretching arms show?
Crook: When, the wakeup scene?
Schafer: Mm-hm.
Crook: The arm--It happens twice,
when it grabs him
and then you can see
at the very top,
you can see, like,
the arms are all wacky.
Like they're all stretched out and weird.
Schafer: Is it really ugly?
Romero: Is that...?
Rice: I think I've seen it.
It's like the top point
is off the side and then where they come in.
Schafer: If you were a player,
would you say that's
the science fiction, uh...
Crook: It's a sliver of, like,
pulled out stuff.
Franzke: It is a potentially really
risky fix, though, because touching--
Getting that camera
to work right in that scene
was--we spent weeks--
Schafer: It's not just reposing
the hand?
Franzke: Right. And I really would not
feel comfortable
messing with the cameras unless
we really have to because...
Schafer: Would you fix it with
the camera or fix it with the animation?
Crook: We can try and change
up the animation--
Schafer: But you can't just
straighten up the arm.
Crook: That's a scary scene.
Schafer: Hm.
Crook: We are trying to take things that maybe--
small things that
we normally might ask
the game play programmers to do,
uh, we're trying
to fix those things ourselves
just because they're so swamped.
But we're not programmers
and we have to be careful.
We don't want to break things.
So I'm kind of learning
a lot of things.
Um, I'm learning a few things
about game play programming.
Schafer: What if Ben Peck
is super miserable
at his new job?
Has anyone called him lately?
Crook: I saw--I saw him at GDC.
He looked a little miserable.
Schafer: Yeah, see what I'm saying?
Crook: That was only 'cause
Anna was giving him mean looks.
Franzke: I saw him on Friday
and he seemed relatively happy.
Schafer: Wait, can we see how many
of these we have to go through?
Romero: Uh, so we're at 155.
The bottom goes
all the way to 252.
So we're about a hundred away.
Schafer: Oh, my God.
Hansen: We don't have a lot of time
in general,
so yeah, in aggregate,
all that stuff is a lot of work.
'Cause what we're trying to do is, like, get to a point
where
we've addressed everything
we're gonna address
and then have the game sit
without anybody working on it.
Just--it's just sitting just
in QA for, like, a week.
And that's the hard part
'cause we--
we've already
eaten into that week.
And so we're kind of faced with
the decision now of, like,
do we just work up
to the deadline
and just ship what we have?
And there's a huge risk
involved with that.
But even, like, the small,
minor polish bugs,
it's like,
you get enough of those
and it does make a huge impact
on the quality of the game.
Schafer: Yeah, it looks really bad.
Um, when we print this disc,
how would people get the patch?
Franzke: Steam.
Schafer: So that's the only way
to get the patch
for their disc-based version
of the game is by using Steam?
Franzke: Yeah.
Schafer: They can't download it
from our website
or anything like that?
Franzke: Our infrastructure--like,
we would require to have
some kind of login service
for people to register accounts.
Schafer: That could be
a huge consumer thing
of them saying I need to--
in order to get the patch,
I need to join Steam,
and I don't want to join Steam.
I bought this disc.
Franzke: Yeah.
Schafer: So it's not like
in the old days,
where a patch was just a bunch of LUA files
that you could just
unpack into the directory
of your game
and it would fix it?
Franzke: We could, but we have
no infrastructure
for that right now.
Schafer: On the server side
or in the game?
In the game would have to have that kind of--
Franzke: We right now have no software
to create an incremental patch.
Schafer: People are gonna freak out.
Rice: Yeah, well, we don't want
to have to support
a whole 'nother platform.
And, like, it would mean, like,
building ground
up an infrastructure
for them to be able
to sign in to something.
For us to be able
to host something,
for us to support a whole 'nother platform.
Schafer: Well, I just think
the other stuff is--
like, just 'cause it's
hard for us doesn't mean
we're not gonna have to
deal with it as a company.
You know what I mean? Like, as
a huge community or PR problem.
Rice: This was a red flag
waved as soon as we said
we were gonna do a box copy.
Franzke: Right, I mean, that's one
of the first things we talked about
is how the patching would work.
Rice: Yeah, well, we can
handle it case-by-case
and give them a DRM free
code whenever we have to
for GOG or whatever
if you think people care
that much about DRM.
Schafer: I mean, probably be they
wouldn't notice all these things
like a flicking shadow
or something under the seat.
But it's just that people who
buy DRM free copies of games
are like, "I'm not signing on
to anything.
I don't want to sign on
to Steam."
Rice: Right.
Franzke: They hate--they hate Steam.
Schafer: And they were loud
about that until we made
the DRM free version
of the game,
the first game, so...
And then what happens
if we ship late to Nordic?
What does Nordic do
if we ship late to them?
Rice: Uh, the disc is late,
then all the dates shift.
Schafer: And then what happens?
Rice: Then all the dates shift.
Schafer: And then what happens.
Rice: Tell Sony and Justin's mad,
and, yeah.
Rice: Yeah? I'm just trying
to balance that out
like how bad it would be if--
okay, anyway.
Maybe they wouldn't notice issues.
Rice: This is why we never wanted
to sim ship a disc.
This is why we wanted to, like,
have the game out there,
have it be patched and finished
before we did. So as soon as
we signed a contract to sim ship,
we knew it would mean
either finishing it all
and having this period
or having a build on a disc
that wasn't fully patched.
Schafer: Say we slipped the
disc date by two weeks.
Does that mean moving
that revenue out of the plan
for two weeks
is Justin's problem
or that there's something
bigger with Nordic
where they have a truck idling
in the loading dock
for two weeks?
Rice: It's that. They want us to
right now announce a date.
And Sony wants us
to commit to a date.
Everyone wants us
We've been holding it off because
of all these
moving pieces.
Schafer: But it sounds like we already
are committed to a date
if we're saying
we can't slip it.
Rice: We haven't totally,
but we should and that's
what he wants to know.
Schafer: Why don't we just
move it two weeks
and then commit to it?
Rice: 'Cause I don't know
that Justin can.
They've been talking--
so there's, like,
million pieces in place.
Schafer: Like, these are all the
ones we know about.
I'm talking about there's a bug
that we ship on the disc
that is, like every--
it's like the elevator, Manny
locked in the elevator bug.
Rice: Okay.
Schafer: Everyone's posting vines
about it all over, it's all
over Twitter the next day.
And everyone's like, everyone's
freaking out about this bug.
Say I can't this patch
'cause I bought the disc,
or I was dumb enough
to buy the disc version.
You know, and it's just like
we're ripping off everybody
and that's the story.
And if it's that on one hand or
slipping the date by two weeks,
I would slip the date
by two weeks.
But I want to know what's
the consequence of that?
Rice: Yeah, we'll talk about it after.
Schafer: Yeah.
Romero: Uh, all right,
almost to the forest.
Let's see.
Rice: That was the first
thing I thought
when we had that conversation.
I was like, oh,
is there wiggle room
in their production schedule
for, uh, the box?
And I looked, and no, their
drop dead is, like, the 24th.
And that's why they
wanted it on the 20th
so they could, like,
prepare everything.
Uh, so it would mean pushing
the box date out, which I think,
since it would be our fault
for delivering a build later
that we'd have to push everything.
'Cause I think, like, if we
delivered the build on time
and they were the reason
that the box showed up late,
then we could have shipped
and not have it sim shipped.
But, um, yeah, we have
to sim ship with them.
Uh, so, yeah, it would mean, um,
moving all the other stuff,
which is possible.
It just is, like, going back
to everybody and making sure
that they're okay with it.
And especially since
Anna's been out all week,
it's made it even trickier.
We've got, like, all the other
programmers piling on now
to try and help out.
So that's helping,
but, yeah, I mean,
I guess we're still gonna
end up with looking like
at least another week or two
of game play bugs.
There's just also this
unknown question of, like,
is there a big bug
that we're missing
that we don't know about?
I think that Tim is
a little bit worried about,
like, our patching solution
on the disc, too,
and even if that's, like, um,
gonna be well met by customers.
Yeah, I guess the question
is whether
we are gonna be okay with
now rolling out
to all of our partners
and potentially having to
move it back a week or two.
Bailey: Yeah, I mean,
that's problematic.
We--it's in our best interests to
stick to the April 28th date.
Rice: Mm-hm.
Bailey: So, um,
it's just there's not a
whole lot of wiggle room left.
Rice: Yeah.
Hansen: Yeah, he's trying to--
he's trying to lay out
the whole thing to Justin.
I mean, honestly,
what we've got to do
is present options for Justin.
You know, there's pros and
cons for each one of them, right?
And it's--we need to make
a business decision on this.
Bailey: Because it's a double hit
for us to, like,
take on more expense for
Broken Age to go a week longer.
But then also not
to have the money
that's being brought in, so...
Hansen: You know, Tim's
already made his decision,
but, you know, Justin needs
to weigh in on it also
because there's a lot
at stake for this, so...
There's ramifications
of all these decisions,
but, I mean, we want to push
for the one that's gonna give
the highest quality game
at the end.
Rice: Yeah, the question is
whether we can maybe just
push the date back of starting
burning all of those discs
and still make the 28th,
because the rest of it
actually looks like
it's kinda on track for the 28th
as far as digital release across
all of our other platforms.
So I don't think that really
affects the digital dates.
Hansen: One week of bug fixing
and then one week of--
you know, nobody's
touching the build.
Rice: Yeah, exactly.
Hansen: It's just in QA.
Rice: If we can go to them and
see if they can move their date
for manufacturing back
and not touch the final date,
then that seems like
it should be good.
Bailey: Okay. I mean hearing this,
you know, you're probably right.
Let's just go ahead and, um...
I think it'd be good to maybe
just even get a call
and just get all the major
stakeholders on the line at once
and then we can talk about
what the date's looking like
and then talk about some stuff
that we can give as well
and figure it out.
Hansen: I almost don't want to, like--
the way we phrase this
is kind of important
'cause we don't want to, like,
ask them as much as like,
we have to do this.
I don't see an alternative, so.
Bailey: We're just telling them.
Hansen: About getting them onboard.
Bailey: We're like, "Hey,
we're in the production,
you know,
so we're definitely not
gonna make the five weeks
that's, you know,
ideal for you guys.
Hansen: Yeah.
[Music]
Um, so I guess
we can start any time,
uh, any time you want.
Bailey: Um, are you guys okay--
we have our camera crew.
They want to film this
for the documentary.
So are you guys okay
with being on camera,
or your voices being on tape?
Nordic Rep: Sure.
Bailey: The bad news is that
we had about a five week, um...
On your production schedule,
it had five weeks out
when we actually gave you guys the build,
like, for us to actually
get the build to you,
and for you then to be able
to get this pressed.
So with the bugs
and other things
we're running up against
now, it looks like--
I don't know if we're
gonna need to go
right up against that deadline,
but we're gonna need more time
than the five weeks
we planned for
in that schedule
you guys sent over.
Rice: I think the date
we know we'd be confident
at having a stable build
ready for you to press disc
is April third.
So, yeah, I guess that's
where the question comes in is
if there's a little bit more
wiggle room on your guys' side
to try and push back that
disc pressing date a little bit.
Nordic Rep: So you're saying
April third would be ready
to replicate, right?
Rice: Yeah.
Nordic Rep: Well, I mean,
that would give us enough time
for an April 28th release.
Bailey: Good.
Rice: Cool.
That's what we were hoping.
Bailey: Yay.
All right.
Rice: Okay. So, yeah, I guess
we just didn't know
if there was, like, buffer
built into that schedule or not.
Nordic Rep: I mean, it's tight, you know.
Rice: Sounds great.
Hansen: That'd be awesome.
Nordic Rep: But let me--you know,
if we can--you know,
if that's a reliable date,
if April 3 is reliable,
you know,
then I'm cool with it, you know.
If we actually do have a
master going into replication
on April 4,
you know, that works for us.
-Okay.
-But there's no--
I mean there's absolutely
no buffer in there anymore.
Rice: That's what we figured,
but that sounds great.
I mean, I think the team's gonna
be excited about that for sure.
Bailey: And having you guys in
here as well, you know,
this could be probably
the biggest launch
I think Double Fine's ever done.
Nordic Rep: Very good.
Bailey: Yeah.
Exciting time.
Rice: So April 28th.
Hansen: Yep, April 28th.
Bailey: Awesome.
Nordic Rep: All right.
Hansen: Yeah, yeah, it's--
we would--
basically it would be
pencils down on the 27th.
Rice: Cool.
Hansen: And then we'd just--
it just cooks in QA after that.
Rice: Right.
Hansen: That should be really good.
We'll have a really solid
build at that point.
Rice: Cool. I mean, it seems
like best case scenario.
I didn't think they were
gonna be so easy to move.
It's 'cause they had that
buffer, waiting.
Bailey: I think the camera helped.
The camera probably did help.
Bailey: Thanks, 2 Player!
Hansen: Yeah.
Schafer: Okay.
So I heard that I could
add a character.
Yeah, okay. No, that's awesome.
Hansen: Maybe....two characters?
Schafer: That's really good news.
I did not want to go into this
knowing that we'd have to ship
depending on a day one patch
for basic stability.
So that's much better.
That's awesome. Thank you.
Hansen: So this week's really important.
So we need to make sure the team
remains focused and we are
reviewing the bugs constantly.
Rice: Sweet.
Cool, and Nordic's gonna be
putting testers on it, too,
looking at German.
Perfect.
Coull: So, um, yeah.
Rice: Awesome.
Sounds good.
Almost there, man.
Almost there.
-I know.
Hopefully everyone
will make one more week...
-...and we'll be, uh...
-All right.
She's in.
She's in right now.
Yeah, she just got here.
We should go talk to her.
Hi Anna.
Kipnis: Hi.
Rice: Are you feeling better?
Kipnis: A little bit.
Rice: But they could turn around
in three weeks they said, so --
If it got to where we had
to move it to the third,
we probably could.
Yeah.
Kipnis: Well...
Rice: Well, I'm glad
you're feeling better.
Kipnis: Yeah.
That was the worst week
to have missed of work.
I mean, of all the times
to get sick.
I would get emails every once
in a while where I was like, fuck.
Well, I felt like I was
letting the team down,
but that the game wasn't
gonna go in the toilet
or anything
while I was out so...
Yeah, I mean, it's nice to
really trust your colleagues.
That's a good feeling
that they actually, like,
took the time to do it
and stuff.
That's, I don't know,
that's great, too, so.
Hey, I'm still not a
hundred percent right now,
but, um, I--I feel confident
that we'll--
you know, we'll make it,
especially with the little bit
of extra time that we got.
Rice: Sounds good.
Crook: Okay.
Rice: Good plan.
Boop, boop, boop.
Yay!
[Music]
Crook: Yeah. Yeah, I'm just
excited to be done, uh, soon.
Three years.
Kipnis: Yeah, it, uh, it's great.
It feels weird.
It feels weird
that it's almost done.
It's the strangest thing.
Franzke: Yeah, it is kind of weird.
It's kind of weird to--
Well, it's kind of weird
that it took three years.
I don't think--I don't think
we kind of thought
in the beginning
it would take that long.
[Music]
Schafer: Well, you know, three years
is not that long for a game.
People will laugh at that,
but Brutal was four years.
Grim-- I mean Psychonauts
was five years.
Grim was three years, so it's
the same amount of time as Grim
with a smaller team
and less crunch mode.
Grim was really, like,
six years if you count
all the evenings that we worked.
Um, but it's weird--it's weird
to look at the old episodes
and just think about how
long we've been working on this
and how different it felt
in the beginning.
[Music]
Look, Broken Age alumni.
We're wrapping it up. We're
remembering the old people
like Levi.
Ryken: Hi, everybody.
Rice: We miss you.
Schafer: Hello, everybody.
Can you remind us, Greg, where we are,
what's the schedule,
and what will be happening now?
Rice: So the next thing is
locking down the build,
which is happening
at the end of the week.
Franzke: So really, it's not actually
all that super glamorous,
but essentially what you
can see is all these files here
that have the exclamation mark on it.
And what that means is that
these files are different
from the version of the file
that's already in that branch.
So that's the release
candidate branch
and so I just say accept
this and it will say okay.
That means I will
overwrite all your files
that you have right now
and then just let Perforce
do its thing.
Have the little guy walking,
which is still my favorite--
one of my favorite icons
in terms of tools.
This is really
a lot of programming,
and especially
release engineering
is just sitting around
waiting for files to be copied
and for certain operations
to be performed on files,
which is just kind of weird,
like one would expect that,
you know, shipping a game
is, like,
super exciting kind of stuff.
But really, in the end of a day,
it's a lot of copying files
from A to B
and sitting around waiting
for those files to be copied.
Um, all right.
So now we essentially have,
like, all the yellow
exclamation marks are gone,
which means we now
have a list of files,
all the files that were changed.
And I'm just gonna say, okay,
I want to commit these
into the release kind of branch,
so I'm gonna say
integration from main.
And this is actually
also lock down,
so I'm gonna say
content lock.
Oh, I actually have
to spell it correctly.
And then I say submit,
and that's essentially it.
So now we grab all the files
from the main line
and copy them over into
the release candidate branch,
and we lock down the build.
Rice: Right now all the, uh,
disc stuff is basically
off to Nordic
and on their plate,
so that should actually go
into manufacturing this week.
And they said they said
they're gonna talk
with us for photos
and gonna update
as they go along.
But this should be
tracking towards
same day launching the disc
as the game digitally.
Schafer: I know what you're
saying, why are you
wearing luau clothes, Tim?
-Yeah.
Rice: Why are you wearing--
-No, it's pretty normal.
Schafer: I am wearing both
pants and luau pants
because tonight we are going
to have a bonfire down at the beach
to celebrate the completion
of Broken Age, everybody.
[Applause]
Yay!
He's like, son of a--
about fucking time!
Yes, okay.
It's just about done,
right, Oliver?
No way it could ever bounce
out of cert now?
You only have time to
eat now during meetings.
Yeah! Yes!
[Music]