Schafer: Hi, guys.
How's it going?
This is the last one
of these we'll ever do?
Offscreen: Yeah.
Schafer: Seems like
only yesterday I was
saying all that stuff,
sitting in this chair
that I can't
remember now,
'cause it's been
so long ago.
Offscreen: Mm-hmm, we talked
about that initial budget
in that chair.
Schafer: Don't bring that up.
[Laughter]
Yeah, it's just--
it's this one,
and then it's, ahh!
[Music]
Schafer: Tonight, we are going to
have a bonfire down at the beach
to celebrate the completion
of "Broken Age," everybody.
[Applause]
Yay!
Teamwork!
It started out like
a really fun idea,
and then it got really hard.
And a bunch of people
wussed out,
but a lot of people
stuck around to the end.
I wanna thank you,
thank you to the whole team,
and thank you everybody.
We're done!
Like, we went to the beach,
we had that party,
things got a little out
of control.
[Yelling]
And it's fun, it's fun
'cause it's, like,
not fixing things
right at the last minute.
We kinda had it done
in advance a little bit,
at least for--
for me and us.
Like, it was, um,
wrapped and submitted.
Like, we had to submit
for the disc version,
and that kind of actually--
it was tough,
but it forced us
to have a lot of stuff done
before the, um,
actual launch date,
'cause we had to have
that version burnt to disc.
And so, um...we had to time
to kind of, like...
adjust to the thought
of it being over.
Um, so, Reds  is done
and it's awesome.
The end.
Rice: It's done?
Oh my God.
That's kinda sad.
We sent review keys out
to press for "Broken Age,"
so there's already, like,
10 or so folks
that are playing
for review.
With the amount of time
that it's taken
and the amount of things
that have happened
in the last three years
is, uh, staggering.
And, um, it was nice to see
everyone care enough
to push for
a final product
that could be something
we're proud of.
Crook: Um, so yeah,
it just, um,
it kind of all came together
at the end.
Um...so I feel good right now.
Offscreen: You feel good about it?
Crook: Yeah.
I think it's beautiful,
and something that
we should be proud of.
Uh, I think people
are gonna really like it.
Russell: Yes, we're finished.
See, I knew it would happen.
And after 13, 14 years here,
you know stuff's
gonna get done,
and it'll be great
in the end.
It'll be all worth it.
Schafer: Rusty.
Russell: I'm playin' through
and fixin' bugs.
Schafer: Well, thanks for playing.
Russell: Mostly playing.
Schafer: Mm-hmm.
Awesome.
What do you think so far?
Russell: I got confused, actually.
As much as I played through--
-I was--
Schafer: That's not good!
Rice: It's not a
scripted cutscene,
so you wouldn't know.
Russell: Yeah, exactly.
Schafer: Excellent, did you figure
it out, or did ask for a hint?
Russell: I had to ask Ray.
Schafer: Oh...
-Oh...
And also, look,
it's running on, uh, iPhone 6.
-Thanks...
Rice: Not anymore.
Schafer: Not--b-but--it's a black screen.
Oliver!
Oh, spoilers for "Act 2"!
Okay.
Anyway, it's running.
Franzke: But, yeah.
As you can see, the game
is running a little thing--
This one just crashed,
but it does work.
I am extremely proud of,
you know,
the product the way
it is right now.
Um...and, yeah,
I hope it will stand
the test of time.
Schafer: And then we are
on the street
on April 28th.
It'll be awesome.
Um, and Anna's alive.
Look at that, everybody.
Yay, Anna's alive!
Yay!
Kipnis: It feels--it feels good.
It feels like, uh, we did--
we did something good
and worthwhile
and something
that hopefully will, you know,
uh, have a--
I don't know, a future?
Like, have a legacy
of some kind.
Schafer: I really, uh, felt good
about the second chapter.
You know,
I feel like it answered
anyone's critique
about the first one,
you know, without changing
the game completely, you know.
I think it definitely was,
you know, harder and longer,
and, um, and amazingly done
in less time, so...
Stoddard: I did my first full,
full playthrough last weekend,
and it is a hard game.
It's really challenging
and it's really well-done
and it's engaging.
Like, I've worked on this thing
for years and I still--
like, the story
was still getting me.
It's pretty good.
And when I hit
the final scene,
like, man, dude,
it's, uh...
it's cinematic.
It's like it hits you.
Definitely.
Um...so that felt good.
I just had to have
a moment to...
start loving it again.
I mean, like, I had this point
in here where, like,
the love I have
for this just kinda
got knocked out
for a few days.
And that was really scary.
That was really scary.
And, um...
It was hard.
Schafer: We're going to
our last stand-ups?
Is it last stand-ups?
I believe it is.
Hello, everybody.
Oh, look at the big--
Did we not get bagels
for the final stand-ups?
Crook: Ah, I didn't try.
Schafer: Come on!
It's our last one.
Get your ass off Bagel.
I brought this
for emotional support.
In case I get emotional.
Crook: Just keep hugging it.
Schafer: I'm not gonna get emotional.
Crook: Squeezing it, hugging it.
Schafer: I doubt it.
I doubt it.
We're not done.
Are we?
We done?
Crook: This is the last standup.
Schafer: You playing right now?
This game is so addictive.
Cannot put it down
for one second.
Um...this might be--
this is our last proper standup
for the full team,
but, uh...
don't worry, I won't give
a speech or anything.
And then you always have
this post-project depression,
which is, like, you've defined
yourself by who you are
by making this game
for so long,
and then it's over
and you're like, "Who am I?
Am I not the person
who makes 'Broken Age'?
What am I?
What's the point of it all?"
Crook: Before, when we were
just doing, like, a big game,
it would ship,
and then the whole studio
didn't have anything
to do for a while.
And every--I think every--
the whole--
You could kinda feel that
in the air
and it just kind of--
it was just--
it was kind of a downer.
And, uh, because there's
multiple projects now,
we can all just
jump onto things,
and that helps--
helps you,
uh, I think helps me,
get out of that.
And so that's why
there was a need
on "Day of the Tentacle."
Um, so now--
now I'm on to that.
Um, I'm--I hear
it's really bad
for people who are
leading the project.
Uh, but Tim doesn't--
I mean, he doesn't show it.
He's pretty good with hiding,
I think, his sadness.
But, um...
He's just sad all the time.
No.
Uh, but I'm sure he--
I'm sure it will hit him,
you know,
because this is three years,
uh, put into this.
Schafer: No, I don't get depressed.
I'm too old to get depressed.
Offscreen: Don't you have any
sympathy for all the people
that have been insisting
the game will never finish?
Schafer: I do--I do feel bad
for all the people
who have based
their identity
on the fact that I'll never
finish this game.
'Cause we'll finish it
and then they'll have
post-project depression.
If I'm not that person
who hates Tim Schafer,
who am I?
Excellent.
Thank you. Panya's
last standup, for sure.
Inversin: Yeah, for sure.
I'm out this week, guys,
so it's been a pleasure.
But, uh, uh, yeah.
Crook: Go inside, Victor.
You're next.
Schafer: Yeah, nice try, Victor.
Crook: There you go.
Romero: Almost.
-Schafer: All right, we'll miss you,
Panya.
Victor!
Crook: Yep.
Schafer: Victor.
Romero: I'll miss you, Panya, uh...
Schafer: Oh, shipping games
is always tense,
and then afterwards
there's this moment
where if there's
ever gonna be
any turnaround
in the company,
it usually happens
at that moment,
'cause people hang on
to the--they want--
everyone wants to finish
the project they're on.
That--so that's
usually the period
where people
will come and go,
is--is in that period.
Okay, everyone,
thanks for coming
to dailies
all those times.
It's over.
Next project.
Rice: Yay!
Crook: That's it.
Stoddard: Man, he's sentimental.
Crook: Yeah.
Coull: So.
Sad panda- I'm leaving.
Um...
What else do you want
to know about it.
No, I mean, um,
the contract was supposed
to come to an end anyway.
The fact that it went on
a month after was pretty--
pretty awesome for me.
You know, maybe they'll
need me again in the future,
but, you know,
you can't be certain, I guess.
Schafer: Oliver is
still cranking away
on the final
final versions of it
to get it out the door.
And then Oliver will be moving
back to Germany, sadly.
I think some of you know this;
we've talked about this.
Oliver is--the--
the--the pull
of the fatherland
is too strong.
He must go back.
Oliver wants to move.
He's gonna keep
working for us,
but he's gonna
move to Germany.
But he's gonna be working
on "Day of the Tentacle."
So you don't have
to be mean to Oliver.
That's the main point.
Usually when someone's leaving,
we make sure everyone
knows in advance
so that they
can be mean to them.
Franzke: So in a few weeks,
I'm actually going to move back.
So it will be interesting
to see how...
how much German culture has
changed since I moved away.
Maybe I'll feel like a complete
foreigner for a while.
Who knows?
I don't even know.
So, all future interviews
will have to be through Skype.
Offscreen: Gonna miss you, Oliver.
Franzke: Yeah...
I'm gonna
miss you guys too.
It's gonna be weird.
Schafer: I think it's--
it's been a tough time
because we haven't,
you know,
it's been a while since
we've given raises to people,
and so there's
other companies in the area
that are making a lot
of money right now,
and so they're able to throw
that kind of money around,
and that'll probably
cause us to--
Uh, that always happens.
We lose through--when, like,
Oculus and Facebook took off,
they started
throwing money around.
We lost some people to that.
Um, but after "Broken Age"
comes out,
we'll be able to throw money around, right,
'cause we'll be rich off of, uh,
all those point-and-click
adventure dollars.
Actually,
we don't expect to make
a lot of money
off of "Broken Age,"
because everyone
bought it the first time.
And, um, but the new platforms
like, um,
PS4 are going to be opening up
some new customers.
Bailey: There's a lot banking on it,
but--but not everything.
I mean,
we diversified
to do some of those
LucasArts properties
like "Grim Fandango" and, like,
uh, "Day of the Tentacle."
Uh, so "Grim" sales
are really good.
Um, you know...
[Applause]
It's, like,
$1.7 million gross,
which is good.
So, across all platforms
for the last week, um...
Schafer: I'm feelin' kinda gross.
Bailey: Yeah.
And, you know,
it looks like those are--
are gonna bring in
a lot of, uh,
a lot of money
for the studio, so...
Schafer: And I hope there's a lot
of people out there
who were just waiting for
the whole thing to be one game
and don't care
about crowdfunding
and they don't
wanna know about
our little
transparency efforts.
They just wanna play a game
when it's done and, um,
hopefully they will buy it.
Please join me in welcoming
Mr. James Spafford.
-Yay!
-Thank you, guys.
James Spafford.
Uh, would you please stand up
so everyone can see you.
This is James,
and rotate one time.
No, you don't have to rotate.
Uh, James...
uh, welcome to Double Fine.
So James Spafford used to be
one of the two people
who ran Mixnmojo, which is
an old LucasArts fan site,
and I knew him back then
when he visited our offices
in 2001, I think,
and gave me some Marmite.
And, um...and now I said,
"In 10 years,
we'll hire you."
Fifteen years?
"In 15 years, we'll hire you"--
as our community manager.
-Whoa.
-He's not the new Chris Remo.
He will never be
the new Chris Remo!
-Yeah.
Muir: 'Cause he's not dead.
Schafer: In other news,
Chris Remo's dead.
No.
Spafford: I mean, I'm a long-time
follower of Double Fine
and everything
they've been doing.
I'm a backer.
Uh, obviously backed immediately.
Um, followed
the documentary series,
which I'm now on,
which is really weird, uh...
Offscreen: Is he aware of
everything that's happened?
Did he know what he was
getting himself into?
Schafer: Don't tell him
about gamergate.
No, he knows, he knows.
That's--that's the exciting
new challenge for him,
will be, um,
rebuilding all the things.
Spafford: I knew what was going on.
I mean, certainly,
lots of people were not happy
about the game
being split.
Um...so I feel like, yeah,
that--that might've been
the start of some troubles.
But probably the start
of any community troubles
was the day that
the Kickstarter was made
and, um,
$3.5 million was raised
and a lot
of people's money
was riding on a thing
that they had in their head,
a vision that they had
that this thing was gonna be.
And, you know, it wasn't the way
some people wanted it to be.
I never want to give up
on people who are like,
"You know,
I'll try everything."
If people
are really mad,
a lot of the time
you can--
you can--you know,
you can bring them around.
There's always some way that
you can make them happy again.
Um...yeah, it's just
finding out what that is.
Schafer: It's--it's good timing,
'cause we're--as we're
wrapping up the game,
we're coming out of production
and getting back into all
the community-facing stuff,
like getting out the last
of the backer rewards.
Like, we still have a lot
of these little mini portraits
that Bagel has to paint.
So, like,
it's come to that point
where we're kind of, um,
closin' the loop
on the story, big story,
and so we'll be facin'
the backers a lot,
and it's good to have
a community manager for that.
Okay, so we're just--are we just
talking about the launch plans
for the game as far
as PR and marketing?
What's--what's your
marketing budget on the game?
Rice: Zero...?
Schafer: Okay.
Spafford: One of the big things
I wanna talk about
is how we talk about "Act 2"
and how we
properly do this,
like how we bring
this thing out.
Schafer: How do we talk about "Act 2"?
Spafford: The biggest thing, right.
Schafer: So just, like,
the--what's it called?
Spafford: Well, like, no, as in...
how are you getting people
to think about it?
You want people to think
about it as a whole game,
-or as episode two?
Rice: Yeah.
Schafer: Like, now that it's done,
I would like it
to just be just "Broken Age,"
as if we never
split it at all.
Rice: So, yeah, I think that the hope
was, like, a year from now,
the story would be more
about just the game as it is,
not that it was split
or anything.
Spafford: When it was
released, we did--
people did reviews of it
and stuff, right?
Like, treated it like
it was its own thing.
So I wonder how
persuadable people will be
to just forget that
and move on.
Rice: But I still think
we probably have to speak
to the people who did
already buy it, and--
Schafer: Yeah, because this is
a worry that I do have,
that people are like,
"When's 'Act 2' coming out?"
And that they don't
see that announcement,
-"'Act 2' is out"--
Rice: Yeah.
Schafer: Like, the answer
to that question,
they might miss the fact
that it came out.
Rice: Yeah.
Yeah, so I think we still
need to be saying that, like,
for people
who purchased "Act 1,"
they're getting
the full game now,
updated with "Act 2" content.
Spafford: Yep.
Rice: But...
Spafford: The PS4 and iOS is
definitely a really good chance
to just talk about
the whole game.
So we've been trying
to get people
to play the PS4 version,
which is a new platform, um,
and doesn't have
that distinction.
Like, it's just one game
on that platform.
So the more people
we can get to look
at that and talk
about that,
the more--
the more hopeful we are
that that can be a thing.
Rice: Not--not
speaking to just, like,
what's gonna happen
in "Act 2," you know,
'cause that's how
we've all been thinking about it
for a long time,
but speaking of, like,
what is this game?
Spafford: Looking at the full--
the full picture
now it's done.
Other than that,
we're just trying to, you know,
beg, borrow, and steal
every bit of coverage we can.
Rice: We were able to get a European
press tour on zero dollars.
Schafer: I...w-well...
Rice: So that's good.
Schafer: We're not paying
anything for that?
Rice: Um, we are paying
for three days of a B&B,
but they're paying
for all of our flights
and our B&B while we're there, so...
Um, I think
it's all pretty set now.
So, um, flights and hotels
and everything is in there.
There'll be--
basically we get to UK first
for the first weekend,
and then the Monday
after that we're doing, like,
a bunch of press
at Media Molecule.
Um, and we'll have Eurogamer,
Edge, and The Guardian, uh,
all that day
in their offices.
And then, yeah,
we have the talk
in Vyborg
with Peter and Ray.
[Music]
Spafford: We should pick a day
for having press around as well,
and then we can start
organizing them.
[Music]
Schafer: So what do you
think so far, Marty?
Sliva: I think it's awesome.
Schafer: Give us your, um,
full review now.
Sliva: Just verbatim, and then you
guys can write it down.
Schafer: We need to know the score
before we decide whether
-you're leaving the room.
Sliva: Yeah, okay.
Schafer: That's just a common--
Sliva: That's--that's happened--
That's happened before
with other publishers, so--
Schafer: Really? They're, like...
Rice: Oh, God.
Sliva: I think
it's mostly like, like,
"You can do an exclusive,
but what's the score,"
you know what I mean?
It's like, well,
I'm not gonna do that, then.
Uh, everyone
always says, like,
"Oh, this is gonna be
the adventure game
that gets people
to play adventure games
who haven't played
adventure games."
Like, you--is that
bullshit to you?
Like, is that--
is that necessary?
Do you think
adventure games need that,
-or do you think it's--
Schafer: I've always been--
I've always been
interested in it,
because it
always seemed like
with adventure games
that we were trying
to get beyond the--
the limited audience
of people currently
playing--playing games.
Not that they're limited,
but there--
there was a,
back in the '90s,
a small group
of the culture at large
that was playing
games at all.
And it seemed like
there are all these people
who weren't playing games
and they're like, hey,
I think you would like a game
that, well, it's about story,
where you don't have to worry
about getting shot in the head,
and, like, you could
play at your own pace
and it involved themes
that weren't
being covered in games,
you know.
So we always, you know,
we always, you know...
People would tell us, like,
"This is the only game
that my girlfriend
will play with me."
And it was--that was
always the story.
Like, there's all these people
out there who, you know,
why aren't
they playing games?
And I think this is the game
they would like.
But, um, you know, it's always
been hard to reach those people,
and, um, and make them feel
like they would like--
You know,
they think of themselves
as someone who would not
play video games.
It's hard to get past that
identity problem, almost.
Sliva: Totally.
Schafer: So I do think about it,
but I don't think
it's necessary.
Like, I think
it's good enough
to make a game
that people--
and that's what this
Kickstarter is all about.
Like, there are these
people who said,
"We like adventure games
just the way they are."
And they don't need
to completely revolutionize
with--with how
they interact.
They don't need to be
a different genre.
They just, "We like
the old adventure games
and we wanna play
another one."
And knowing
they were out there
and we were making
the game for them, uh,
is what made it
special this time around.
Rice: There's always been, like,
conversation coming up
here and there about how we're
gonna give backers the codes,
or if we're gonna
give them early access
to the game
or anything like that.
And I feel like
it's never been, like,
fully talked about
and decided upon.
Schafer: I was--I wanted to give it
just the--the day before,
-the 24 hours before.
Rice: Yeah.
Spafford: Yeah, if it's possible
without too much mess,
then I think that people
will really appreciate it.
And in fact,
we've set the embargo
for press
for the same time
as the backers
getting their keys
so that, you know,
everyone's getting
their thing
at the same time.
Offscreen: Yeah, 'cause the embargo
thing was such an issue last time.
Spafford: I think there is all kinds
of emotions about that.
Rice: Tim, did you hear that?
Schafer: What?
Rice: "Digital Trends"
posted an article,
"Why We're Breaking
the 'Broken Age' Embargo."
Schafer: Tell 'em maybe he
didn't agree to anything,
but he knows
he's bein' a shit.
Bailey: I was looking over all
of our news broadcasts,
and basically
all the exposure went out
when the backers got it,
like, two weeks ago.
Spafford: I think that whole situation
probably should have been done
a bit differently.
I think we learned
a lot from that,
by the sounds of things,
or at least I hope so.
And I've certainly
watched that episode
and--and thought, "Okay,
we need to not do that."
Yeah, so, it--today is Friday.
Uh, on Sunday night,
we're gonna send out
backer keys to people,
which is pretty exciting.
Um, 24 hours later,
the game will unlock on Steam
and be pushed out, uh,
around the world
onto however many millions
of platforms that we're doing.
Um, so by Tuesday,
uh, morning
when we all come
into the office,
the game will be out,
everyone will be playing,
no one will have any problems,
everything will be fine,
and everyone will be
having a good time.
That's--that's the gist of it.
Hansen: Flawless.
Franzke: What could go wrong, right?
Hansen: Yeah, don't say that.
Rice: It's all gonna be perfect.
Hansen: It--it may not be perfect.
Rice: Um, all right.
All right.
Let's put out
the Kickstarter update?
Spafford: Let's do it.
Schafer: Yo, yo, yo, yo, yo.
Yo, yo, yo, yo, yo.
Hi, everybody.
Hello, hello,
thank you for waiting.
Thanks for--
sorry about the delay.
It's still so interesting,
Melina just magically
appears there.
Hello, Melina,
nice to see you.
Awesome, awesome.
Okay.
Hi, everybody.
Uh, today I've been
very preoccupied
'cause "Broken Age" is
in the hands of our backers
and people are playing it,
which is amazing!
Yeah!
Offscreen: Do you wanna look
at the forum right now?
Schafer: Okay.
Let's go to the forum,
shall we?
"Spoiler: Need hint urgently."
Ah! Ah!
Take that, right?
Right?
Where's the general...
"Let's talk about how much
we love the game" thread?
Let's see.
Discussion and feedback.
"I finished this morning.
What an incredible game!"
That's all I'm gonna read.
That's it.
"Everything about 'Act 2' has
improved the game dramatically.
The puzzles are
a lot more detailed.
Required me to pull
out a notepad."
Yay.
That's nice.
I'm glad it makes--
I get excited when
I pull out a notepad.
"I liked 'Act 1,'
but it was a little linear.
'Act 2' is perfect.
And to Tim and everyone
at Double Fine,
I really appreciate you
and what you've done so much."
Well, that's nice.
Ah!
The game's out.
I mean, it really
comes out tomorrow,
or midnight tonight.
But it's out,
the review embargo is lifted,
we got a 9.2
from "Game Informer,"
and it should be good
for launch,
official launch day
tomorrow,
where it'll be out on all
platforms and everywhere.
Um, so now we just sit around
and read reviews
and pretend we don't
care about 'em.
That's the...regular thing.
I'm gonna sit there,
like, all night
just waiting for them
to come in.
You see one, you're like,
"Oh, that--
that was awesome!
I'm gonna read one more!
Oh, that was bad,
I'm not gonna--
not gonna read any m--
Oh, that one was nice!"
And then it all evens out.
I just was reading, like,
two different reviews,
one talking
about being too hard
and one being,
it's too easy.
And, uh, you know,
that just seems to be
the way with those games.
They're just, like, um...
people--people
react strongly
and very subjectively
and, um...I don't know.
Like, I feel like it takes years,
almost, for people
to really decide
how they feel
about these games.
So 10 years from now we'll
find out if it was any good.
Offscreen: It seems a bit strange
that there's review scores
for "Act 1," "Act 2--"
And the whole thing.
Schafer: Yeah, it's a mess...
it's a mess.
Never split
your game in half.
Rice: By the way,
there's a lot of people
talking about it,
so that's good.
Um, and tomorrow
we're partying,
and I think I sent an invite
out to everybody.
So, bar crawl, I think we're
just starting at Victory Hall,
'cause it's close
and we can walk there,
and then we're gonna go--
Schafer: And then the hardcore.
Rice: Chinatown.
Schafer: To people who care about
history and wanna relive history
through the bars
of Chinatown and beyond.
Rice: So, tonight at 9:00 our time,
midnight Eastern,
is when all the other
platforms will go up.
Bottle Opener: In the name of Lars Halford,
open up!
Franzke: Okay, so we've
got Ouya lined up.
I guess we just need
to press that button.
Rice: The button?
Uh, Spaff figured out
some way
to wire this weird
Divekick button...
Spafford: It's not that weird!
Rice: ...to launching the game.
-Cheers.
Franzke: Well, cheers to you guys.
Spafford: It's okay, we're
toasting the five--
four-minute
countdown
to pressing the
blue button.
Do you want the blue pill,
or the yellow pill?
Rice: Oh my God,
everything explodes.
Franzke: The game gets deleted,
obliterated from the server,
so don't press
the yellow button.
Spafford: All the money
is refunded.
Franzke: The code gets
unwritten, the art unmade.
Rice: Yep.
Spafford: What are we gonna do
for four minutes, you guys?
We could read Twitter
for a bit.
Spafford: People are really happy.
Rice: The reviews have been
-really good.
Spafford: Yep.
Rice: Just, like,
the way they describe
the puzzles
and the writing,
it makes it--
makes it feel like
people actually
really got it,
-which is nice.
Spafford: We should get ready,
because we're about
to--to go into...
Rice: Let's do it, you guys.
Spafford: You should.
Franzke: Okay, Greg,
It's hovering
over the button.
Rice: You do this one.
Franzke: I do this one?
This is Steam;
this is the big one.
Rice: I know. You do this one.
Franzke: All right.
Spafford: Press the "Okay" button!
Franzke: All right, here it goes!
It's live on Steam.
Rice: Yay.
Spafford: Oh, my God.
Rice: Okay.
Spafford: All right, next one.
Franzke: Okay, here's iOS.
Spafford: Oh my God,
oh my God, oh my God.
Rice: Oh, man...
Franzke: All right, here, Spaff.
Franzke: Spaff, you do
the OS X App Store.
Spafford: Release this version.
Franzke: Release!
I'll do Ouya.
Rice: Yep, there you go.
You're in that one.
Spafford: Ouya's live?
Franzke: Waiting--yep.
Spafford: Okay.
Franzke: Just Google Play.
Rice: Okay, wait,
is this the last one?
Franzke: Yeah.
Rice: Let's all do this one.
Franzke: Okay.
Ready?
Rice: Final build,
one, two, three, go.
[Music]
Franzke: But, yes,
this is my last, I guess,
full day in the office,
one could say.
Not that I'm actually gonna
do any work, but, um...
Today is "Broken Age"
launch day, officially.
Uh, so lots of parties
lined up.
I am just gonna pretend
they're all for me,
for my leave--for one
of my leaving parties.
Uh...but yeah,
it's--it's weird.
It's weird.
What is that? Oh.
Oh, because we don't
actually need this anymore?
That's true, I guess
I don't need to talk while--
Brr!
There's that.
All right?
Rice: We just put out the new
trailer, so we're trying to, like,
spread those around, um...
Offscreen: Elijah Wood?
Rice: I did see that.
So Elijah
just tweeted, like,
thirty minutes ago
about the game.
Right there, see?
Boom.
Yay, Elijah.
Like you see right now,
we're at, like,
twenty-five or so
on the list.
Um...and then the hope is
that that'll start going up,
so, by a couple things.
One is, we can
check and see now
if it's getting featured.
Okay, so there it is.
Yay.
So this showed up.
So this'll help,
especially since it's on sale.
Um, that's always nice.
On Steam people see
that sale number.
We do get daily Android
and iOS sales.
PS4 probably won't, uh,
give us any kinda inclination
for, like, a week or so,
maybe, um, maybe more.
Spafford: They're the most
interesting ones, I think.
Rice: Yeah, that'll be
interesting, 'cause it's new.
Um...brand-new sales
and it's reviewing well
there and everything.
So, uh, I think we'll have
a better idea in, like,
a couple weeks
across all platforms,
but we'll at least have
an inkling of what to expect,
um, from the ones
that we can see soon.
It's just, those are the ones
that we've already been out
and being sold on
for a while now,
so it's hard to say.
That's it.
Congrats.
Schafer: Uh...
Yeah, yeah.
Rice: You're so excited.
Schafer: Yep.
Phone voice: Press one.
To send a voicemail,
press two.
Schafer: I don't know what hap--
why it did that there.
Phone voice: Home screen.
Schafer: Oh, man.
Rice: Okay, all you'll do is say
"Green," and then "Okay."
Kipnis: Green and then--
Schafer: You press "Send"
to accept the call.
Rice: Yeah, this is an old phone,
old-school phone.
Kipnis: This is a really
old phone, yeah.
It's--it's a burner we got?
Greg: Yeah.
Kipnis: Is this what drug dealers use?
Rice: Yes, it's a drug dealer--
Schafer: Oh, I got a voicemail.
Okay, okay.
Phone voice: Home screen.
Kipnis: I love that it announces.
Rice: All right, can we start?
Schafer: A hint line--we're talking
about doing a hint line,
getting a burner phone
and just making it a number
that people
can call for hints.
You're supposed
to say, "Action."
Maybe talking to me...
Hm.
I'll probably just be
getting people angry,
people calling to chew me out
about "Spacebase."
Here's a hint:
Go buy someone else's games.
Hi, and welcome to
the Double Fine Hint Line,
which we have had
for a long time,
but no one's ever called,
it's weird.
Uh, but we're answering calls
today for "Broken Age,"
'cause today is the launch
of "Broken Age"!
Phone voice: Call one.
Schafer: Oh, we got a call!
Hold on, everybody.
Hello, Double Fine Hint Line,
can I help you?
Phone: Uh, hello, is this Tim?
Schafer: This is Tim.
How are you doing?
Phone: Oh m--oh, my God.
Hello, my name is,
uh, Steve Kaufman,
and I just wanna say,
you are the greatest developers
in--in history,
basically.
Schafer: Oh, that's so nice
of you to say!
-Oh, that's lovely!
Kipnis: Wow.
Phone: Uh, I was really
happy as a backer
to see it all come together.
Schafer: Aw, thanks for backing.
Phone: So, I love it.
Yeah, um, and I actually
have a legit--
like, I need a legit tip.
Schafer: Okay, all right,
that's why we're here.
Kipnis: Wow, this is
really working well.
Rice: There's a lot of people--
Schafer: Hello, Double Fine
Hint Line, can I help you?
Kipnis: Maybe some--some
asshole would call in and just say
really mean things to us,
live on the stream.
But it was, like,
the opposite.
It just, like, it completely
blew our expectations,
in the similar way that
seeing the game get funded did
on that first day.
It made you feel
like the world
is a much better place
than you thought it was.
Schafer: Bye.
Phone: Goodbye.
Schafer: What a lovely fellow.
Lovely fellow.
-That was spoiler-free.
-Yeah. There we go.
Spoilers:
Uh, our backers are great.
Phone: This is Emory Biloski
from, uh,
Israel calling,
actually.
Schafer: You're calling
from Israel?
What time--
what time is it there?
-Isn't it super late there?
Kipnis: Shalom.
Phone: It's, uh, it's like 1:30
in the morning.
Schafer: Shalom.
Hello, Double Fine Hint Line,
can I help you?
Double Fine Hint Line,
Rice: Blowin' up, blowin' up.
Schafer: Hello, Double Fine
Hint Line, can I help you?
Phone: Oh, shit.
Uh, hi.
Schafer: Language!
Kipnis: Yeah, it was just--
it was a really
pleasant surprise,
like, just how lovely
everyone was
and, like,
how fun that whole day--
that whole day
was really amazing.
Spafford: That's it.
We're done.
Kipnis: Yay. That was--
that was a great last call.
Rice: Well, we might turn
the phone back on later.
Kipnis: Really?
Rice: So, you never know.
Schafer: While we're hangin' out,
just out in the bar later?
All right, let's get
this good time over with.
Woo!
Nothing seems to happen
until I stand up
and get
everyone's attention
and then say thank you
to everybody.
I've made so many toasts.
Peter McConnell's here, everybody.
Peter McConnell.
Nice to see you.
Thank you for all the excellent
music in the game.
McConnell: Well, thank you.
When you've worked
on something
for--for
a good long time,
you know, over two years,
you know,
two and a half for me,
three I think for the--
for--for the--the
team at large, um,
uh, it's hard not to be,
you know,
a little misty-eyed
about it.
It's-it's like getting
to the end of the game,
when you play the game, um,
where--where
you have to, um, say,
oh, well, you know,
these characters
have become my friends
and--and now I have to say,
you know,
goodbye to the story
and goodbye
to the characters.
And so there's a certain
amount of sadness, I guess.
And--and, uh,
certainly, um,
you know,
there's a little relief.
It's always nice to be--
actually to say,
oh, finally, you know?
Um, you know,
but there's also that,
oh, well,
you know...
I mean, that's...
that's like, uh...um...
It's, uh,
an--an era, you know?
A really big project
like that,
you love like--like a--
like a child.
And, uh, letting it go
out into the world
is a--is a--
is an emotional moment.
Schafer: Call me if you need any hints.
If you need any hints,
give me a call.
All right.
Now, then...
[Gasps]
Agh!
[Laughter]
That's what you get
for being cute!
TV: Oliver, safe travels
and best of luck for the future.
And everybody else,
stay awesome, stay strong,
and find joy in the things
that you do.
-Bye.
Schafer: Bye!
Kipnis: Aw...
Wow.
Schafer: Awww.
TV: "Broken Age" got released...
Kipnis: Oh!
Schafer: Majus!
TV: I'm so happy for all of you.
Congratulations.
You finished
this work of art,
and now everybody
can see and play it
and it's wonderful!
[Laughter]
Struggled with problems
and obstacles.
Ups and downs
are a normal part
of the whole project.
And you should
embrace that.
It's part of it.
"Broken Age" is made
out of the ups and downs.
I am really emotional
right now.
I wish I could talk to you
for real right now.
And hope I see you again
soon in the future.
And, uh,
let's make more games.
Let's show the world
how the sausage gets made.
And, um, yeah.
I love you guys.
Crowd: Aw!
TV: And...yeah.
Let's, uh,
let's--we--we'll--
we'll talk in person,
so let's not do this.
[Laughter]
Schafer: Let's not let
this get weird.
TV: Bye.
Bye.
I love you.
Crowd: Bye, Majus!
Schafer: I mean,
crowdfunding was so great,
and is so great
in a lot of ways.
Like, it's--the--the, um,
the relationship you have
with the community
and the--
and the nature of the money
is so, um, perfect
for what you wanna do,
do something creative
and--and community focused
without worrying
about ties to people
who might wanna try
to influence your game
because they
gave you money.
Um...it's--it's weird
because it just happened
to time out--
it happened to coincide with
a weird phase of the Internet
where everyone's super angry
all the time and it just, like--
it was hard to be
that open and transparent
and give everybody--
It's like we opened up
a little tray of,
you know, bludgeoning
instruments so that--
for people
could beat us up with.
And then people picked 'em up
and just beat us up with them.
And we're like, huh, that was
an interesting experiment.
We probably shouldn't have
given all those weapons
to all the people who are mad.
But, um, if that had not erupted
at that moment, you know,
maybe I would've thought--
'Cause at the beginning,
the transparency
was nothing but, like,
um, hugs and, uh,
high-fives all around.
Like, everybody at our--
you know, our PAX meetups,
like, that was our
community experience,
was everyone just
telling us how much
they were excited
about the game
and how much they loved us
and everything.
And then when we announced
the change in the schedule,
just all that--
just people just--
it seemed like there was
a big crowd of people
just ready to--
just really super mad.
And if you Google, like, um,
"'Broken Age,' broken promises"
on the Internet--
which I do every night--
if you Google that, you'll see
all these angry articles.
Not just from, like,
random people on Twitter,
but, like, these journalists
who are like,
"They really let
everybody down with this
and they should
really be sorry."
And, um...
and here we are at the end
and we're shipping the game
and it took a long time,
but it's everything
we said we were gonna do.
Uh...and I want to mail
all those people
individually and be like,
"It's time for you to
apologize about that article."
But I don't think they
feel like they were wrong.
I think they feel like--
that we still really messed up.
But, um, I don't.
I feel like...
I feel--isn't it great
to know I've learned nothing?
But I feel like...
[Laughter]
I feel, like,
officially that--
I feel like I just need to make
an official announcement
that I don't apologize
for anything,
because I feel really good
about it.
And if we had shipped
one day earlier,
the game would've been
one day buggier.
And, um,
if we had shipped the game
that the original
$3.3 million paid for,
it would've been small.
And I like the game
that we made instead,
and we put a lot
of our own money into it,
and I think I'm really,
really happy.
This is the game,
this is what the game
kinda said that it wanted
to be, about this size,
and we did a really
good version of it.
And so I don't apologize
for anything.
[Music]
Raz: He makes me laugh.
"And that's why
it's called a game."
Schafer: Yay!
[Applause]
That's awesome.
Uh, even though
you like basketball...
Burbank: We all have our faults.
Schafer: That's awesome.
Well, yes.
Well, that's awesome.
Now, uh, congratulations, Gabe.
No speech?
Gabe: No.
Schafer: Okay.
Oh...one more thing.
We have boxes
of "Broken Age,"
actual boxes
and we have enough
for everyone here to get one!
Ryken: It's under our seat?
Schafer: What?
Look under your seat...
and that'll give me time
to open this box.
Offscreen: Now that this is
wrapping up, like,
how do you feel
about the whole experience?
Schafer: I wish I really knew
right now if I could say 100%
what I learned
from all that.
'Cause some of it's still,
you know, uh, too soon.
Like, uh, 'cause there's
this part of me that's like,
I just wanna
not tell anybody
about what we're
working on right now.
Like, I feel
just kinda, like,
so exposed that
I just wanna be--
I just wanna have some
secrets for a little while,
just as a kinda
break from that.
I had a pleasant trip
down memory lane
making an adventure game,
but I remembered
how hard
they are to make.
And, um,
I don't think
my next game will be
an adventure game.
I wouldn't say I'd never
make one again.
But in the end, I really--
I really think the team
put together
a beautiful game,
and that's what
I'm most happy with.
'Kay.
Now, this is
gonna be awkward
in case
this came out wrong.
This is a little light.
That's a different game.
What?
Whoa,
-look at that.
-Beautiful.
It looks beautiful, okay wait.
I don't believe it.
The design of this
was supposed
to have Vella
on the bottom,
'cause her hair is
touching the logo.
Not that I'm gonna complain,
'cause it's really awesome.
Okay.
I--I just have to demonstrate
before you leave.
This is fantastic.
Let's see if it works;
I've never tested this before.
Gah, no,
it doesn't work.
Gah!
Nope.
Let's see,
how does it actually--?
Okay, get rid of this.
Whoa...
Very cool.
And that, and that?
See?
And then, oh...
I want everyone
to do that
when you get your copy
and fix it, okay?
[Applause]
That is kinda funny,
we did Kickstart this thing
and now it's actually
a box in my hand.
Well, that pretty much
ends this documentary.
And...scene.
I really hoped
when it came out
people wouldn't
forget about
how it was funded and just
kinda talk about the game.
But it seemed like
every review had to talk
about
the development story,
and so that was
part of the lore
for a long time, still.
So I hope, um,
five years from now
when people talk about
adventure games,
they can look at it as
just an adventure game.
And so I think it'll be
remembered well,
and people can
just kinda get over
the crowdfunding part
of it.
Kipnis: I--to be honest with you,
I'm not really sure how
this whole thing is gonna
be looked at in the end.
Um...
I--I guess, like,
everyone has hopes for, like,
a game when it comes out,
and I had certain
hopes that, um...
maybe were not fulfilled,
necessarily.
And, uh, and it has more
to do with just, like,
I really hoped people
would love the game.
Um, and it's not to say
that they didn't,
but I kinda just, um--
I think there--there was
a lot of controversy
surrounding the game
and the company
that I wish
hadn't been there.
Like, I just wish it was...
I don't know.
Annable: It was a long,
hard road,
and it was
very public,
and I feel like
there were
a lot of things
that changed.
Um, and they
weren't necessarily
just because of "Broken Age"
and its visibility.
I think the company
is a different company now
than it was
three years ago,
and I'm trying
to still figure out, why?
I don't know,
are we just older?
Offscreen: Do you have any expectation
of "Broken Age's" performance?
Annable: I don't know.
Bailey: And then...uh,
talking about sales
of "Broken Age,"
so, uh, sales on Steam,
we had a feature spot.
Um, it acted
more like an update
than, like,
a--a new push.
Um, however,
we got a feature on Apple,
which is doing really well;
about $25,000 a day.
Um, and then we also have,
um, sales for, uh, Sony.
PS4, we had, like,
$100,000 worth of sales,
uh, over the weekend.
And it just got featured,
so, uh, that's cool.
Schafer: My expectation--
my expectation
of "Broken Age"
in the end
would just be to break even.
I know it was kind of
always like a Kickstarter,
like, you plan on it--
Like, it's--the risk is gone
of losing money on it,
so you know you've broken even
if you just make the game
to that amount of money.
But we made it, like,
twice as much,
almost, as we got in, or more.
And so, um, we will just
about make that back.
And the biggest change
is that we don't need
the publishers anymore, 100%.
You know,
it used to be, like,
there was no money in the world
outside of publishers.
And I think crowdfunding's
here to stay.
I think it's, um,
hopefully gonna grow.
And in my dream--
my dream world,
it would be big enough
to fund AAA games
and it would be the way that
we fund all games going forward.
So now when we're
talking to a publisher,
the deals are better.
We're asking
for less money,
but we're also not entirely
dependent on them
to make payroll next week.
We're not like,
"Please, we just--sign us.
We'll--we'll sign anything,
we just gotta make payroll."
It's like, okay,
you gotta kick us in the teeth
once a month
and all this stuff.
And now we only have to take
good deals with people we like.
So we still work
with publishers,
but, um, it's different.
Because we're 100% in control.
Annable: Yeah, we're not...
we're not rollin'
in millions of dollars.
I--I don't know
if that would
necessarily make
us happier, though.
Schafer: You guys are the best.
Thank you for all
your lovely audio.
And thanks for your beard.
Stoddard: It's kind of a milestone.
I think there's a--
there's a few things in general
around gaming that
"Broken Age," like,
really kinda did a push
towards a new area.
And I like that.
Um, there's a whole bunch
of stuff,
like, we could've done differently
and, like, we definitely
fell down in some areas.
But, like, so what?
Like, that's how you--
that's how you go forward.
Like, if you never fail,
then you just
aren't learning anything.
You're just...
being boring, really.
Franzke: I think it was
a huge success.
Without this project,
who knows?
Maybe Kickstarter would have
never been the prime platform
for, you know,
crowdfunded games.
I think it made it possible
for a lot of other people
to--to work on
their dream projects,
so that's--that's pretty cool, yeah.
So overall, you know,
I couldn't be happier,
I really couldn't.
And, you know,
the other day, um,
the other day I went to just
a random technology store
here in Germany,
and--and we just, um...
walked by this little thing.
So, just have--to see this
physical manifestation
of all the work that,
you know,
went into--into this game is,
like, super awesome.
Schafer: Hey, Ray! Good job.
Crook: Has the soundtrack in there.
Schafer: Oh, I forgot to mention,
it has the soundtrack in there.
Crook: I mean, I guess we did
accomplish what we wanted to,
which was to do this game.
And we--and we did that,
and we--and we finished it.
I think what we did do
that was the--
that I think was the most
beneficial to everybody
was that we kind of
cracked things open
and we let people look
inside of how things work.
And this maybe will help them
to see how things--
uh, how difficult,
uh, it is,
and how we're kinda lucky
that anything even comes out.
Like, that any video games
actually get finished, um,
is kind of a miracle.
And--and so that's good.
I hope that--
that helps...
I--I hope that helps people
who are fans of video games
and like playing
video games,
it just helps them
understand
and have a little bit
of empathy towards, uh,
those of us who are
in this industry.
Um...you know,
we're lucky to be in it,
and I--you know,
I'm grateful to be in it, um,
but it's not
always easy,
and--and it's--
and I'm glad that
we were able
to show that to people
in--in an honest way,
so it's kinda neat.
I mean, if Double Fine's
not around in 10 years,
let's just, say, um--
it'll always be rem--
like, it's out there now
forever, right?
Once it's on
the Internet, um,
it'll always be there.
And so...so...
Double Fine
will always be...
...around.
[Music]
Stoddard: I think it was
very positive.
I think there was
a lot of stuff
that we really
did contribute
to the games industry.
And...uh,
and there's a lot of stuff
that we sidestepped and,
like, misstepped.
And we're trying
to learn from that, too.
So, um,
considering all that,
I--going back and playing
the actual game,
I actually think
we did really solid work.
And I actually
think it's, um...
I think it's
a really good game.
I haven't really seen many
reactions that are just blas.
Like, it--it's usually
a strong reaction,
one way or the other.
And to me, in any art form,
that's great.
Like, that means that
it's provoking something.
And I think that's
what this is about.
If, like,
we did three years of work
and there was all these
trials and tribulations
and at the end
somebody just went, "Meh,"
like, that would be crushing!
But it hasn't been like that;
it's been the opposite.
Like, it's either
really, really good
or really, really awful
or, you know,
very, very vocal,
no matter what.
Great.
Then we did our job.
[Music]