[Music] Schafer: You know you got drunk when the next morning
you're just starting to think of things that you said, no.
I have this memory just walking down the street yelling and screaming the entire time.
Schafer: I love Chinatown.
[Music] Schafer: Did you see how many pages I got done?
So far I've got actual writing.
This writing paid for by Kickstarter.
So, it's a book. It's coming along. We came up with a code name.
Do you want to ask questions or should I just start talking?
Rice: DF adventure. Budget.
Schafer: Budget? We need that. We might not need that.
I think we can have food.
Launch event.
I hate to cut the launch event.
That much for PAX Prime really? Rice: Um hm.
Schafer: I mean that, we might not need that.
Let's just say if we're being really bare bones on some of this stuff.
Rice: We're cutting so much stuff right now.
Rice: Ah, it's the things that like...
Schafer: Greg thought of... Everything I thought of is in.
Everything Greg thought of is out.
Rice: Yeah. So I was being really conservative on like trying to figure out stuff outside of just paying the members of the team
that we might need to pay for.
And some of that stuff might not be necessary.
So it's...
Schafer: Well, it's tight for me.
I mean, it's tight for me in terms of like the number of people we have on the team.
Like I wish we had more programmers.
So if we did that.
So if we cut out all those, some of those things, we'd have like another $100,000, which would be um...
some programmer time.
Rice: Yeah.
Schafer: OK. All right.
And then we have how long to actually make the production.
'Til next November.
Next November's like infinity far away.
Rice: It's pretty far.
Schafer: We could do eight games in that time. It sounds so long.
Cut to November.
What? The game isn't started yet?
Wait.
Done with that. We're in Alpha, oh.
November this year? Rice: Yeah.
Schafer: We can't do that, it's crazy. That's insane.
We're starting in November next year. Rice: No.
Schafer: That sounds good.
Rice: That would be a year and a half.
Schafer: November this year, oh, that's much closer.
Rice: I mean that gives us uhh...
five, five whole months of production.
Schafer: Five whole months of production?
Oh my God.
Schafer: Well, I'm in an interesting position now because I'm running the company and I'm running a project.
So on the one hand I'm just, I'm equal to the other project leaders and I can't really abuse my ability to like pick up resource up
and put them on a different project.
But I do when they're not looking, so that's fine.
All for the good of the project.
Team Member: Ostensibly, we going to take somebody off your team to put them on DFA.
And you're going to be short-handed.
Schafer: I mean when you're project leader, you have to kind of fight for your team.
I mean, it's a fight for resources.
And you care about the company overall but you still know that to make your game good you should get the best people on it.
And so you kind of, you have to do a little recruiting.
You have to talk to them, you know, outside of meetings and stuff and be like, hey, are you interested?
I think we know you'd be, this would be a good opportunity to you.
You could, you know, you'd be moving up or you'd be taking on more responsibility or we're doing this really cool kind of art or something like that.
Get people excited about it.
And mostly we just said that we're doing this project and most people like Anna and Brandon, you know,
mentioned to me they wanted to work on it.
Dillon: I mean I was big gamer when I was a kid.
But like adventure games were always kind of special to me in particular.
The fact that I wound up, you know, in a configuration where I could get to work on an adventure game with, you know,
with my favorite adventure game designer.
It's just crazy and still kind of mind-boggling.
Schafer: And because the schedule is so tight on DFA and it's got such a small budget, that's, that is a bit of worry, too.
Offscreen Voice: Holy shit!
Schafer: I'm nervous, though. Offscreen Voice: Why are you nervous?
Schafer: 'Cause I really want Brandon on the team.
And so do the other teams.
So if he does something really awesome, I'm just going to get sad if we then don't get him on the team.
Dillon: So basically over the weekend I just wanted to prototype some tools work.
Schafer: Me, too. I just had, it was Easter.
I didn't get around to it.
Dillon: This is how I celebrate Easter. Schafer: It's beautiful.
Dillon: So I'll show you my super-awesome adventure game here.
Schafer: Oh my God.
Schafer: I didn't know you could draw. Incredible.
Dillon: Yeah, yeah. And I feel like we're basically done.
Schafer: Yeah, we just got to art this up.
Dillon: And so like I started with the classic data editing thing, which is walk boxes.
And so like got a little, you know, a walk box here.
Schafer: Ah, that's crazy. Dillon: Like look how accurate.
Schafer: Right. Now click on the outer space there. Dillon: It's fine.
Schafer: Let me see this. Let me see this.
Dillon: Oh, you're breaking the illusion.. Schafer: Oh, crash.
It was a really good puzzle.
Brandon is a genius and a great programmer and also someone who has like a deep love,
a deeper understanding of the low level systems required but also a real affinity for adventure games and tools and pipeline.
Dillon: So like this is honestly the stuff that I'm most excited about, right.
It's like, you know, coming up with a tool chain for everybody to use, where like, you know, whatever crazy idea that Tim has, we can get it into the game
as quickly as possible and actually see whether or not it works.
And tune it up so that it can be as good as it can be.
I like being behind the scenes.
Schafer: That's crazy, OK. Programming is actually happening, on the game All right, you guys.
Awesome. That's cool. We're actually doing actual work.
Schafer: I Probably should go design it now.
Dillon: It's really nice to just get something on the screen and like that's always the first step to, like it's very clarifying
to, you know, have stuff present and actually interactive, because then it's easy to figure out what to do next basically.
Rice: Oliver. Franzke: Hello!
What have you got, man?
Franzke: It's pretty cool.
Rice: This is the game?
Franzke: It's kind of a game. Rice: Oh nice! Walking in 3-D space.
Franzke: Well, it's like scaling it vertically, but that's, that's pretty much how we're going to do it in the final game as well.
Rice: So all these are flat planes and you're just scaling the size of the character?
Rice: And then we've got Oliver and he's doing a lot of system work on the engine and getting the engine kind of in shape.
Franzke: Well I was born in Germany of course i'm from Germany.
In fact, from East Germany.
So because of historic reasons I can be here today, otherwise I would probably be in Moscow right now, I guess.
I'd probably follow the people that work in the industry, like from a young age, you know, I always was playing games and was interested in the medium.
It's certainly kind of strange to be here now, to actually write adventure game from scratch.
It's kind of cool, I guess it's what a lot of people in the gaming industry kind of dream about
and would love to do and it's kind of, it's awesome to be here now at this time
and like be able to be part of this project, for sure.
It's very exciting.
I should probably mention that this is not the final game, so please nobody freak out at this point yet.
Schafer: You know, I've never worked with Oliver before directly.
He's worked on Once Upon a Monster.
And it's funny, he worked on the special edition of Monkey Island back at Lucas.
Also he's German.
Franzke: And if I have time, which would be awesome, like to actually dialogue system so you can initiate like a dialogue with some...
some other thing in the world.
Kipnis: So what we're looking at is an implementation of that, of a dialogue sequencer.
We have this database of lines.
So i'm just using that to test out my system.
So I wrote this little test dataset that the red bots are going to insult each other with.
And so, yeah, let me show you what it actually looks like when you play it.
My friends had Nintendo and that was, that was the best for me.
Like I remember I played a lot of Super Mario Brothers.
And I mean, that kind of blew my mind at the time, because when I was growing up I was kind of the oldest kid.
And I would come up with games to play with everyone else to entertain them and stuff.
And I realized when I played Super Mario Brothers that this was kind of the same thing.
Like someone made up like this like little world for other people to experience and to see.
And you didn't even have to be there; And it was just like magical.
It was like magical technology where I can do this stuff that I had been doing as a child.
That was like my dream. I got my dream job somehow, basically.
Schafer: And she, Anna's been implementing my dialogue longer than anybody in the world.
What the hell is that sound? [siren in background].
That happens every Tuesday at noon.
It's not Tuesday. It is Tuesday.
You know, you hear this robot voice?
Where's the robot voice?
Oh.
[faint distorted voice in background].
You can barely even hear that.
What if that was saying "get out of the building"?
I don't know.
It sounds like, like our government has been shut down.
You are all loyal servants of the...ok so I was saying,
I mean no one's had to implement more of my dialogue ever than Anna, probably because she's been doing it since Psychonauts.
And hopefully on this game, I mean she's... I haven't written a lot of dialogue yet, but she already knows kind of what I'm going to write structurally.
And so she's already writing the systems to implement that.
Rice: So then we've also got Lee Petty, who is the art director.
Petty: It's kind of hard to tune for unless you have...
Rice: This is the old one and this is the new one.
Petty: That's the old one?
Rice: This is the old one, yeah.
Petty: That's a little different than I remember it.
Petty: I've pretty much been in the game industry since 1996 constantly.
I was at Accolade for about five years.
I worked on a variety of projects there, some of which shipped, some of which didn't.
I actually was cursed.
I don't remember how many years, but I think it was like my first three years in the industry,
everything I worked on was cancelled.
It was like, ahhh.
I can't get a single game on my resume.
Luckily games didn't take three years to make each back then, right?
Schafer: Yeah, Lee's been here for a while.
He was, came in, in the middle of Brutal Legend and took it over and made it look good.
He's been in the industry for a long time.
I think if you look at him you can see the, it's a wear on his face from the games industry.
No, he's worked on the games for a long time.
He knows, he knows everything.
He's, you know, he's run his own projects.
He ran Stacking all by himself. I didn't get involved in that at all.
He wrote the dialogue for it. He did everything.
So we're lucky to have him on projects for a little while.
I'm trying to figure out whether we can steal him for good or not.
But there's so many other things we need him to do.
Don't let him see this footage, though, 'cause he'll ask for a raise.
Rice: Yeah. We're starting to get like a team on the game.
Schafer: This is the nightmare team from hell, you guys.
You've never seen a sicker, crazier team.
Petty: I'm getting Wi-Fi but it's not connecting to the Skype.
Did you, you signed out on purpose, right?
Rice: Yeah, because it went away.
Petty: Yeah, I don't know what's going on.
Skype server seemed like they're having issues.
Schafer: OK, this is the first stand-up. Isn't it exciting?
We can't do it without Bagel. You can't get Bagel?
Rice: Internet's being weird.
Kipnis: Should we just call him?
Schafer: Bagel, we're having troubles with Skype.
Can we just speaker-phone you in?
Bagel: Yeah, let's do it.
Schafer: OK, we're doing it.
Rice: Is that all the way up?
Schafer: That's as loud as it gets.
Say hi, Bagel. Bagel: Hey, everybody.
Rice: And then we've also got, we've always had Bagel on, doing like concept arts and backgrounds and stuff like that.
But now we've got an art director on the project that'll actually start trying to take those images that Bagel has made
and figure out how to actually get them in a game and get them to be like working game assets.
Schafer: Bagel Stapley, Nathan.
Stapley: Buddy.
Schafer: Look at that baaaaaaa. Lee Petty is here.
Petty: What's up, Bagel?
Schafer: Lee Petoir is here.
Stapley: Can you hear me? How is it?
Schafer: Yeah. I can hear you, can you hear me?
Stapley: Yeah, I can hear you.
Schafer: Oh, man. I haven't paid my property taxes.
So embarrassing.
So one of the main things I want to do is pick what you're going to paint for Lee to mess with in after-effects.
Stapley: Yeah. Schafer: Remember that? Stapley: Yeah.
So is that how we're going to do it?
Like I'm thinking of layers basically.
Petty: The goal is just to get like a type of environment, you know.
Like maybe it looks like something that the player could walk, kind of left or right and have it scroll or into.
Kind of either one we could explore.
Schafer: Right now he's taking, you know, Bagel's work and Bagel's not a very technical person
so he just paints these awesome paintings.
But then making it actually look good in the game is a whole different thing.
And so we've got Lee working on actually making that a realized game playing world.
And it's really fun to see them working together, because they're so different but they're putting together this, I think,
awesome looking visual style.
Schafer: There's a lot of cabins in here.
Petty: Hey, that'd be a good one, Tim. That cabin.
So if you wanted the player walk into the screen there, like it's a little slightly different
but similar to that whole circus sequence in Monkey one.
You just walk into that and they can make a move up to that top shot basically.
Petty: We haven't designed in the actual characters yet for the game.
Tim is still writing and coming up with exactly what the world is.
So we just sort of picked a character out of one of Bagel's sketches and put it into the game.
And we needed to do, you know, we just needed it to move around.
So I just did some really quick animation on it.
It's certainly not great animation but just to get it to kind of move around the world.
And follow the camera.
And so I think, you know, you kind of get a sense of, is how the camera might follow the player and kind of lag behind the player.
How it might move around the screen.
And you'll see that one of the things we're doing here with this character is that as he's in this canopy, he's kind of tinted green and darker.
And as he emerges into the sun, here he becomes a little brighter.
And we don't really have, you know, any true lighting that's going to paint it into the painting,
but I'm doing some simple things where we're using like color gradients based on location of the world and kind of multiplying it in this character.
Just with the goal of getting to feel part of that environment.
And that's a type of trick that we could do technically in the game image if we wanted to.
And it's really quick to do.
But it's enough to help him harmonize with the environment.
Schafer: Please join me in welcoming Mr. Chris Remo to the company.
[Applause] Schafer: Remo's our community manager.
He's been here now for two weeks or so, ish.
Chris, could you please stand up.
[Laughter] Any questions about any of that stuff before we talk about projects?
I'll give you the update on Double Fine Adventures, awesome game.
I'm working on design stuff and we have a team actually working on tools and engine and visual,
pre-visualization of what the art side will look like.
And I'm putting together one of my deliverables for the milestone, in a couple weeks.
It's like a story document and stuff.
And at that point I'll be like probably sharing more info about the game with other people company-wide.
Rice: Well I mean, Tim's been doing brainstorming stuff for a while.
And that's still what he's doing, just kind of holing up in his office and figuring out what the game is.
Schafer: You know, at the very beginning I'm locked in my room a lot writing dialogue.
But then I kind of have the job of pulling this whole thing down the road.
You know, so I was ready to finally pitch to the team.
I'm not really, haven't really felt right to pitch to the whole company yet.
That'll come later but, so I pitched to the whole team.
Schafer: OK. So I'm going to talk about the game today with everybody.
And some people have heard about it and some people have not.
Did I talk to you about the game?
Some people have not, not just you.
[Laughter] Petty: There're several people in Wisconsin.
Schafer: As you see, I've made a lot of progress.
I've designed some monster designs. Rice: I like it.
Schafer: And then I was going to go and do some detail about some ideas for the beginning of one side of the story.
Just 'cause the first example, like a sample game play and then we can all tear it apart
and talk about how it's never, never, never going to work.
Schafer: And it's an interesting process where...
deciding when to solicit feedback and when to actually sell.
It's like sometimes you're selling and sometimes looking for feedback.
And the idea... And early on I could sense like in the meeting, 'cause we talked about that as being a feedback session about the pitch and stuff.
I realized I didn't want any feedback right then, like any in-depth feedback.
So I kind of pitched the game and then kind of moved the meeting forward and ended it and because there is an early stage
where you don't want any feedback because it doesn't really mean anything.
Because they don't know still entirely what you're thinking and they might have an image in their head
but it probably isn't exactly like what I have in my head.
So I almost don't want their opinion of it because they're not talking about the thing I'm talking about.
They're talking about their own, how they see it.
Offscreen Voice: Can I contribute as a devil's advocate?
Schafer: I like where this is going.
Remo: To me the strongest parts of this by far are the thematic aspects of the two characters in parallel.
Especially switching between those, I think, could be incredibly important and really, really cool.
Both in terms of game play and aesthetics and the stuff supporting that seems so high-concept to me that it might end up being top-heavy.
Like it seems, it just seems like a really complicated thing.
Schafer: People at, you know, at that meeting can bring up any sort of problems but it's just too early, you know.
I dare them. Nice try, Chris Remo.
What were we thinking inviting that guy to the meeting?
Hey, maybe this thing you're doing shouldn't be done. Thanks.
Remo: That's... I mean...
Schafer: I guess because I see it working in my head, it isn't that complicated.
I see that being like just providing a structure, actually, to how everything has to behave.
Schafer: I do want is like when I say the idea, what other ideas that makes that person think of.
Like you know what would be cool? And how they want to add to it.
Petty: I love hearing new ideas.
I like, Tim is a very, a lot of times Tim, the way he describes ideas is like, like the fact he described a box cover for a game
that doesn't exist is a very Tim thing to do.
Like he has, he's not an artist per se, like visual artist, but he thinks very visually.
And I think that's helpful for someone like me and it's probably why we work so well together, is, you know,
he's got these ideas and I can sort of, you know, as he's drawing out the birthday cakes and stuff like that
I probably shouldn't talk about...
As he's drawing out some of the ideas on the white board in really simple fashion, I'm immediately starting to think about like,
well, how's that going to put together in the space and how can we emphasize that or make that work.
And so that's exciting to hear.
Schafer: Anyway. So you pick which side you're on.
I've only been, I've been working on this one a little bit.
So imagine it would just kind of scroll the boy off the screen.
And she would be sitting here leaning on this tree on a hillside.
My drawing gets worse and worse the more people are watching.
Kipnis: Are those her legs?
Schafer: It could be
Lee: She's a tick.
Schafer: Yeah, turns out she's a tick in the end.
Kipnis: They're both human.
Schafer: They're human, yeah,
yeah, they're human.
Petty: Yeah, I think the idea's really cool and I think visually, I think there's a lot of interesting stuff that we have,
I haven't really had a chance to talk to Tim yet, but I think there's a lot of interesting stuff thematically
that is appealing to me.
I mean, there's this sort of almost Tale of Two Cities quality to it.
I can see a lot of good ambiguity in the way that that story is structured.
I think that's really, will be great.
And to be a way that we, from a design and narrative way move the genre forward a little bit.
Kipnis: I want, I want something new to be brought to the table that wasn't there before.
And I'm not sure what that is quite yet because I still don't have like a very clear idea of what the game's going to be like.
But hopefully I can contribute to that.
Franzke: Yeah, I know, I'm confident from a technology point of view be able to do what is necessary.
I hope it's going to be good.
[Music] Schafer: All right. Rice: Wait you forgot the big thing.
Rice: Bar crawl.
Schafer: Who can go to the bar crawl tonight?
Petty: I can't go tonight.
I'm too sick, actually.
I have to go home and sleep.
[Music] Offscreen Voice: Actually, Tim, can you just say what we're doing again?
Schafer: Where... you don't know where we're going?
Kipnis: It's for the camera.
But you know, should I make sound really natural like I'm just happy to be talking about it?
Kipnis: Hey Tim, where are we going, by the way? Do you know?
Schafer: What? Kipnis: Where are we going?
Schafer: I don't know. Where are we going? No.
Tonight is a very special night because we are going to retrace the history of Double Fine
through the code names of our projects.
Shall we do that again?
Projects.
The history of our company as told by the code names of our projects, which are mostly taken from Chinatown dive bars.
Offscreen Voice: Why don't you tell us about what happened last night?
Schafer: You mean between me and, oh, oh.
Last night.
So we went on a quest last night to find a code name for the project.
It's fun. I mean we used to, like in the very beginning of the company,
when we only like, the whole company was like twelve people, we'd go out a lot together.
And go bar crawling together and we hadn't done that a lot lately.
But it was fun to get back out there again with the team.
Kipnis: I think you're, you're greatly overestimating my alcohol tolerance.
Schafer: All I heard is you are great.
[Laughter] Schafer: It was like a team kickoff event.
[Music] Schafer: Lipo was the very first code name of our very first project.
This is the code name for Psychonauts.
Rice: Never heard of it.
What's that?
Schafer: Let's go.
Schafer: Buddha is the code name for Brutal Legend.
Hi, I'm Tim. Nice to meet you. What's your name?
Man: Peace again. Schafer: That's a weird name.
Schafer: EZ5 is the code name for Happy Action Theater.
Grasslands was our code name for Psychonauts II.
Who knows if that'll happen. If that happens, we call it Grasslands.
Bow Bow was the code name for Brutal Legend II, we started on that.
[Singing] Schafer: There's some documents called Bow Bow.
Vesuvio was Once Upon a Monster.
Empress is short for Empress of China and Empress was the sequel to Once Upon a Monster or Twice Upon a Monster,
it probably would have been called but that got cancelled.
But you still go there. It's important to go there and remember, pour out a drink for the cancelled projects.
[Clinking glasses] Schafer: And last night we found what might be the last bar in Chinatown
that we haven't named anything after and that's Red's.
Schafer: Hey, here's to the Red's team. Red's.
That doesn't sound bad at all. Red's.
Schafer: Code name Red's.
[Music]