Stapley: Yeah, that's pretty. Pretty colors.
Stapley: Yeah, I was looking at the end there.
The 20th of September, October, November, December, January, February, March, April.
So yeah, everything looks cool here.
Yeah, those last three months right there seems like there's going to be a lot of changing.
[Laughs} From November to February looks a little crazy.
Yeah man. It's going to be pretty nuts.
[Music] [quite fantasy music]
Petty: Well, then we need to come up with another plan because right now it's not possible.
There's just not, one artist can't be the primary, like he's the, he's the, you know, like literally he's the renderer for every object in the game.
And do concept design on the schedule we have.
Schafer: I think if I hadn't been through the process before, I'd think the project was falling apart last month.
It definitely is a little bit of a tension as you switch gears and you're talking about practical matters.
But it wasn't that tense, you know.
Petty: For all the artists involved but certainly for Bagel, we're going to have make, you're going to have decide, I guess,
which, what you want the hierarchy of his time to be spent on.
[Ambient sci-fi music] Schafer: I want him to come up with both the, you know,
that really just like content and then actual style, both.
Petty: There's other options there, that we talked about all those options.
I don't think we've committed to one particular solution yet.
Rice: I think it's an ongoing conversation, so not really.
Schafer: I mean yeah, we're doing, since we're doing a game that's like a different engine type than we've ever done before, it's like 2D.
A whole different engine, new devices we'd never worked on and an adventure game, which we would have never made a straight adventure game here at this company.
So we're doing so many new things with this project that we're just learning.
Every time we try to do something, we find out like that's not going to work.
We do have to, of course, correct and try different solutions.
But that's totally normal, expected.
Offscreen Voice: Don't fuck with my wall.
Rice: But I mean, like a lot of it isn't like, there's a problem, we're fucked.
It's like we need to pay attention to this and try to start figuring out ways to make it work.
And we started thinking about that and feeling more comfortable.
Schafer: Well, we have, we brought on Levi and he's helping out.
Rice: We have some new people, but like they're getting familiar with everything pretty quickly.
Ryken: I was actually, on Friday I was looking at this.
Just getting inspired.
This is the museum near Tokyo.
It's super cool and I went there and I bought that there.
And for Friday, I just, the first thing in the morning I was getting inspired looking at that.
And then someone was like, you know what?
They're playing a bunch of those right now and apparently for like two weeks they're playing all of those studio Ghibli films.
And I'm just going to be there every day.
It's happening right now. Yeah.
Over the weekend I saw three: I saw Nausicaa, which is like a big inspiration for stuff that we're doing right now.
[Offscreen] Yeah we just watched that last week.
Really great, it's really great.
Rice: Yeah. We had like another art slot.
We didn't know what we were going to fill it with and like right now it makes sense
because concepts the most needed and that's why Levi's around.
But I mean, who knows?
Like later in the project we could be ramping down on concept and need more animation and have to switch it out.
But yeah, we always had one other spot for an artist and I'm glad that it was Levi.
Offscreen Voice: How far along did Peter Chan get with his contributions?
Rice: How far did Peter get?
I think the last stuff that Peter did was some environment designs for spaceship stuff.
Schafer: All right. It's been good talking to you, Peter.
Chan: Thank you again, you guys, for everything and it was a lot of fun.
And to be part of it.
So thank you for inviting me.
Schafer: We'll see you again. Petty: Thanks, Peter.
Rice: Yeah, it was a bit of a bummer.
I mean, he was offsite so it wasn't like we were hanging out all the time, which would have been super fun.
But still, like I did look forward to every Friday, getting like a drop of art from him.
But Levi's around so like having him right next door and getting to see his stuff, which has been like a totally different take on it and you know,
being able to hang out with him in the office has been fun.
Rice: Yeah. I don't know if you talked to Lee much about what you're going to start with, concept-wise.
Ryken: Yeah, I have concept stuff for boy world stuff.
Rice: Did you check out Peter's? Ryken: Yeah.
Rice: Yeah, are you scared?
It's a lot to live up to, man.
Ryken: I'll get out my tracing paper.
Rice: Yeah, I don't think it works that way.
Ryken: Peter Chan did a bunch of the early stuff and I've been looking at what he's been doing.
This is me, actually look at this.
That's bootleg P. Chan.
Schafer: And we have interviewed an intern, an art intern.
I haven't met her yet, but everyone seemed to like her and think she was good.
And that would help, too.
Offscreen Voice: Oh no, you filmed that!
Schafer: Please also join me in welcoming Marius from Germany, where did he go...
There he is! Marius Fitz...
I'm going to have you pronounce your last name.
Can you pronounce your last name for us?
Fietzek: Fietzek.
Schafer: You know, Marius was the one who made an adventure game as a job application for Double Fine, which seems very nice.
Fietzek: Hey, I heard about the Double Fine Adventure and was super-hyped and yeah, I thought like if I want to,
if there's a chance to work with my idols on the 2D animated game, then this is like the only chance maybe ever.
So I made an, application video game.
Schafer: Our plan is to actually release that as a Double Fine Adventure and then pocket all the Kickstarter money.
We'll give you a small percentage of it.
How long will Marius be here, Mr. Greg Rice?
Rice: Three months.
Schafer: You get three months, holy cow.
And what will he be doing?
Rice: Who knows? Schafer: Who knows.
Rice: Animating. Schafer: You'll do some animating on Red's.
Fietzek: But I started with the whole cinematic approach on the very first cut scene, just to see how it feels.
I thought of a very quiet start where we first see the spaceship, because I don't, I don't remember a point at the space boy part
where we actually see the ship.
Schafer: Well, Marius is great.
Like he's like, he'll just show us, you know, a story board and it's really hard to like how someone do something
that's really great and really funny, but just for what you were thinking of it, maybe it's not right.
Schafer: And the same way the girl starts.
She's just laying on the hillside and it's not a cut scene, but like a steady state; you exit out of it by tapping.
And the same way with this.
It's really got to be that it pans over and shows him and he's laying there on the bed, and the same kind of just, you know.
[Schafer] So you got to like tell him, like I had to tell him like this whole sequence was backwards.
And he's like, oh great, OK, great.
And then I come back the next day and it's completely different.
Exactly the way I wanted and it's perfect and it's like, oh, that's great.
[Schafer vocalizing sound effects] Schafer: That's awesome.
Schafer: You know, it's like, finding someone like that is really, it's hard to find people like that and so you kind of hang onto them.
Of course, he's supposed to go back to school.
So then you have to figure out whether you want to derail someone's education by trying to recruit them to come to your company.
Which of course, I have no problem with.
I'm already done thinking about it and I've already thought about it while I was saying that sentence, so, so much for his education.
[Laughter] Rice: We're finally like fully staffed and we've got like our team,
all of our budget's totally spent on everyone who's on the team.
So I think that, you know, a month or so from now it's going to feel like everything's just kind of moving forward steadily and the game is being made.
Rice: At the time when we started the Maiden Feast, that was kind of the only puzzle that was far enough along
that we had enough of a design to actually start building stuff.
So we did know going in that it was like a super kind of meaty puzzle that was going to be a tough one to implement.
And we still, you know, it was kind of all we had to go on at the point.
Schafer: I had the Maiden's Feast designed so they had to like, oh, we got to pick that, 'cause that's the only thing that's really designed.
Rice: But by the time we'd gotten it to like the first pass kind of state, then we had designs for this Cloud Colony stuff,
which we knew was just a lot easier to implement and a lot more indicative of the rest of the game.
Schafer: So navigation across different layers and pointing and clicking, talking to people, camera motion is all part of Cloud Colony.
Rice: One of the nice things about being able to make those kinds of decisions and jump around is we can like really look at in the moment
what is most important for the game and be able to kind of like change tracks, without having to like clear that decision with a publisher.
Schafer: So we kind of left Maiden Feast where it was, which is, you know, has like a stand-in, a couple stand-in pieces of art in there.
Much as it pains me to leave that unfinished, but we'll revisit it soon, I think.
Schafer: This is a kick-off meeting for the Cloud Colony.
Required reading for this meeting is this document everyone' read, I'm sure.
I've already started working on it.
So I think it's just good to go over all the puzzles in case it exposes things we haven't thought of or just questions you guys have.
Are you ready? Ready to begin?
Schafer: This is the part of the game right after the Maiden's Feast when you get, when you break away and you hitch a ride on that buzzard, on the corset.
And you fly.
It takes you up into the air.
She's the sacrifice girl who's just chosen to run away instead of being sacrificed and feels that she may have just endangered,
she's been told that this will endanger her entire town if the monster's not appeased.
So now the monster's all upset and she's feeling like I have to do something to get rid of this monster and to protect my family and my town.
But before I get back there I'm going to have to like figure out a plan.
So she arrives in the home world, if you will, of the bird, which is a little village made of primarily nests that have been,
that are buoyant on these really thick clouds, that we're calling the Cloud Colony.
[Music] Schafer: I feel much better because I actually, like I felt good
after I wrote that cloud document, but that was really only like four puzzles.
And the spaceship one has like sixteen puzzles in there or something.
So I'm catching up now.
[Music] Schafer: Aha! Work. I did work.
This is the spec for the whole spaceship.
Designed all the puzzles for the spaceship.
Offscreen Voice: Really? All the puzzles?
Schafer: Yeah, all the puzzles for the spaceship.
And this is just two-thirds of the puzzles for the girl's world.
But there's still, I mean, there's still a lot of stuff to design.
Schafer: But it's like I have plot points, you know.
I have things where I know I want that to end, Act One.
And then that ends Act Two.
And then I have these plot points that happen.
And then to get to that plot point you have to create obstacles and puzzles at the same time, which come out of the story.
Break out of routine.
Spaceship boy has this routine that he's stuck in every day in space and he has to break out of it.
That's the first puzzle.
You do work backwards.
Like you know, it's like you actually aren't designing puzzles.
You're designing the obstacles in a lot of ways.
Like you say, you had a situation in the game where character, you just know there's a plot point where they have to shoot the President.
And so, I don't have any plans to shoot the President.
So, but anyways, say that was a puzzle in the game.
The President's really bad.
You got to shoot the President.
You know, I work backwards, so some cool wish fulfillment, like OK, he's going to be, he's sneaking into the White House.
How would you sneak into White House?
You could wear a mask that made you look like a visiting ambassador.
Like how do you make a plaster cast of his face to make the mask?
Then maybe it's to trick him into tripping and falling in cement.
And then at each point you think, OK, was that an actual revelation?
Like you don't want to have, it just be a series of tedious chores.
It's got to be like oh, I have a really clear problem that I need to solve.
Like the three most obvious ways to solve it don't work.
And the game anticipates that and like has a great response for when you try to execute that solution.
You put a little like, aha!
Good try, no.
But did you think about this?
And that little nudge is like, oh, you know, kind of, like doesn't give you the answer
but kind of points you back towards the ballpark where the answer is.
Schafer: This is the first puzzle.
So the puzzle is that you open this a little bit.
And then you try to go to it, it closes.
And then there's some really counterintuitive, almost opposite of normal way of thinking that makes you realize, ah!
If I did this really weird thing, that would actually work.
The thing you had to do with the lock is take the lock and actually lock the gate shut.
So now when you try to pull the chain, it can't pull the gate up and instead...
'Cause then the player's like, oh, I'm so smart, you know.
I figured it out.
Now that a lot of stuff is designed ahead of those guys and they're able to look at it and work on it.
That always relieves a little bit of tension.
Rice: Tim has filled in, it looks like boy world and I think he's even put more girl world stuff in.
Have you even looked at this, really, Levi?
Ryken: This is all Tim does?
I thought he was supposed to be writing things, not just writing little things on Post-its.
Rice: Yeah, he's writing the whole game on little Post-its.
Ryken: Oh, OK.
Rice: There wasn't much there before, so it's nice to see that it's filled out.
Rice: It's definitely unique and different than anything he's designed or written before.
So I think it's cool to see that he's trying something different and kind of going out on a limb a little bit.
I haven't seen any writing yet, so I don't know what that's going to be like.
Because it does seem like this game has a much more serious tone than his other games have,
but I'm excited to get to that point where I start seeing Tim's writing, because I'm sure it'll be awesome.
Rice: So far this is in the game.
This is all in the game.
It looks like this.
And now we're going to be starting on some of this stuff.
Rice: And we have an approved girl, so that's exciting.
Petty: So let's see.
So let's look at the suicide girl. So she's got...
Schafer: See, you call her suicide girl, too.
Petty: Yeah. Schafer: It's sacrifice girl.
Petty: I know it is.
So which of these dresses do you like the most?
Schafer: My favorite one is that one, but I like the original one.
I like that one, too.
Schafer: So I just put them in front of my daughter and let her pick.
That solved the whole problem.
Schafer: These are the princesses from papa's new game.
Schafer: I call them princesses.
Which one do you like best?
Think really hard.
Why do you like em?
Daughter: Because she's so beautiful.
Rice: And she's looking good.
We just got her in the game.
She's walking around and everything.
The boy's getting there.
We've done like two rounds on him.
Schafer: Scott's been working on characters in the morning.
He's been kind of splitting his time with a book that he's working on, an art show or one of the zillion things that he does.
He's very busy.
Campbell: So it's an ongoing kind of, kind of project and this is the culmination of it.
Culmination of like a year, you know, like a year and a half's worth right now.
And then we have a book coming out, so that's what we're doing, so.
Schafer: He's drawn some of the sacrifice girl and spaceship boy.
He's been drawing some of the Cloud Colony people.
And I'm supposed to look at those, right.
I've got to give him feedback on those.
Schafer: I do like that guy, too.
But then again he is doing a cool pose.
Campbell: And it's going great, man.
It's looking really good.
I definitely feel that like relaxation of like knowing that like these designs, even if they're a little unfinished,
I know they're going to go to Bagel and he's going to make them like, fucking make 'em Bagel-style.
Dude, I just swore again.
I mean, I thought for sure I wasn't going to swear in these things.
I'm mellowing out, dude.
But yeah, he's doing great.
He has a lot of work ahead of him, though.
He's stressed about it, but Bagel's the kind of guy, he's like just this kind of chill dude, you know.
He's like, I know.
He's like, I'm going to, he's like, I'm going to have a lot of work ahead of me, but ah.
'Cause it's like it's all fun stuff, you know, he's doing what he loves, which is like painting that stuff, you know.
And he's definitely, he's definitely feeling kind of nervous, but I'm so excited for it to be his, his look, so yeah.
Offscreen Voice: So Bagel's in the studio this week? Rice: Yeah.
Bagel's in my house this week. Offscreen Voice: Perfect.
Rice: He had to take Marius's spot from the couch.
So Marius got kicked out.
I'm like running a hostel right now.
Stapley: Yeah, it's weird.
There's a lot of farting going on.
He has these weird nerdy glasses that he wears at night.
Schafer: Why is Bagel in the office this week?
I don't know.
Hi guys.
Schafer: Hi, oh my god you look so real.
Lee: He's come out of the camera!
Schafer: The microphone is working so well today.
Bagel: My microphone is awesome!
Crook: Now we can't turn you down.
Schafer: Lee was starting some new processes with art production, like trying to get Bagel to be pretty independent
where he could just paint actual art for the game right into the engines.
So getting that set up was really hard to do over Skype or Google Hang Outs, like we do.
We don't always have the smoothest conversations over that, I don't know if you noticed.
Stapley: [inaudible] Petty: I think we're going to do it tomorrow.
Stapley: [inaudible] Petty: What's that?
Stapley: [inaudible] Petty: I'm sorry, I can't make it out, dude.
Stapley: [inaudible] [Laughing]
Stapley: But it is good to kind of sit right with them, you know.
Crook: Yeah, I think this texture, the painting style goes really well with this sort of weird... Stapley: Brush stroke.
Crook: the way we're animating it.
I think it goes really well with it.
I think it's cool.
Stapley: But yeah, there are some things that are easier just to talk to, like walk over to Lee and talk to him, I think.
I've already done that like three times today, which is pretty nice.
Rice: And here like with such a small art team, like it's going to be really important that he's not only painting stuff
but like making sure it gets into the game right and looks good and he's viewing it in the game and seeing how that changes.
Petty: So like Brandon spent a lot of time making sure that all the tools he was writing
were going to help Bagel and make sure that that was a really smooth process.
Brandon: The main thing that I've been working is enhancements to our scene editor so that the tool works a little bit more like Photoshop
in terms of being able to hide and show the layers that you're working on.
I got the Nav meshes in there so that instead of just editing these in text files you can actually,
you know, individually kind of lay out the geometry for the walkable areas.
Just really trying to flesh the stuff out so that the workflow for artists is a lot smoother.
Rice: And it's almost there so I think that's the, that's the idea, is to try to get him comfortable with that process.
Stapley: Yeah, so you can see...
Right. Right, right.
Still totally getting used to this shit.
[Music] Stapley: Hey, bros. What's up?
How's it going, fellows?
Offscreen Voice: So, has this been coming along?
Stapley: Oh, it's almost done, it's almost done.
No, I'm just kidding.
It's not done at all.
I'm going to give up on it and come back to it later.
And there's a bunch of other shit to do and I like don't have any fresh eyes on it anymore, you know.
I've just been looking at the same thing for like a week and I'm over it.
I'm going to just work on it until stand-ups and then Tim's going to check it out.
Petty: In terms of like how good the readability is.
If it's feeling right to you, you know, story, theme-wise and all that, before he digs into some of the other areas.
And then you know, like there's a lot of, like because that Cloud Colony...
Schafer: I can see how the world's going to look pretty and how it's going to all look like it's one cohesive thing,
but the secret thing that I'm hoping for is still, we have some of the, Bagel's ideas that only he would come up with for the landscape.
Kind of bizarre.
He doesn't have those in there yet.
Stapley: Yeah, this was Peter's, Peter's concept ideas.
Lee's layout.
Would I do a painting of this?
I'm not sure.
I don't know if I would.
But like I'm doing a painting of it now.
OK, man.
I'm wondering about that Bagel filter thing.
I'm just wondering what it is, you know.
What if Tim's happy with it.
I should talk to Tim.
Schafer: I have not talked to him about that.
I haven't talked to him on this trip about how he's feeling about everything.
That'll be interesting.
Hopefully we get some alone time.
Petty: I just don't know about the painting Bagel.
Now how are you feeling about the like...
We've been going back and forth a long time just trying to get a feel for that whole process.
Stapley: The paining process? Petty: Yeah.
And then like work on this big ass fucking layered files and...
Stapley: Yeah, yeah. I'm comfortable with that.
I'd like to actually get involved more with like the concept stuff, though.
Petty: Yeah?
Stapley: I feel like I'm just kind of a painter.
I just feel like people are expecting it to be mine somehow, you know, just 'cause, you know.
That's what people are saying.
And like it's supposed to be my style but it isn't really.
Petty: It may be that you're feeling like the painting isn't the side that you care about most.
Maybe you feel more about the shape, language and the concept design and we, you know, Levi does painting and you do layouts.
There's flexibility there.
Stapley: Where like I don't paint everything but be kind of like overlook, you know.
Kind of just try to keep everything together.
And that way I'm able to do some more idea stuff.
'Cause even now the way it's going, like I don't think, I mean, like even this way
I don't think I'd be able to do all these paintings in four months.
Seventy paintings by myself, anyway, you know.
Well, at least if we're going to say like this is Bagel's style game, then I would, yeah, at least I would have a little bit more like yeah,
you know, that is my stuff. You know.
Instead of like, ah, it's like an awesome Peter Chan drawing or something, you know, that I colored.
Why don't we like finish off this sprint until the end of the month, right.
I'll try to get all this cloud things going.
Petty: But I think it's a tougher thing where that if we come up with a sketch of a plan that we think might work,
then I think we should try it sooner than later, 'cause fuck a sprint.
Who cares? I don't care.
There's no publisher fucking us in the ass over it.
Like with just the whole point is, it's just there to like be milestones as we make this game, right?
So if we, you know, as long we're meeting Tim's goals for the project, as long as we think we can actually get it done
and as long as we're all willing to give it a shot, there's no reason in the world we shouldn't be flexible. Right.
Stapley: I think it was because really when it first started, it was going to be like $300,000
and we're going to just try to do some retro Day of the Tentacle shit, you know.
And I know things change so much from the beginning of this Kickstarter thing, you know.
And I know now it's huge, it's a big thing, which is great.
And it's awesome.
But, I think we can work it out somehow.
Schafer: You know, right now Bagel's been doing a lot of painting, which is not necessarily, I can see where that would feel like,
you're just like doing a coloring book or paint-by-numbers.
Those are just my terms, not his.
Stapley: I don't know.
I don't even know how it's going to turn out.
It might turn out totally different.
I'm just kind of glad I got it off my chest, that's all.
Schafer: Yeah, I think his coming out here in person is what allowed him to open up about that.
I think he's over Skype.
It's hard to really talk about, how you're feeling.
Stapley: I'm glad I said it, because I was all worried about it.
So I think so.
I think we're going to try to start doing that.
Schafer: Like I'll feel a lot better once we made one of something.
Like once, 'cause I was feeling like we had not yet accomplished, the game was looking good and coming along, right.
But we'd not yet accomplished that thing of seeing something in the playable version of the game that had that crazy Bagel-style yet.
Like the special element of like surrealism or just kind of dream logic that his paintings might have.
I hadn't yet seen in the game yet.
So once we have something like that in the game, I'll be like, OK, great.
We just need to do that a whole bunch of times then I'll feel a lot more relaxed.
But until you achieve that, there's always this question of like will you be able to achieve what you want to do.
You know, it's tricky, 'cause you got to make, get the game to look the way you want it to look,
but also get done on time with the people that you have and also all those people have to be happy.
Yeah, like you're trying to get people to contribute their whole selfs to the project.
So that's challenging.
But it's what I spent the most of my time recently, like the last ten years recently, like doing, like trying to solve that problem.
How to make a group of people work well together and bring the best ideas forth and make good stuff together.
[Music]