Stamos: Just even taking like what's the new schedule out of it for a second, it's like can we finish the game for, you know, the remaining amount of money?
Because I think we're in a situation where we need to significantly increase our funding for this game.
Or significantly reduce the scope of the game.
[Music] Rice: OK.
Stamos: That said, really talking about the overall schedule.
Right now the overall schedule for Red's is posted as April.
And I think there's a sense from the team that that's not actually a feasible timeframe.
Min: I think, I think just the larger goal is when, like hey, when's our Alpha?
What's that mean?
When's our Beta?
When do we ship?
When's that, our big trailer coming.
Those are sort of like, like the few hi level stuff that I like to kind of get an idea of.
When are the ports coming online?
So it does worry me, because that does make a big difference in terms of what to do now.
Crook: And for me, like dates and things, just working here for this long...
I've just gotten used to things change and so I don't freak out.
And I think, you know, there were times where it was, yeah, we've had people freak out and like leave because they freaked out.
And so I kind of learned that, you just sort of, we'll figure it out.
Stamos: Not enough of work has been done for the team to have confidence that they're really halfway through.
Stamos: And I think there's a lot of work to do still, to understand really what the scope is,
but it's coming into, it's coming into view.
I think it's expanded a lot from what they originally thought.
And when projects evolve like that, you need to really reevaluate the plans.
So having a clear plan in place that you can iterate on is a good start.
So I want to get like the tools in place and help Greg get the tools in place to have that, so that there's a plan that he can easily iterate on.
So that's mostly what I'm helping with.
Stamos: Job number one is to make this game awesome, because it's just too important to do anything else.
First steps first is to figure out at least where we're landing.
And so that's not pick a date and work back from that.
It is more of a bottoms-up.
Let's map out everything that we know about the game and then really see how long it will take.
Schafer: Like can we do that before this milestone is over or after?
'Cause what we'll find out in this milestone is if we can bring, if we can bring, Cloud Colony to Alpha to Beta that'll mean something.
Not the end of all our problems, but it'll mean something.
If we can't bring it to Beta, that'll be even more informative in a way.
Schafer: But I never believe that we're going to be late, but I've been late before, a couple times.
Three or four. Every time, most of the times.
So we really want to prove that we can get the Cloud Colony done this month so we can prove that we're, we're picking up the pace
and we're, you know, we can finish stuff.
Schafer: It's great. I mean this is what I've been waiting for, it's been really frustrating to be in the writing cave
and the designing cave for a long time.
'Cause it's like work's being done on the game and I'm not participating in it.
and now I'm getting much more, being much more participatory.
And I feel like, I feel like I'm able to point at what needs to get done and push on it to get it done more.
Schafer: There's two things like for me, now the first one was pretty much the same as this is, but it's just like harder to list out.
Things that I'm looking to find answers for.
'Cause I want find answers to almost everything, like is the game working?
Is the game right?
Is it, like you have this feeling after the sprint and like that's exactly what the game's going to look like,
but as far, as close as we can except for the things that are obviously we can't.
That's the first one.
The second one sounds like, it sounds like a disagreement but it's not a disagreement.
It's really just working at it from the other end.
It's that I really want the Cloud Colony be done.
I mean like done with the Cloud Colony, 'cause we've been working on it for long time
and we have a lot of other areas to get to.
And so I want to have it be, as much as possible, have the approach of like we're not coming back to the Cloud Colony.
I want to be approaching it like we're finishing off in terms of Beta, you know.
Schafer: So we're going to go, actually go through the game play and make sure we itemize all the things that need to be done.
Franzke: That's the idea.
All right.
And you were, Greg is the official note taker.
Rice: Yes. Schafer: OK.
So I'm trying to solve a puzzle.
I'm trying to make Jessie like me.
Jessie doesn't like me.
So when you go over here and you interact with Jessie, where the hell did I go?
There, what's that?
What was that?
Kipnis: That's if you click off the nav mesh or something like that.
Like that, that happens.
Schafer: Her turning animation's a little much.
Kipnis: It's a little much? Do you want it to be shorter?
Schafer: Well, it makes it really unresponsive that she has to do that turn.
You kind of want her to just move right away.
Rice: Play-throughs are awesome, yeah.
'Cause it gets everybody in the same room together looking at it at the same time.
It like nails Tim down to where like he has to like sit there and play it with everybody in a room and get directly like,
point out the things that he's not happy with.
Because I mean, he plays it a lot and he'll send the email feedback and he'll bring things up in stand-ups and stuff.
But it's nice to just be able to sit there and like everybody see it on the screen together
and like know the things that he is not happy with and that need work.
Schafer: So first I have to solve that puzzle.
So I come back here and I'm like...
[Groans] Schafer: So task for Oliver, make that crash optional.
Franzke: All right. Optional crash system.
The game has encountered a problem.
Do you want to crash now?
No. All right. Game is recovered.
[Music] Schafer: One of the hard things about making an adventure game
is that the team doesn't often find the game fun when they're working on it.
It's not like a first person shooter where even if you're working on a first person shooter, it's fun to play it.
But an adventure game, you know all the solutions, all the puzzles and you know all the jokes.
So there's no like discovery or you know, you know, wonder or...
It's fun to see it come together and it's fun to see that you're making something good.
But you don't stay late.
No one's going to stay late to like play Red's after, after hours.
Hey, you want to play Red's?
Yeah, let's do it.
Let's hook it up.
'Cause like, oh, yeah, I know.
This is the puzzle I wired up.
So and that's always been sad.
Schafer: OK. I'm trying to remember how to actually make games.
I'm trying to program.
First let me get all the latest stuff.
It's syncing up.
Now I'm going to run the game.
Never actually done this before.
This is gonna be embarrassing.
We should film the second time I do this.
'Cause the second time I'll be like [makes computer noises]
oh, this is Unix. I know this.
[computer noises] Offscreen Voice: Is that Jurassic Park?
Schafer: That Jurassic Park joke.
Is that getting too old to make that reference?
I'm hoping I can actually just enter dialogue myself into the engine.
'Cause you know, when you, you know, for a long time from Psychonauts and Brutal Legend stuff,
I'd write dialogue and then someone like Anna or Kee or someone would have to come and implement it.
But then you don't get to really like tweak it.
Like I like to put stuff in and then see how the timing works out and then mess with it.
And also it'd be nice while I was writing if I didn't think I was just creating a whole bunch of work for someone else to do.
It'd be great if I could, if I'm going to put it into Excel or if I'm going to put it into a database,
I might as well just put it into the game.
And then I'm not creating work for, you know, that way Anna can work on something else and I can just do this.
And also at my age I really would like to learn something so I don't have Alzheimer's.
But I think it's too late.
I think I have it 'cause I can't figure out at all what's happening.
How do I open this scene?
How do I open?
Open in project?
That's a bunch of things.
Can you believe I have a CS degree?
Class of '89.
Voice.
X vertical Font.
Where's the dialogue?
Where's your dialogue?
I'm going to go ask her really quick.
I'll be right back.
Schafer: And then I'll totally be able to program this entire game myself.
I got it.
I totally had it all figured out.
Wait...
This looks totally different than on her computer.
Why did she set me up like this?
She totally lied to me.
I'm going to have to go back there and ask her again.
Ugh.
Schafer: Like in theory, me being able to program my own dialogue in the game would save time.
It's not there quite yet.
See, I'm taking up Anna's time but it's going to save her time later, when I can program the entire game myself.
Let's see if I remember anything that Anna showed me.
I don't remember anything that Anna showed me.
It's annoying because I did touch stuff and now I don't know if I touched something.
I pretty much reverted everything I touched.
Schafer: So embarrassing.
Schafer: I got it. I'm in.
I've hacked the mainframe.
I'm totally, I'm seeing all the beauty that is Red's simultaneously at once.
Well, that's a day's work. Done.
Schafer: But there's this pressure to, we got to meet the milestone.
I just got to get all this writing done.
I can't be messing around with like this stuff.
So I changed gears and just focus on getting all the dialogue done and it means that Anna has to spend a lot of time implementing it,
but the question is will there be a point where I can actually, you know, get up and running enough on the programming to make that efficient?
I don't know.
Kipnis: There's just a lot more content, I think, in these, in Cloud Colony than there has been in the other stuff that we've had.
And it's a lot of work to get it all implemented.
Crook: I don't know. It'll be all right.
It'll be OK. It's always this way.
Ryken: It's, I think back the first game that I worked on was Brutal Legend and that was, that was my concept for what, you know, games are like, you know.
And in this one it's like, it's not going to take four and a half years?
Sounds like a good game for me.
But yeah, there's a lot of iteration in the beginning and then you find, you get closer to the spirit of the game
and I feel like when the game starts gelling together, kind of like the way just recently the girl got a shadow.
And I was like happier than high hell that Just the smallest little thing goes into the game and it,
it's no longer just this, this animated stick figure walking around.
It's gelling it together and it gets exciting, it gets exciting because like those things are going to be there as we're carving out
those little connectors to the world that you're walking in, you know.
They're going to be there when we start on new areas already and you're going to have a feel for walking through the spaces
and it's really cool.
Schafer: Look at that sinking!
That's awesome.
I can't save her!
I can't save her, I can't save her! Get up!
Oh my God, I've had this dream.
Schafer: No, I get more excited about this game every day because as it starts to come together,
because we started from just scratch, it's cool to actually see it become real, you know.
Because of the framerate I can't click anywhere Schafer: But I think the game is looking a lot better,
the characters are really pretty.
The backgrounds are getting better and better looking.
And you know, we're starting to see the basic interface working now.
And with music in, you know, it's starting to really feel like a real adventure game.
Ryken: And I was just doing the flat paint over on the art that we had that Lee did, sent out.
Schafer: All right, everybody.
Let us break.
And let us do this again next week.
Stapley: So yesterday I was just sort of going through and painting a bunch of the scenes files.
And now I'm just addressing all that feedback from the walk-through, play-through.
Ryken: Yesterday I was drawing hands for the girl and then I got sick of drawing hands for the girl.
So I stopped drawing hands for the girl.
Hands are the worst!
Why does anybody want to do hands?
Petty: So now she has hooks?
Ryken: Yeah. She's always going like this.
Fietzek: And yesterday I did some last final changes on the forum post, which is online now.
So also, this is my last stand-up, which is so sad.
And yeah. You know, like I, yeah, I want to say a tiny bit.
I'm not so good at this, but just a big thank you to all of you guys.
It's been an amazing three months.
You guys are all amazing and amazing people.
I'm so thankful for that internship and I did a group picture of us.
Kipnis: Awww!
Franzke: That's awesome.
[Laughter] Everyone on the team, including you guys.
Kipnis: Aww dude, thanks a lot. Bagel: Lets just scan that in.
Fietzek: I'll send it around.
Kipnis: Should we make it poster size?
Fietzek: It should be big enough.
Petty: Thank you, Marius.
Thank you for all your hard work here.
It's been awesome having you here.
[Applause] Schafer: I thought we might be able to convince Marius to stay
because we would have had to just derail his education as I said, but there was, I was not expecting the real reason
he was going back to Germany, which was for love.
And though we are evil enough to end education, we could not fight the force that is love.
Schafer: We were trying to set up a contract where he could keep doing what he's doing from Germany, making animatics for us.
It's kind of like when Scott Campbell and Nathan moved to New York.
I would just try and keep those guys working for us because I, you don't, you know, people, people who are talented people
don't come around every day and you got to like hang onto them when you can.
Marius: Yeah. I can try coming back next year.
[Music] Schafer: I feel like now we're actually moving at the speed that we're moving at.
As soon as they get all locked down with the process between Bagel and Levi and Lee,
I think it'll be, feel like we're moving at a good clip.
Offscreen Voice: So you're back?
Stapley: I'm back in action. Red's.
No way man.
Tim should wear my hat.
[Music] Stapley: I'd like to actually get involved more with like concept stuff, though.
Yeah, I feel like I'm just kind of a painter.
Petty: Well, you and I talked about that, right?
And you said you, Stapley: Yeah, yeah, but like...
Petty: you wanted to do, Stapley: the way it's turning with, because all the designs are approved, so it's basically like, it's approved.
You know what I mean?
Petty: Individuals have changed what they wanted to do.
You know, initially Bagel did want to do a lot of painting.
And I think as we started getting into that, he felt like hey, you know, I really want to be more on the compositional side, which is fine, you know.
But that means we're going to have to shift things around.
Petty: Do you think this process is going to make that better?
Stapley: Which process?
Petty: Whatever, we're sort of being non-specific...
Stapley: I think having more hands painting and oh, well, I don't know.
I think I would feel, well, at least if we're going to say like this is Bagel's style of game,
then I would, yeah, at least I would have a little bit more like yeah, you know, that is my stuff.
Stapley: Like this sacrifice scene.
This is actually, I did the layout in this one and the camera angles.
And I feel good how that went.
Offscreen Voice: It's more Bagel.
Stapley: Yeah, I feel, yeah, like this is maybe more Bagel.
A little bit.
Petty: Click down, like just double click towards the bottom so she walks down there.
Schafer: What the? Whoa..!
Schafer: Yeah, I like the, the first tested out was the sacrifice area, the new method.
And I really liked that.
It's pretty and I like that whole setup.
I like the crazy big bird cages that are moved and ripped open and I think those are cool.
So it's promising.
Stapley: Yeah. So now it's just, I guess there's just a question of like talking to Levi and Lee this week
and figuring out the paint, how to make it look consistent, you know.
That's, I think, the big major thing right now.
All right, you know, that's the thing, a worrisome thing that we should work on.
Petty: So this is the very old one, right?
Based on the color key.
So, I painted this one entirely with a charcoal brush, 'cause when we started I thought that's what we're doing on that one.
So it's, I think it's, it's a little too linear.
It's too charcoal-y and colors are all wrong.
Petty: It's been difficult.
It's weird, it's weird finding out which area, why it's been difficult.
Part of it has been has been, he's evolving his own approach, to like the clouds specifically is very different than
sort of what painted the lumberjack.
So as his approach has been evolving, I've been trying to like paint this way and we've been changing it back and forth.
Petty: I kind of feel I knew the way we should try handling this one is, if you, say take this scene
and do like a line drawing composition and then do like a little small color key.
And then we give it to Levi and have him try and paint it.
Ryken: I feel like we wouldn't need that much of a color key, considering we were coming from an establishing shot already.
Petty: We've been doing other things as well, as like, you know, I have brush sets that I made basing on he likes to use in Photoshop
and we're kind of updating those.
So those can be given to all the artists that are painting digitally.
It's difficult.
I mean, I think one of the reasons why it made sense to have him paint stuff on the back end is it was,
it would have been, he'd be the last person touching each asset.
So it's necessarily just going to be more unified stylistically.
But by moving him to the front, it creates more, it probably gives the overall sense of things a little more quirkiness that he would have.
But it means we have more potential like consistency drifting going on, on the backside.
But yeah, I think it's been, everything's been moving pretty well actually.
I'd say we made lots of really good progress this sprint.
Dillon: Like I'm actually really happy with the progress that we made in terms of this stuff.
We got a bunch of big features in and the tool's a lot better, kind of stuff.
Rice: Just the little things, too, just like the cameras feel so much better.
Just navigating around is way better now.
Dillon: It's just one of those things where it's like, you know, getting a basic system in there is easy and
giving it enough love so that it actually feels good is hard.
Like having milestones like this where we're really focused on polishing up an area,
is a forcing function for like we have a camera system but what we actually need is a good camera system.
[Laughter] Rice: Yeah.
Dillon: So I think we may have gotten a lot of traction in a lot of different areas and that stuff this time around.
Rice: Cool. Thanks, bro.
Rice: Oh, what? How successful is the Cloud Colony stuff gonna be?
Yeah, how close are you going to be to it actually being finished .
Rice: Well, I think we'll have a better idea of that after I go around and talk to everybody, which I'm going to do right now.
Crook: But it's nice.
This is working, which is really great to have.
So you know, Rice: Yeah.
Three weeks ago we didn't have any cut scenes.
Crook: It's been sort of stuttering and going, you know, but that's smoothing out so we're making progress.
Just not as fast as we would like.
Johnstone: So he's cleaned up. Rice: She.
Johnstone: She, she. She's cleaned up.
And I'm really done in like five minutes.
Rice: Sweet. Johnstone: Jessie's.
Rice: Awesome. Cool.
Johnstone: So that's where I'm in.
That's where I'm at.
Rice: Perfect.
Why is raining on your screen?
Johnstone: Oh. It's rainy moods as a soundtrack.
It's nice.
Sometimes it's nice to listen to ambient noise.
Rice: Cool.
Johnstone: So why not?
Rice: This isn't going as fast as I was hoping it would.
Miss Kipnis, I'm coming to you.
Kipnis: So I mean, I don't, there's no way I'm going to get through my entire list, but I'll get, you know, I'll get as much as I can.
Rice: Cool. Cool.
Petty: You know, there's not a ton left.
I mean, I'm pretty much on schedule.
I'm running a little behind but it's only theoretically behind.
Rice: Sounds good, man. Petty: Yeah.
Rice: We'll see how the play-through goes tomorrow.
Schafer: Before we start, I'm going to guess that, like our goal was to finish Cloud Colony this sprint.
I have a feeling it's not finished.
Rice: You might be right.
Schafer: Oh man.
I haven't even, we have like another two week sprint that it would be great if we could finish Cloud Colony in that.
I don't want to just keep setting up the team to fail, though.
Like OK you guys, we're going to finish Cloud Colony this sprint.
OK, I didn't do it.
OK, this time we're definitely going to finish. OK, no.
That didn't work either, but OK, this sprint is the one.
So I don't want to say that, but there still is a lot to do.
I mean, you can't right now play the three puzzle branches, any of them to the end.
Rice: So yeah. Try to figure out now what you'll be looking at.
Schafer: Yeah.
So we don't know what's going to happen because, even if this sprint did finish, if we'd finish Cloud Colony we'd be looking at like,
looking at the design of the game and how much time we have.
That we would not probably finish the game in April as we had previously thought.
Rice: Um hm. Schafer: Which we're still thinking we're going to finish in April, Rice: No. Schafer: we've done some math that means, Rice: We did some equations.
Schafer: And if we go past April that would mean going past our money that we got from Kickstarter, which would be not great to do.
We're having discussions with Isa and Justin about what, how we want to deal with that.
So I don't think we're going to conclude any of that in this meeting, but that's the problem that we're working on outside of this, too.
Schafer: So see how much we did get done.
Rice: Yes. So there's, I have two files on Google Drive.
One is the budget, one is schedule.
The original schedule that we made was like an attempt to get as many people on the team as we can
and try to include like all of the things outside of that camp that we need to pay for.
And then like fit a game into that time, essentially right.
And like as we were progressing like it was obvious that we weren't tracking to anything that was going to fit in that time.
So now the hope is to try to start from scratch on a new schedule, taking in account like what we've seen with Cloud Colony
and how long it's taken us to do that.
How many other additional screens and areas are left in the game as its currently spec'd
and try to take a new stab based on what we know now, at how long we think it'll actually take to make the game that you are designing.
Stamos: So the new budget for this scenario includes going all the way to September and the increased team size,
which the increased team size is, you know, like four or five people.
Bailey: And has like 1.1 million dollars more costs.
Stamos: Yes. But the thing about this schedule is that it assumes at a certain point that systems work gets done
and that the team gains efficiency and the number of scenes almost doubles at a certain point in the project in order to get it done.
So it's actually pretty aggressive.
Bailey: Then I have to go find, I need to find money.
Stamos: Yeah. That is the concern.
Bailey: OK. Because right now, you know, it looks like, you know, the plane's kind of diving down a little bit
and we just need to, we have time to pull up.
Schafer: What does the plane diving down stand for?
Bailey: That's, just
Schafer: Us crashing?
Bailey: Yeah.
Schafer: The whole company crashing into the ground.
Is that what you're saying or are you being, Bailey: I mean, the nicest, so the thing is that Red's, this project is,
it's going to determine the studio's success going forward.
It's a major portion of my forecast of the health of the studio.
It hitting next year is absolutely necessary and how successful it is once it, you know, is out there and it's live, you know,
determines our ability to be independent and kind of have our own creative control, like that we're enjoying now.
So...
Schafer: It just seems wrong to make it cost more than we got.
Because we were so lucky to get the money that we got, because I'm going to feel like this moral thing to finish it
for that amount of money or less.
And I'm sure our business guy would love for us to finish for less.
But the game also has to be really good.
And it is an important game to the studio.
And strategically it's an important game for us because we own it.
We will, we don't have to share the money with any sort of other party, investor or publisher, you know, it's all ours.
So it makes sense for us to make a really good game.
Bailey: We have to, we have to deliver on the vision and I don't think it's going to be done in the budget.
So we have to find more money.
And I feel like not only does it need to deliver on what the community is hoping it is
and the people that actually backed it, but the whole community in general and the crowd funding that's actually occurred since then, we're the poster child.
And we're the poster child, you know, succeed or fail.
And so, you know, we'd like to see more games funded this way.
Rice: I think it's also just important to keep in mind that there's like other impacts besides just funding the game.
And that like if we now go get a publisher for this game then it's suddenly like voids everything we've said about the project
and everything we're trying to do.
It's hard and I know like we're looking at a number that's large, that we're saying we need.
But like as much as possible just trying to make sure that it's as good of money as this money was.
Bailey: I think, you know, there are, obviously there are financial realities that we have to be conscious of, but I mean the reality is that, you know,
it needs to be a Double Fine game and the quality and it has to deliver on Tim's vision
and so it comes back to, you know, can we, what would be like the minimum scope of the game
that you would feel it's still, delivers on how you envisioned it.
Schafer: I mean, every time I've been up against this kind of situation, which is almost every time, there's scope
and then there's money, then there's efficiencies and I've never seen this solved any other way than all of the above.
Stamos: Yeah. Schafer: You know what I mean?
Some scope reduction, some efficiency improvements, some extra money.
Not like any one of those things being the answer.
Bailey: Ok. Ok.
Rice: We can get it done.
Bailey: Should we do like an all hands in and team?
[Laughter] Rice: Yeah man.
Rice: OK.
Bailey: Alright guys.
Rice: OK. Let's keep those.
Rice: Ultimately the number one decider in the schedule is when do we feel like we have a game that we're proud of.
So it's trying to figure out the best plan of attack to get us to where we feel proud of the game and are ready to put it out.
But I think we're safe to assume at this point that it's definitely past April.
So we just gotta kind of figure out when that is.
And how we're going to get there.
We'll handle it.
[Music] Schafer: What we've really done
is we've really banked the entire company on this one project and if even one thing goes wrong, it'll take down the whole games industry.
Is that kind of what you're, or you mean it like more like a Phil Fish thing?
Now that, you're gonna use that.
That's when you know.
Listen, that was copyright Phil Fish.
I can't do that.