Brown: Good, a little more slowly.
Technician: And, 115.
Kaufman: Not quite.
We won't activate the Omicron Inhibitor until we're ready to take the shields down.
Brown: Mm!
Yes.
Sorry.
I'm steppin' on you, but: Wow. Yum.
Schafer: "Wow. Yum." Brown: Dude, I love when--
When they get it right, it's like, fuck.
Schafer: I want to eat your voice when you poop it out.
Brown: It's the best.
Just fucking poopin' in my mouth.
I'm saying that just for you.
[Music] McConnel: Um...
I just really like to... to be here whenever I can make it up the...hill.
It is a little reminiscent of the field that the girl starts out in, now, isn't it?
When I did that theme, um...we hadn't moved yet.
Uh, so I sorta had to imagine that field and work to the picture, um...
But you know, uh...
The idea of a...
of a beautiful field with solitude that you can go to to just get away from everything
and with a little village below is-is definitely, uh...
you know, definitely resonates.
So maybe I...now that we're moving back to the girl's world, maybe it's time for me to take more of these walks.
[Music] Schafer: What is happening here?
What has been going on?
I've been so isolated writing in here.
What else has been going on?
Every time I play the game, it's got new crazy stuff in it, which looks awesome.
Franzke: So here's the start screen.
And if I can basically linear blend into 8-bit mode and come out again and go back.
And the game is actually full--fully playable.
Schafer: I don't know. Oliver just snuck that in over the weekend.
He's like, "Hey, hit this-- hit this key." And I was like, "Why?" And I hit it.
It was like, pow, awesome.
Franzke: Um...and there are a bunch of things that are happening.
I mean, obviously it's pixelated, but we're also, like, kind of compressing
the color range as well, like in the old days.
So we're kind of trying to emulate that you only have 256 colors.
Like, since the beginning of the project, I was like, well, you know, I really like the old-school games.
I like the pixelated art style that we had back then.
Um...and then I was like, well, I wonder if I can just, like, take the image and do some
just shader work to it to, like, make it look like, you know, it's a game made in the '90s sometime,
like a little bit 8-bit.
Uh, and it works pretty well, actually.
So far it seems okay, actually.
I thought I would be way more stressed out.
So far it's okay, and probably, uh, when you do the-- when you can do the whole cutting thing,
you can cut, like, you know, months in the future; I will be sitting here like, oh my God!
Schafer: And the team is bringing up the last parts of "Act 1" to alpha level.
Um, starting work on the pyramid.
There's a pyramid in the game that's getting brought to alpha this week,
and it's looking awesome.
Well, alpha is just that there's something rough in there representing everything.
There's like, mm-- all the assets are, like-- Something's in there taking a place for them.
And then--and then you get them all workin' the way you want them to for beta.
And then after beta, you're hopefully just fixing bugs.
Way ahead of schedule.
Rice: We're--we're good.
We're where I said we should be.
Schafer: Well, things move quick once you-- You know, you have certain deadlines.
Like, we wanted to get a bunch of, um, voice done so we could get a PAX trailer.
And, um, also 'cause the animators are waiting for the voice to start--
They haven't finished, like, a single scene in the game yet 'cause then you want the final voice in there.
So we wanna get that done, and once it starts rolling, it, um, it goes pretty quickly.
Crook: You know, when they play, go through the playthroughs and stuff right now, sort of the animation
is sort of the least polished, oftentimes.
And, um, and so sometimes it's rough, like, to sit through playthroughs, you know,
and-and know that the quality is not there yet just 'cause you haven't gotten to that phase.
Schafer: Greg came in; he has a question for us.
Brown: Greg! Rice: Hi.
Brown: How are you doing?
Rice: I am doing well, how are you?
Brown: Hey, I'm good.
Rice: Sweet. Um, no, I just, uh, I got an email from our new executive assistant
that was trying to set up Tim's flights, so I wanted to see how things were looking
and if she should go ahead and do that.
Brown: So if each one of these characters has at least 80 lines to read, then, yes.
Rice: I think we're gonna have enough written.
Schafer: So that's a question for Malena or someone with access to the database.
Rice: We can have Malena run that right now.
Schafer: Okay. Today we're gonna start.
Please welcome Malena.
Malena Annable.
Annable: I'm so happy to be here with you guys.
Schafer: Here in person. She's come through the magic of the screen to our world.
Just like the monsters in "Pacific Rim." She is a producer,
and she specializes in localization and things involving the dialogue database.
Um...even though she's up in Portland, she remotely tracks all that stuff
and she does localization for all of our games.
And, um, she is the one pushing on me for the writing deadline to get it into Khris' hands, 'cause it kinda goes,
she gets the raw writing and puts it in the database, and, um, and gets the script all ready to hand off to Khris.
That's a good question; why is she here?
Maybe she's up to something.
Annable: Yeah, I wanna talk to you about more dialogue things and...
Schafer: I have to write more dialogue? Annable: Yeah, you do.
Schafer: God. Annable: You don't want me to write it.
Schafer: Gotta be done by now. It's gotta be done by now.
Annable: So, yeah, so I'm-I'm busy with that all week.
I'm happy to see everyone. Schafer: But if I write it this week, it'll screw up the schedule, 'cause...
Okay.
Annable: So I want Tim to write in the way that whatever feels most comfortable to him.
And as fast as possible.
Dialogue is so important to our games, so making sure that we have, like, a really strong system--
I have--there's a dialogue database that Paul Du Bois built and it's amazing.
And it's just--for me, it's just management of, like, you know, tens of thousands of files.
I mean, "Brütal Legend," there are over 35,000 lines of dialogue,
and I had to manage that across five languages.
And...it wasn't that bad.
Rice: But, yeah, we could have Malena check out current status of lines per character.
And so if that happens, you think, um, like, casting-wise we'll be ready?
Brown: Um, I think we will. I think we're, like-- I think by the end of this meeting
we will know who we're gonna choose for everything, and then it'll be me calling and checking avails
on them all for next week.
Schafer: And then a lot of our friends are coming back.
Richard Horvitz, the voice of Raz, is gonna be doing some voices.
And Jennifer Hale, um, from "Brütal Legend" and "Mass Effect," is gonna be--
Yes, Shepard is gonna be doing, uh, I think the Mom computer.
Um...and that's all we have to announce right now as far as voice, but that's very exciting stuff.
Get that all wrapped up so we'll actually have something that we can put into the game and show at PAX.
This weekend?
This weekend, oh my God, it's coming up so soon.
We're flying down to LA to record the voice for the game, at least a third of it.
It's a third of the voice for the game.
And we've got some, um, interesting people coming down to do voice.
Some old friends, some hopefully new friends.
We'll be locked in a room together, me and Khris Brown, for four days.
[Music] Horvitz: There is no room in the Space Weaver's life for friendship.
Brown: Aww... Horvitz: He slides alone, like a shuttle of yarn across the warp of time
on an ever so--shortening-- Schafer: Fucked that up.
How can you fuck that up?
You totally fucked that up.
Horvitz: I love that!
That is so fucking good.
All right. Here we go.
Schafer: It's kinda like he's Pee Wee, rebel, loner.
Technician: And, 24.
Horvitz: Look, see, see, look at this, look at this island in front right here, see?
And it's just like this hairline's receding.
I can't stand it.
Brown: Really? Schafer: Lice check? Lice check?
Brown: It looks good. Horvitz: No, not...
Brown: Tim, you have lice.
We have never cast a game this quickly.
Um, and we have never cast a game with, um, a budget this limited.
I mean, it-- with the exception of, you know, with "Day of the Tentacle," you have, like,
1,500 lines, you know what I mean?
But even then, I think, um...
I think we probably spent more money on "Day of the Tentacle." That's Tim, who started the company,
and he was one of the chief game designers at LucasArts, working on, like, "Monkey Island"
and kind of this whole, um, set or series of games
that people feel really strongly about.
They have a really strong emotional connection to those games, and then we've continued...
I started at LucasArts in 1990.
And there were 60 of us.
Like, LucasArts was 60 people.
I mean, we were a bunch of goofball rejects.
It's not--it's not how it is now, where you have guys who go to college
and then video games is a place where you can be successful financially.
Do you know what I mean?
We were all kids who were alone...
and computers were...
our friends, you know?
And so then we were in a safe place where we could be together.
So, yeah, we super bonded.
Um, all of us.
I mean, we all still talk to each other and I think we'll talk to each other
for the rest of our lives.
Schafer: Yes, we do know each other really well, 'cause she was back at Lucas back in the '90s.
So we've known each other for a long time.
You get into a lot of strange, um...
kinda routines in the studio.
When you--it's like-- for some reason, sitting in the recording studio is grueling.
Like, you're just sitting in this little chair, you're hearing voices, but like after a day of that
you're like, oh my God, I was in this tiny room all day.
Like, I mean, maybe it's like editing for you guys.
But it's like, you're in a tiny room, faced with a big control panel and you're talking
over this inter--I don't know why it's so exhausting.
I am so delirious from that 30-hour session that I, uh, I don't even know who I am anymore.
Brown: It's almost like it was "Brütal Legend." Schafer: Oh, God.
Thirty hours.
I delegated all the hard sessions of that one.
I only come for the movie stars.
Brown: You're tellin' me, man.
Schafer: I mean, I only come for the stuff.
Brown: You only come for the important stuff.
Schafer: I leave the stuff where the script is really idiot-proof.
Do you like that term?
That's like a writing term.
Like, it's director-proof.
Yeah.
In screenwriting class they're like, "You gotta really write your script so it's director-proof."
Brown: That's because people were working with directors who aren't me.
Schafer: It's just--it's a...
That's obviously not the way I feel.
Brown: What?
Schafer: That's obviously not the way I feel.
Brown: You just--okay, so I wanna hear Frank's blowjob story.
No, your writing is awesome.
It's perfect and fantastic.
Schafer: It doesn't compare to Frank's blowjob story.
So in between takes, um... you just start to, um...
for some reason tell extremely dirty jokes.
This is going in a weird direction, obviously.
Brown: Well, the camera's off, right?
Schafer: Nope.
It's like, um, going to some weird, uh, foxhole or trench together.
Technician: Hi, Jan. [Offscreen] Hey, how are ya?
Technician: I'm good, how are you? [Offscreen] Good. Good to see you.
Technician: You too. [Offscreen]Check, check, check, check.
Check, check.
Check, check, check, check.
Cash, cash, cash. Mark?
[Technician] Yeah, you're--no, you're good.
No, please no more.
Schafer: The boy, Shay, that's the story about a boy who was, um, raised essentially
by a giant spaceship all by himself, and he lives alone on this giant spaceship
and it's very quiet and lonely.
Um, and he's cared for by...
uh, there's a mom and a dad that appear on the computer screens and take care of him.
And these big, like, knitting arms come down for the mother and that's you, the mom.
Hale: Oh... Schafer: And it was great when he was 7, but now he's 14, he's startin' to feel
like he's tired of this kid stuff and he wants to do something real with his life
and go out on adventures.
And so he meets this shady character...
People who do--the professional voice talent people, like Jennifer Hale and Richard Horvitz,
who just do this all the time, they walk in the studio, they don't know anything about it, they grab the script
and they cold read it, and they nail it after a couple lines like that.
Brown: And they walk in, and it's like, okay, they gotta pull it out.
So it's--it is the hardest-- you know, as Jen Hale says, she's like,
"It's not just acting, it's acting on steroids." It is the hardest job.
And you can't rely on your facial expressions.
And how frantic is she when she's, um, "Shay, where are you going?
It's not safe. Shay!!!" with three exclamation points?
Schafer: Um-- Brown: Is it like yelling, or...?
Hale: On a scale of 1 to 10.
Schafer: Um, she--this is when even more hell has broken loose.
Like, the ship is actually being attacked now, and Shay is running to go fix it.
He's gonna go get his space suit.
And he's running down the hallway, and so you're in one of the orbs
and you're doing your normal thing, like, trying to calm him down, but then he's not stopping
and you're like, "Hey, he's not listening to me.
He's not listening to my-- He's not being calmed down by my thing.
And then, what's he doing?" Hale: Okay, so 4:48, is it,
"Dear God, he's going to die," or is it, "Hey, listen to me"?
Schafer: No, it's the--it is the first-- the former more.
Hale: "Dear God, he's going to die." Schafer: Like he--like's running out into a tornado, kind of like--
Hale: He's running into a tornado, okay.
Shay! There you are.
Something's happened to the ship, but don't worry.
Your father's gone out to fix it.
Shay, where are you going?
It's not safe!
Shay!!!
Brown: There we go. Schafer: Wow.
Schafer: Nice. Brown: Perfect.
You know, and the actor loved it.
I mean, you really want an actor who loves what they do.
I don't hire celebrities for a payday.
At any other company, at any other studio, people will say, "Oh, let's get so-and-so!
You know, we're X studio, we have X million dollars.
Let's just pay them, because it's gonna be rear ends in seats."
And I'm like, why do you want someone who's only here for a payday?
Otherwise, it's a waste. It's a waste of money, it's a waste of the actor's time.
You don't want someone who's just, like, not having fun and not into it.
And that's the thing about Tim's writing and that's the thing about Double Fine,
is that it's so incredibly rewarding, the actors, they come in and they do it for essentially what's free.
Hale: All missions are cancelled.
I love you.
Brown: Good. Can we get, um, three in a row, um, slow and super sincere?
Hale: Uh-huh. Brown: Of "I love you"s?
Schafer: Is that just for personal use?
He--this boy is-- now that he's 14, he's startin' to feel like, "I'm sick of these--
I wanna do some actual action and get out there." Kaufman: Yeah. Schafer: And that's when he meets Marek.
He's, like, the wolf who comes out of the cracks; he's been watching.
Brown: Do you wanna hear the aud, or are you good?
Kaufman: Uh, yeah, I'll listen to it again.
I-I-I...you mean, my, uh...?
Brown: Your read? Kaufman: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
David Kaufman, Marek.
You came because you are done with children's games.
My name is Marek, and what I'm about to show you is no game.
Schafer: We were talking about that when we were casting.
It was like, well, we have this other guy we know can do it, but I really like this guy's voice, and it's new.
And I usually tend to go for that, like, really unique voice more often,
even though it's a risk, because sometimes you bring somebody in 'cause you like the audition
and you don't know anything else about them and it turns out they can't do anything else
except for that exact thing they did in the audition.
Or they can't hit the audition again.
Sometimes we've had people come in and they just can't seem to capture
the magic of the audition again.
And even-- so we'll play it for them, like, "Listen to this audition."
And they'll be like, "Um... I don't wanna do it that way." He's--the way you read that is a nice contrast to the mom,
who's--the computer is like this-- the ship's computer is like this really over-mothering mother
who's just, you know, everything is sweet and she's being so sweet to the boy all the time,
and then you're just, like, you're not cutting him any slack and you're just like,
"I'm not here to love you, right?
There's war going on." Kaufman: Tell no one.
Do you understand?
No one.
Schafer: Whoa.
Kaufman: No one.
Schafer: I like that; scary.
Brown: Perfect.
Yeah, having this dude in here has just, like, made the game, like, whoa, fuck.
I mean, to see those people come to life, I mean, as you saw with Marek, like, all of a sudden, you know,
it wasn't just these lines on the page.
It was like, holy shit.
Like, yesterday when I was listening to him I was like, oh-kay.
This game, uh...um...
It's not just a funny thing anymore.
Like, it's not just like, oh, this is really sweet and we have this sweet boy and he's coming of age.
But once we had Marek, it's like, that's the linchpin, do you know what I mean, for the boy's story.
Like, once we have him, that was crazy, you know?
And I--and I went home and I was like, okay, this game has a heart, it lives and it breathes,
because we have that conflict and we have that intrigue.
And that's, I mean, that's so amazing.
The game went from being, like, oh my God, it's cute and it has beautiful characters and da-da-da.
But, like, Marek-- And I'm-- seriously, like, I am-- these guys will tell you,
like, one, I'm s-- a total super bitch.
Two, like, like, there's--I--like...
There's no reason for me to tell you this.
Like, there's zero, right?
Kaufman: That's awesome. Brown: Yeah. It's fucking awesome.
Schafer: She's even understanding what a bitch she is.
Also that.
[Music] [Mario game sounds]
Schafer: Sorry. I'm getting really into this game now.
Brown: No, it's super cute. I like the little sounds.
Schafer: Oh, I walked right down the thing, the thing!
Brown: I really...
I'm trying to resist getting...this.
Because I wanna play "Animal Crossing." Schafer: Get "Animal Crossing." It's good for you.
Brown: I--no, I can't.
Schafer: "Animal Crossing" made me a better person.
Brown: Really? Schafer: Yeah, 'cause it's all about...
Brown: Making nice things?
Schafer: Just every day-- no, just every day doing a little bit of stuff.
Not, like, rushing through things for a goal or anything like that.
It's really-- I think it's mentally good for you to play it.
Dang it, I really suck at this game.
Brown: 'Cause every minute that I'm not either working or...
Schafer: Hello!
Hello there. Black: Hi, Tim Schafer.
Schafer: Welcome to the project "Broken Age." Black: Thank you for having me here. Is it well lit enough?
I feel like we're in a dark shadow.
Here we go.
Schafer: I feel good about this. Good.
Black: Tell me about the project.
What are we doing today?
Schafer: I'm so glad that you asked.
Black: Is this who I'm gonna be voicing?
Brown: Yes. Schafer: Yeah, Harm'ny.
We're, like--yeah, he's kinda like a guru.
Brown: He's like a cultic personality.
Schafer: And a little, like, not shady, but a little bit like, "Heyyy, hey."
'Cause he's a little bit of a fraud.
Black: Okay. I have no idea what's going on.
Schafer: And Harm'ny's main thing, he runs the cloud colony, that's his main thing.
Black: Harm'ny is a cult leader. Schafer: Yeah.
And a little bit of a fraud. Black: And he runs the cloud colony.
And is he also like other gurus, where it's also about, like, uh...
"Let me give you my seed. It's--believe me, this is--" Brown: See? All the guys wanna touch your vagina.
That's what I said: Does he wanna touch vaginas?
Because all those dudes do!
Schafer: We don't really-- Black: Well, all the gurus, it comes down to--yeah.
Brown: For sure! Schafer: We don't really explore that very much in the game, but I don't think it's--
Black: No. And we don't need to.
It's-it's-it's there, though. It's underneath.
Brown: It's implied, it's implied. Schafer: I think people assume.
Seeing Jack again was really fun.
Um, I haven't seen him for-- since the end of "Brütal." And so it was fun to see Jack again.
He was a good sport.
Black: I feel like I need to research a little while before I start acting.
Schafer: We told you way too much.
Okay, so there's a few lines today and there'll be more in-- we haven't done--
we've only written the first half of the game so far.
So when we're at the second half, I hope we can get you to come back again, yeah.
Black: Okay, you ready?
Technician: Cool, I'll give you a take number, then we'll be rolling, and if you need
your headphones adjusted, just let me know.
Black: All right, and...
Technician: It's take 1.
Black: Take 1, self "Action." Oh-ho-ho, oh my!
A fresh face rises from below.
Oh my!
Schafer: I like that.
Black: Wait, let me be more of a cult guy.
Oh my!
Oh my...
Oh my goodness.
A fresh face rises from below.
Hello.
Before you ask, let me answer.
Yes, you may live here in Meriloft forever.
Brown: That's perfect.
Schafer: I love that gentle version you just did.
Brown: Love it. Schafer: That's awesome.
Black: Before you ask, let me answer.
Yes...you may live here in Meriloft forever.
Schafer: Yaaay, I love that one.
Black: Oh, now we're gettin' somewheres.
Schafer: Yeah, it was really fun to watch Jack come in there and just start with one thing and he does it
over and over again and he kinda hones in on the character.
And we're not directing him, but we're directing him by not directing him
in that he knows that if we hear something we really, really like, we'll chime in and be like,
"That! That's perfect. That's amazing." So if he's not hearing anything, he's just gonna keep working it
and working it until, you know, he gets something that he likes and then we'll probably like it, too.
Black: What? No! What? No!
Uh...I mean...
Take it away.
I need it like I need a-- I need it like a blue jay needs a bowling ball.
Schafer: Maybe he--yeah, he really recomposes himself and does--goes back to his total, like, smooth guy voice.
Black: Oh, okay, yeah.
Black: What? No!
I'm...uh...I mean...
take it away.
I need it like a blue jay needs a bowling ball.
Brown: Good. Schafer: That's awesome. Great.
Black: Am I--am I all finito?
Brown: Yeah. Schafer: That's it for now.
Black: That was so easy! Schafer: That's so easy!
Yeah, I do have the little one, and this one.
Black: I feel like I should do something dramatic so that-- Schafer: You wanna punch me? Black: Yeah.
That'll teach you to not give me a very big part in your game.
Schafer: That felt right. That felt good.
That was dramatic.
Crook: How was recording? Was that good?
Schafer: Oh, yes. This is, like, like, dailies.
Rice: Tell us all about it.
Schafer: Uh, recording was--was awesome.
Yeah, Marek was awesome. He does this kinda creepy thing.
Kipnis: Who is he? Rice: Who is he?
Schafer: He's...he's someone who does a lot of game-- no, a lot of game work, but, um--
Kipnis: Was it Lee? Schafer: I didn't recognize his name.
It was Lee Petty.
No, he did it different than Lee.
Like, Lee was kinda like, "Yeah, you, gah..." That sounds like Lee. Rice: Yeah.
Schafer: He was more like, "Come here further--" He was--he did it a little creepier.
"While you've been traveling and plating ice cream..." Rice: Oh, that's awesome. Schafer: "...and playing with trains--"
And, uh, Richard Horvitz, who did Raz, did, um, a couple of characters.
And he did the Space Weaver.
Not as good, of course, as Dave's, but it is Raz.
None of the cut scenes have been animated because we just got the professional VO in,
so you'll hear the professional VO, but we haven't animated to it,
so it's a lot of, like, animatics, like, sliding around, which I'm sure
you've seen before in games, maybe.
Rice: You gotta wait till you have the voice to animate to it.
-Ah, okay, right. Schafer: So some of the-- some of the background art is final
and some of the in-game animation is more final, but, uh, the cut scenes definitely get super janky.
Crook: We've got all the pro VO, and so...
we just have too much work to do for the animators that we have.
I mean, we used to have a much bigger animation team, uh, which was-- it was probably a little more
than double, maybe, than what we have right now, when we were on "Brütal Legend."
Um, and, you know, people have left and we've just never replaced anybody, so...um...
So, yeah.
So, yeah, so we had to hire an outside animation team or a company.
Schafer: We have so much animation to do, we have to use outsourcers, which we've never done.
I've never done outsourced animation before 'cause we've always tested it and it's always looked terrible.
But this group looks good, and the test we did looks good, and so hopefully they'll just do some awesome stuff
that'll help us get the game done on time.
Is that it? Rice: Yep, I think so.
Schafer: Get it all out. Let's outsource the rest of it and take it-- call it a day.
Petty: Pleasure cruise. Rice: Perfect.
Schafer: Woo!
Gardner: Oh, see, he's typing.
See, that's someone typing in Portland.
What's gonna happen?
Look! See?
Aww.
See?
He, like--I think he even is a backer, too.
Yeah, see, he is a backer.
Ha!
This is Alex.
He's the guy that's supervising all of the stuff over at Super Genius.
And they're the people that we're doing the contracting with up in Portland.
So you can see in this animation, it's really-- this-this hand gesture
of the wolf, the attention that somebody spends, it really feels like there's more
than just two drawings there.
And it's that sort to attention to detail that we just don't have the time.
What we get with Super Genius is that we get to add all that character to the animations
and we get to spend all that time saying, "Hey, this'll just be hilarious if we make him, like, you know,
skip down the, you know, the hill instead of just copy the walk animation and paste it there."
And we get the-- we get to add all that stuff, but instead of right now being like,
"What are we gonna do? We're screwed!
Like, there so much work to do!" And then you ship a game and it's like you just look at it and you're like,
wow, we didn't polish that, we didn't polish that, you didn't polish this, you didn't polish that.
Like, there's always, like--there's-- you ship a game and there's-- all you see is, as an animator,
is the stuff you didn't polish.
And, uh...
You know, with Super Genius, it's like hopefully what we're gonna see is a game where it's like
that game where you're al--that I've always wanted to work on, where everything's polished,
where you look at it and you're like, the whole thing is--is all--
is done all the way.
How about this?
Hey, Ray?
Will you--so-- Crook: I'm workin'!
I'm workin'; leave me alone.
Gardner: I know, I finally got you workin'.
I want you to see this, uh-- Crook: I turned this over to you so I could just work.
I'm just kidding, I'm just kidding.
Schafer: Oh, yeah. Our expert crack team of judges are the animation department.
I mean, the animators, they're the ones who are-- Ray's the lead animator, so he's in charge of making sure
that everything animated on the project looks good, including the outsourcing team, so we leave that up to him.
Crook: Once we got the--the pro VO, it kinda changed the wolf a lot for me.
It's fine. I mean, I don't think Tim has seen this scene, so...
I hope he's--he's still okay with-- See, I hope he's still okay with that sort of, like...
Gardner: Oh, this?
Crook: The, like, poppy gestures, you know?
Where he, like, comes up and he's like, bum-bum, bump.
I mean, it's-- it's probably okay.
-It's probably okay. Roberts: Yeah, it-- Until--until Tim sees it and says--yeah.
Gardner: If he was--like, if he just drew back slower-- Crook: Right.
Marek: Affirmative. Crook: "Affirmative." Yeah, I think we should just slow it down.
I think he should be more like, "Affirmative." Gardner: All right, cool. Then I'm gonna give 'em
the note to watch out for that.
Crook: And just--just make it less poppy.
The--but he delivers it pretty quickly, so...
We'd better let Tim choose.
And then-then-then-then Elliott can win.
Roberts: Fuckin' Lee.
Schafer: All right. Rice: Cool.
Schafer: Don't show this stuff. Rice: I won't.
Just, it's pretty. That's all you need to know.
Hamilon: Yeah, that this part of the game is pretty?
Um...but yeah, this--I mean...
Yeah, this is cool. This game looks good.
I wanna play more.
When you--are you guys gonna have a demo of this game?
Greg: Also meeting today about a PAX demo, um, and what the scope of that will look like.
Start figuring out a plan for that.
Schafer: Okay. Rice: Should be fun.
Kipnis: I would...I would vote against a public demo for now.
Schafer: What would we have at our booth, then, if we...just do a trailer?
Rice: Nothing. Schafer: What do you mean, nothing?
Rice: It'd mean we have no games at our booth right now.
Schafer: I mean, depends how we show it.
Like, showing adventure games on the--on the-- like, at E3 and stuff was always a nightmare,
'cause, like, you can't get-- it's not like jumping into a mech and shooting a bunch of stuff, or even playing "Brütal Legend."
Like, so, you can't-- it's hard to really kind of-- I mean, now that we have-- that headphones are more common
and stuff, I think it's a little easier to demo them.
But you're still, like-- sitting there for a while being stuck on a puzzle is not something that's fun to do,
and people are lining up behind you to see the game.
Petty: The big problem with this whole thing, potentially, is that we're gonna disrupt all this--
we just spent all this effort getting everything into a flow
that's going to unblock our dependencies.
And so even doing any of this work is probably going to disrupt that somewhat.
It's hard to say how much until we look at that.
But, um, polishing the spaceship to beta right now, uh, I think would be the absolute worst thing,
because we have so much areas of the game that have issues we've gotta work through.
And people like myself and Bagel, some of the animators, need to stay out ahead
or we're gonna get exactly where we were, where everything's blocked up, and part of that happened
because of the last trailer we did.
I mean, obviously, there's an undeniable benefit.
It's hard to quantify the benefit, is always the issue with making these decisions, right?
'Cause, like, well, people get excited and that generates goodwill, but...
Schafer: Like, the two things that I want spoil each other.
Like, showing really meaty gameplay and not spoiling things are, like,
kinda mutually exclusive.
Rice: All right. This is all good stuff.
Schafer: Except you're doing the smile.
You're doing the "I'm really unhappy" smile.
Rice: No, I'm not! I, like-- Schafer: "Yeah, life's shit like I thought.
Yep, that's exactly what I thought life was like." Rice: No, I mean, I've always been about trying to, like,
figure out how we can do it without disrupting.
But, uh, now we just have to figure out what that means for our PAX plans, so...
Schafer: I mean, in the end it's not even about it being disrupting.
I really don't care about disrupting Lee at all.
I mean, it's really-- that does--no.
No, I mean, it's not even about that.
It's like, if we really felt like, oh man, it was such a juicy reward
at the end of it, like, if it was really, like, that demo would really turn people, like,
millions of people into fans of the game, like, I feel like it would be great.
But I feel like showing the spaceship to the press would not necessarily convert
a whole bunch of people, you know, um...
Petty: Well, that's what I meant by disruptive: Is it worth it?
Because like you said in the earlier episodes, no one cares how well a game is produced.
I don't think anyone cares how well a game is promoted if it comes out and it's not good.
Schafer: The one--at least the one discipline here that we can agree no one cares about is production.
Crook: You said both those things. Schafer: I don't remember saying that.
Petty: But, I mean, it's the same thing.
Like, good production/promotion, if it's not-- if we--you know, I want it to be as good as it can be.
Rice: It's just a hard--like, it became a lot more important with all the press shit that went down
'cause, like, now what does it look like, oh, suddenly we're taken off the floor map of PAX
and we pulled out of PAX? Like, that looks bad.
Schafer: That's 'cause I thought someone was gonna throw acid in my face.
You can say that: "Tim was worried about acid." Rice: But, yeah.
Petty: Okay, but then what if we showed a press demo that wasn't totally polished?
Which is worse?
Giving 'em ammo to hate on?
I think that's worse.
Schafer: Honestly, I--if I could do anything right now, it would just be sit out this PAX.
Rice: Yeah, we-- Schafer: I feel like we just don't-- Rice: I think we might have to if we don't do a demo.
Schafer: I don't know if-- can-can we, now?
Rice: We'd probably have to pay for some stuff.
Petty: We could have a kickass merch booth.
Rice: Uh, yeah...we could do that.
[Music] Bagel: Uh, I think it's going good.
It's pretty rad.
I think we've all, like, gotten a lot better at art, you know, over the last year.
So lookin' at all the old stuff is, like, kinda hard, but we all see stuff, I think, that we know we wanna change.
And, um, it's getting to an exciting time right now.
Uh, it's polish phase, you know, just figuring out what we're gonna polish and just lookin' back
at all of our old stuff and bringing it all together into an awesome game, you know?
But, yeah.
I feel like it's goin' pretty good.
Pretty exciting, but it is also super scary that we only have, like, what, four months left.
Right? But, yeah, I'm gonna go-- I'm goin' out to San Francisco on the 16th of September,
and, um, I'm gonna be out there for two weeks, and we are gonna, like, talk about polish,
figure out a plan, and then just start nailing it.
[Music] Schafer: We've got some professional voice in the game now.
You can hear--uh, and it's awesome, 'cause they're good.
Black: Oh, my!
A fresh face rises from below.
Before you ask, let me answer.
Yes, you may live here in Meriloft forever.
Rice: Yeah, it's one of those things that, uh...
changes, uh, the production values of the game in a very short amount of time.
Like, 'cause it kind of all comes in at once, in one big chunk,
and suddenly you go from having very non-professional acting to very professional acting.
And it--and it just, uh...
I think it just reminds you it's real.
Schafer: A huge difference.
It's--it's huge. I mean, we've been looking at these temporary cut scenes for so long where
the characters are all moving-- 'cause they don't wanna put a lot of work into it until they have the final VO.
Now that we have the final VO, they can just go to town.
And so we're gonna see, um, a whole different game experience
where it just feels so much more polished.
Rice: And in a game that's so much about character and story, um, like, it's gonna be really important
that that is sold correctly and those actors are selling it right.
So, you know, Tim's an awesome writer, and now to have, like, people who are able
to take what he wrote and, like, even make it better is pretty amazing.
Schafer: And "Act 1" of our game is now in alpha, which is exciting.
[Offscreen] Woo! And--woo!
But it's lookin' good.
Rice: Cheers.
[Music] Schafer: It's gonna be fun when we can actually, um,
celebrate, you know, shipping.
And--but it'll be kind of sad, 'cause it's been kind of fun to do all this and...
[Music] I'm not gonna celebrate till the whole thing ships.
I suppose we'll have some sort of celebration on shipping "Act 1."
Then I'm like, don't talk to me until it's done.
April/May. April/M-- Definitely between April and November.
Depends on how many the first act sells.
If it sells a lot, we'll just go all the way into 2016.
Just kidding.
[Music] Kaufman: Okay, that's all we can do.
We're pulling out.
Don't make the same mistake you did last time, boy.
I-I don't understand.
What is it about this creature?
Brown: Excellent.
Schafer: Let's throw in for the fans-- edit together the lines to make a big dirty, like,
"Spock and Kirk having sex" video.
I like to put stuff in there for them.
"Pull out now, boy." Brown: I just...
Schafer: "Think about baseball."