Schafer: Oh, Brad is out. Okay.
Hello everybody.
Hi. It's good to see you.
Hello. Thank you for coming.
So, uh, it's Monday, and Friday was terrible.
Uh, all of you were here.
I want to just think everyone for, uh, showing so much class
going through that difficult day.
You guys all, um, uh, held together nicely.
It was a rough day on everybody and, um, I think you showed a lot of compassion
for the people who are leaving and also understanding for those of us who had to make that decision,
and it really helped us get through it.
And we will--we are getting through it, and it's, um...
Now we have a bunch of games we gotta make and stuff to do.
Um, we are still helping the people who need letters of reference,
letters of recommendation, stuff like that.
Help--doing what we can to get them set up with new engagements.
Um, but other than that, we here are still working on these games.
Did you want to talk about the layoffs?
-Is that part of the documentary?
Talk about the layoffs. I'm gonna have a drink.
Can I drink on camera?
If the kids are watchin' this, kids, don't drink.
A week ago, we had a project canceled, an unannounced project from a publisher
that really liked the game.
We had just done our vertical slice and then gave us great feedback on it
and they said it was great and they really liked it.
And then the next call was they're canceling it for higher-up reasons.
Well, that was a big project that was funding a lot of people.
And--and then another one of our publishers from another project is having financial problems
and can't pay us.
Bailey: You know, it's public news now that Majesco is, um...
Pardon me.
Not timed there.
Majesco has made a public statement that
their, you know, continued ability to perform as--as a going concern is at stake and, of course,
we did Costume Quest 2 with them and the payments were not complete for that.
So we're actually-- we're owed money by Majesco that we're not getting paid.
And then, of course Costume Quest 2, um, because of that statement, you can infer
that it's not being marketed properly and it's not being distributed to its fullest extent
that you would expect from a publisher, because there-- you know, the means and the people there to do that
just don't exist anymore.
Um, so it's kind of a perfect storm.
It was a bad week to put it mildly.
So, glad that week's over.
If that publisher hadn't canceled it, you know, things would have been--
were looking really good for the studio.
Um, I think things are still looking really good for the studio,
but only because we took quick action.
Schafer: So we had to let go of 12 people.
Some of them, uh, had been here for a short period of time and some of them had been here for a long period of time,
over ten years.
So that was really hard.
Stoddard: What do you want to know, how I feel about them and-- Off camera: Yeah, yeah, how was it? I mean you--
Stoddard: It was horrible. -Yeah.
It was really horrible. Um...
I mean, I understand why it happened, but, like, we--the audio team was super tight, uh,
and now there's two of us instead of four.
Um, it was a heavy hit.
The day of the layoffs were just brutal.
Kipnis: Uh, well, I will say that the layoffs-- I wasn't actually at the office when it happened, so...
And, um, at first, like, I--I got-- I got text messages about it
and it was, uh...
it was really tough to--to hear about it, um, and it--it was tough to, like, not be here to say goodbye
to some of those people that I've worked with for years and years
and, like, you know, I'm gonna miss a lot.
I don't know what else to say.
Crook: And you always feel a little bit guilty when you're still here, you know, and other people aren't,
um, and it hurts morale quite a bit, um, but...
but I know that it--I know that it was not taken lightly.
Hansen: It was the hardest day of my life.
I never thought we would be in that situation, but project cancelations happen and, you know,
sometimes you can absorb it and sometimes you can't.
So Tim and I almost avoided each other just 'cause we knew that we had to meet and talk about that.
And I didn't want to, and he didn't want to either.
There was no, like, oh, yeah, it's so easy, it's person X, Y, and Z.
It's like every single one of those people are-- they're huge contributors to all these games we've made.
They're the people we hang out with after work and so-- And, you know, and it's tough for Double Fine in general,
because historically, I mean, we even said this in the media in the past,
we don't do layoffs and that sort of thing.
It was--it was a tough decision for sure.
Russell: A lot of us just stayed afterwards in the room, after we were told, and just talked about
the history of the company, and just, we were like, we couldn't believe this happened to us,
but you know, in the game industry and in any entertainment industry,
it's--it's the norm.
We're the exception, so in that respect I-- I--I feel lucky,
and we'll survive, a little bit smaller, a little leaner, but we'll make it.
[Music] Schafer: So basically we are powering forward on our, um,
uh, remaining titles that we're working on.
Those are the stories I really wanted to make the documentary about
but we could never do that, like, those publisher games,
to see, like, what it's like, all those meetings where they're saying,
"This game is so great, we can't wait to see it." And then the meeting where they actually said it's canceled,
we have to cancel it, but I hope you still make it 'cause I really want to play it.
That was an actual quote from the guy, he was like, "If you make it
I really want to play it." It's like, "Oh, thanks, that makes up
for me laying off 12 people.
That--I totally feel good now that you want to play this game
that you just killed." But, um, since I'm mostly fueled by angriness and bitterness,
then I'm stronger than ever right now.
You know, whatever works.
[Music] [Chatter]
Schafer: Oh god, is that thing still here? Mitchell: It's way funnier now.
Muir: It was just sad. Mitchell: Yeah.
Muir: It wasn't bad. Mitchell: No.
Schafer: That one that you found under the sink?
Muir: It's really good. It's like, uh...
Mitchell: It's gooey, though.
Muir: Chipotle.
Schafer: Is everyone here?
[Murmuring] Hello, everybody! Hello.
And thank you for coming back to work here again for another year.
It's awesome to see you all here.
Welcome back.
Nice to see you all.
Rice: Yeah, man.
2015.
Schafer: 2015. Wait a second.
Does that mean we didn't finish in December?
Rice: Yeah.
Comin' on three years.
Schafer: Three--no kidding? It's like Rip Van Winkle.
All I remember is the Kickstarter, and then I woke up and it's three years later.
Crook: And we all have big, long--and we all have big, long beards.
Schafer: Yeah, we're just here with beards.
Ray, where did all that money go, what?
I guess we should ship this game.
But the game was awesome.
Um, but, um, but we-- I think I'm trying to this week still keep play testing,
especially the problem areas in the game where people get hung up the most
and catch any remaining dialogue.
There's probably some object interactions or examine lines that are still missing that I would love to catch.
Please keep talking and don't be freaked out that we're not answering you, 'cause we'd just like
to hear what you're thinking.
Miller: All right.
I'm already baffled.
Vella: Is this one?
Miller: This must be incredibly fun to watch.
Schafer: We're not even here.
Miller: What's that? You're not paying attention?
Schafer: Yeah, I'm doing my taxes over here.
Miller: I think I'll switch to Shay 'cause I can't figure this out.
Schafer: I mean, it's--it--that-- the first puzzle, it's, like, one of the first puzzles that Vella has,
and you have to do something and get this visual feedback, and you have to mess with it a lot and get some more feedback
to kind of figure out the patterns.
Um, and then it's just a problem of, like, have we kind of inceptioned? Is that a verb?
Put the idea in the player's head of what they want to do enough.
'Cause sometimes you just mess with the game and you just kind of bang on it
and you--woo, you solved it, you don't really know how you solved it.
And that to me is almost a worst-case scenario.
That's almost worse than getting stuck forever, you know?
Like, getting-- 'cause being stuck forever, if you finally solve it you feel great.
But if you solve it in accident, you're like, I don't know what just happened, you move on
and you kind of get this kind of bored feeling.
And it's really easy to just accidently put this one line in
that makes everybody just know what to do immediately.
So it's--it's like a lot of-- 'cause time--time is short and we don't have much-- we don't have much time left,
and to solve these problems, to make sure that everyone gets through the game,
it's really tempting to just kind of, like, short circuit all the puzzles and make sure
that everybody can get through them.
But you have to kind of take a lot of time to actually really look, um, carefully at, like,
each mental leap the player is making.
[Off camera] If people were saying the first one was too easy and you're taking out a lot of the hints,
I mean, are you afraid you went too far in the other direction?
-It seems like there's a lot-- Schafer: Well, I'm hoping-- I'm hoping we went way too far.
Rice: But yeah, like Tim said, in general I think we're gonna keep play testing
in hopes that anything that we find that is a problem
down the road could be changed.
Crook: Are we gonna have-- with--with Ben leaving, are we having any other-- another GP coming on
or are we gonna be able to just absorb?
Peck: Um, well, it's my second to last day here at Double Fine.
And, uh, just trying to, like, put a bow on as many things as I could before leaving.
The place I'm going to is quite a bit-- it's like a larger company so...
I'm--yeah, I'm gonna miss the...
like, the small little scenes at the lunch table or, like, company meetings and stuff like that
where, like, it's okay to make a dick joke or, like, it's okay to...
to just kind of be yourself a bit.
Um...
I'm hoping I can kind of take a little bit of that for-- like, with me wherever I go, you know?
I feel bad I'm not gonna be there for, like, when the shit inevitably hits the fan, you know,
and the game needs to be finaled.
Kipnis: That jerk.
No, I mean, it sucks.
It sucks. I mean, Ben--Ben contributed a lot to the--to the game and, you know, we're--
we're having to kind of figure out some stuff in the code that he wrote when he could have been here to help us out.
I mean, it sucks, but, um, we'll just have to finish without him, you know?
Crook: I mean, I will say, you know, we've had to transition because, um, Lee left the project
and, um, that was-- that was scary, um, because he--he seemed to know
what was going on with everything.
And so I think Anna's had to take on a lot of some of the responsibilities that Lee had, um,
as far as puzzle chains and--and how those are all put together
and--and the logic.
Um, so I'm sure that's been stressful for her.
[Offscreen] Do you regret not getting to see Broken Age through to the end?
Petty: Yeah, you know, I'm trying to think.
I think this is the only time I haven't stayed on a project
all the way through.
It was a lot of those, um, small decisions right at the end of the project
that have a big impact on the game 'cause all the content's there
and it's all connected.
And sometimes just pushing and pulling a few things
can--it, um, can really help the game, and it's nice to be part of that.
But, uh, I don't think I'll be part of that for Act 2 anyways, but--
I think I'm--I'm excited for Act 2 to come out, because I think Act 1 had a lot of great things about it
but it was incomplete, and, you know, you can sort of see the whole arc or play the whole game,
might get a better sense of whether that was successful or not.
But hopefully I've helped set that up, um, to be a--to be a great experience.
Schafer: But we don't need anybody.
Broken Age team.
We don't-- we don't need nobody.
We'll finish it ourselves.
So where are we supposed to be right now, Alpha on the finale?
Rice: Yeah. You wanna look at the...
Schafer: When is beta on B2 and G2? Is that there?
Rice: Yeah, so we'll show you the timeline as it is right now.
Um, but Matt and Vic and I, and Malena are gonna meet this afternoon now, uh,
and want to get a lot more clarity into just closing out the project,
but also, like, these beta sprints and--and things like that as well.
Hansen: Right now there's a tendency for people to gravitate towards whatever is the, you know,
maybe the most interesting work, and that's not-- might not be the most, uh, highest priority work.
We just need to do some load balancing and some estimates as far as, like, how long is it gonna take
to get this shit done, 'cause people-- if people don't tell us that,
we might be fucked already and we don't even know it.
Rice: Um, but, yes, Ray, you're correct.
The, um, the right reaction to this is, it's a lot to do in two-- in two months and change.
Crook: Yeah. Rice: So, um, I think that's why we wanted to make sure that these dates
get in front of everybody's eyes and that people are looking at it differently.
Hansen: Is it reasonable? I mean, or are you-- or you're like, I don't know, man,
'cause your gut checks are usually pretty good.
Crook: Wow.
Yeah, but I think it's-- I think it'd be all right.
Do you think the GPs are gonna be--I mean, 'cause there was a time where
there were gonna be four of them.
Now there's two of them.
Rice: We're getting all the box stuff ready to go and actually manufacturing in, like, February, um,
to where discs would be pressed in mid-March.
Kipnis: Yeah, and the game--does the game run on the PS4?
Franzke: Nope. Kipnis: Yeah.
And--and I think it's really important to have a, "Okay, Tim, this is it, like, you can't..."
Hansen: Yeah. Kipnis: Like, absolute content complete from, like, Tim content complete maybe.
Hansen: Last call for alcohol.
Kipnis: Yeah, last call.
Let's just call it that, last call.
It's really hard to, as a creator, to turn yourself off.
What I want to do is be able to account for that and I want Tim to be able to do that.
I want him to be able to, like, "Oh, God, this is it, that's right,
I can't add anymore after this." And I want him to be able to, like, have that time
and account for it in our--in our milestone, like, timeline and stuff.
Because I want him to be, like, happy with what we come up with.
Because we know his creative process, it's important for us to schedule it appropriately.
Rice: Yeah, um... Kipnis: Yeah, I didn't realize, like, how soon the beta was.
Jesus Christ. Rice: Yeah, and I don't know, Matt, like, right now every-- there's a lot of hands on Grim,
but, like, obviously that's just a near-term problem that's being solved soon.
But after that, um, yeah, I don't know what kind of, uh, strings
we can pull with people on other teams, um, as needed.
Hansen: They can't. I mean, we have milestones. We won't get paid.
If we don't get paid then the studio shuts down.
Rice: That's what I thought.
So I was just making sure that that was the case.
Hansen: I'm just gonna be totally blunt with you guys, but you can't touch (redacted).
Kipnis: Yeah. Hansen: I'm sorry.
Franzke: Yeah.
All right. Rice: Cool.
Franzke: Let's make this happen, huh?
Rice: Yeah. All right.
Like, you guys are the right people to ask about this.
Like what--what does gut say about the timeline?
It's basically two months till pencils down.
Inversin: I'm not totally scared just yet, but I might be terrified.
We'll see.
[Offscreen] Did you get to learn anything from Lydia when she was still here?
Panya: No.
She had a lot of the Act 1 shader stuff, so, like, her signature's over everything
so I can pick up where she left off in that sense.
Uh, but she's not here for me to kind of ask questions.
Scheduling with effects is always kind of scary, 'cause there's always this, you know,
four-week window at the end for polish, and, of course everybody wants to polish at the end,
even design wants to polish, and that trickles down.
Animations get tweaked at the end, and then visual effects and sound effects
are the last two guys to kind of get, uh, to touch it.
So as long as everyone knows that the sound effects and the visual effects guys are last and they give some buffer,
then we shouldn't be too, uh, too screwed.
Stoddard: I want to make sure German gets hit because we have to re-volume graph
and re-special effects process all of the German recording for Act 1 and Act 2, and that's a tall order.
Rice: Yeah, and it's getting delivered beginning of February, right, and then don't we--is the plan to have outsourcer on it
that should take, like, three weeks?
Stoddard: We--yeah. Hansen: We have Ashley coming in.
Stoddard: Yeah. Hansen: And she'll be, uh, helping...
-...specifically for this work. Rice: Yeah.
Schafer: I would like to ask you to join me in welcoming Ashley Coull to Double Fine.
There she is over there.
Ashley.
Coull: You know, a contract. It's a short amount of time and, you know, there-- there's no--there's no guarantee,
and it was a staggering amount of work as well, but, uh, the opportunity to be here
and be a part of this community, uh, Camden even pulled me out-- pulled me out of work one day,
and I think he got about halfway through the sentence of, "Hey, so there's this contract thing," and I was like, "Yes."
And he was like, "I--uh, yeah," and I was like, "Yeah." Um, and that's kind of how--how
the balls got--got rolling, I guess.
Schafer: Because we have German VO in the game, which is awesome, and it sounds crazy. I started playing it.
I mean, I don't mean crazy, I mean in a language that is not my own.
-German Vella: Hallo? Schafer: There we go.
[Coughing] That's a German cough, obviously.
[Disproving sigh] [Laughter]
I really like the German version. I'm gonna play through the whole thing in German.
Stoddard: Yeah, that was-- that was a-- the was a big, big thing,
so she's just-- she's kicking ass, Paul is kicking ass.
He really is stepping up.
I mean, it's like kind of both their moments to step up.
O'Rourke: I mean, it's always enjoyable. Tim's writing is hilarious most of the time
and it's really good to just-- like, usually when I'm editing--
I don't want to talk bad about, like, sports games or anything,
but if I had to edit, like, Madden dialogue all day,
probably kill myself.
But going through Tim's stuff is actually pretty enjoyable.
Um, I gave him a huge cut scene the other day.
Dude, here's a big moment, go do it,
come back when it's done.
And he came back and it was damn near perfect.
Like he nailed it, so I'm like, okay, I'm not worried anymore.
The layoffs were not good, um...
It's definitely-- This--this company is under stress.
Everybody is being super pro and they're making good product, but, like, it's-- it's heavy duty right now.
And I'm just really happy to see this team kind of gel, uh, you know, in the trenches and really get it.
Me?
(speaking in German) [Offscreen] What was that? Franzke: I--what?
[Laughter] Coull: Uh, I said I'm editing all the German lines.
Franzke: Can I read-- can I read this?
[Laughter] Franzke: Oh.
Rice: We've gone through this now with all the leads, yeah,
but, um, yeah, now we wanted to present it it to you.
The next week is-- Schafer: Last set call.
Rice: Huh? Schafer: Tim last call...
Rice: Yeah, we'll get to that.
So like, tomorrow the hope is during stand-ups to, like, relay this whole thing to the entire team,
not just the leads.
And I feel like we gotta kinda give, like,
a bit of a sense of urgency and just, like, that kind of thing.
But I feel like it's also trying to put people's fears to rest, which would--I think one of the big ones is that,
like, we're gonna continue to iterate on the game...
-...and things like that. Schafer: So terrify them with the deadlines and put all their fears to rest.
Rice: And then hopefully, uh, just pep rally, pump people up?
Schafer: If we use the words "dig deep" at any point, I'm just-- Hansen: Will you say it? Schafer: No.
Rice: No. Schafer: There's always a point where someone talks about digging deep,
and I just-- I don't want to say that.
So we all gotta dig deep, you guys.
Hansen: All right. Rice: Yeah, I pro-- I think I might put the dates
on the whiteboard again, too, just so everyone can look at them all the time.
Schafer: If they view that, they'll film it.
Rice: Yeah, red, white, and blue.
Romero: That's encouraging.
Broken Age, fuck yeah.
Schafer: Does that help?
Romero: Tim last call. Is that a milestone?
Rice: Fuck yes. Romero: Okay.
We submit to ratings boards on the fourth?
Rice: Yeah, I think it's that-- Kipnis: When do we know what line...?
Crook: Tim said he would try to call him. When he said you're hitting the line, it's okay.
Maybe I just gotta try to find one that...
Rice: Ready? So we've been meeting production team with the leads
to come up with closing plan stuff.
So next Friday we have our next Sony milestone, which Oliver is working on.
I think the big thing is PlayStation 4 running.
Schafer: Is there anything on there new or shocking to anyone?
Crook: It's all shocking, but nothing's new.
There's nothing new.
Schafer: There is a lot of stuff to do in a short amount of time,
but there's no big unknowns to me, at least, on it.
There's no design yet to do, dialogue yet to write, and big ques--
things that could explode into-- I mean, like, it seems like it's a known amount of work now
that can't expand, and, um, and it's clear that it can't slip
because you can see the commitments that are on it.
As far as I'm concerned, like, everything is just no-- everything just has to be pushed through the machinery,
and that's the easy part, except for it's hard.
No, we're--we're the dream team, all here together.
For some reason, to me it's always relaxing when it's finite even if it is tight
because you know when it's gonna be over.
These next three weeks are really where the game goes from being good to great mostly.
So, um, it's gonna be exciting and, uh, if we have to order food,
we'll order food.
Crook: Food.
Boston Market?
Schafer: No. Crook: Promise Boston Market, I'll-- Schafer: Wait, you want Boston-- Crook: I'll work late if you--
No, I'm just kidding. Kipnis: Wow.
Crook: Just kidding.
Schafer: If you've gotta lure a man away from his family, make it Boston Market.
Crook: Yeah.
Schafer: It's like there's love in that meal.
Kipnis: That's--that's what Caroline did for us during Psychonauts.
Remember that? Rice: Boston Market?
Kipnis: Boston Market, like, every night.
Crook: Yep. Kipnis: And, uh, and I gained-- I gained, like, 15 pounds during during crunch.
Schafer: That's to keep you in your seat.
[Music] Schafer: Uh, on "Reds," we did a whole play-through of the team
of the finale of the game to figure out how to push that towards, um, completion.
We are also starting on the PS4 version.
Hansen: So we have a milestone on the 23rd, and that's to have it, like,
"playable," um, on that platform, so-- But it looks like that's come along really well,
so good job, Oliver.
Schafer: Look at it playing on the PS4.
[Offscreen] How's the port process been going in general?
Franzke: It's good. We essentially added PlayStation 4 and PlayStation Vita
to a list of platforms, but kept the ship date the same,
um, so that makes things a bit more interesting.
I love working on consoles, but it's a very different kind of challenge, like,
for example, the Vita is very memory constrained, um, so that, you know,
it's--it's a very tight memory budget for--for the game, and if you're just leaking some memory somewhere,
like, you're gonna have a bad time later on, so there are, like, a lot of really interesting things
you need to take into consideration.
Or can you compress the data in some way and stuff like that.
And I think the end-- the end will be tough, for sure, shipping.
Like, so, for--for consoles, um, what you have to do in order to release games
is you have to go to something that's called certifications.
The next milestone is on the 20th, which is-- like, it's very ominously called, like, beta
which is supposed to be TRC complete, uh, essentially for Sony
so there's a lot of stuff that needs to happen before that.
Those are all the requirements you need for shipping a game on a--on a Sony platform.
Schafer: I'm sure we're TRC complete.
Franzke: Oh, yeah, no problem.
Um, so they will essentially, like, run a game and make sure that every one of those requirements is met.
[Offscreen] How does stuff like Assassin's Creed happen?
Oliver: Uh, I'd rather not comment on that.
It's really sad, because I'm pretty sure all the people who worked on the game, you know,
didn't want to release something that's substandard.
Um, so very often, it's--it's-- actually really sad for the developers,
but there's a lot of, like, pressure from various departments
to make the game happen essentially.
Are you feeling some form of pressure like that now?
Well, I mean, but if you-- if you don't have a publisher who's, like, does what, uh, needs to happen,
but as you can see, everything is so tightly packed, uh, that there's really no time to slip any of those milestones.
Franzke: Yes, please. -Okay.
See, crunch has already started.
Schafer: Yeah, we're getting near the end where some nights people are working late
and we're ordering food, and, um...
and hopefully that won't be too long till it's over.
And people who are staying late now, it's 'cause they want to make sure the game is really good.
[Music] I know the biggest hurdle is just the amount
of work there is to do.
Uh, we have to do a whole bunch of cut scenes.
Still have to go in.
Crook: Camden there was the issue with, uh, Bob Chothra coming out of the mountain
that we were gonna-- did you talk to Tim about that and Peter?
I don't know about-- I'm in that scene still.
We're making some changes, so I just-- Stoddard: Okay.
Schafer: Just saying that gave Ray a headache.
Offscreen: How is the ending cut scene coming along, since that was sort of, uh-- that had to be--
the music had to be done, so that was kind of locked.
Schafer: Yeah, yeah, 'cause we kind of locked it, but I feel good about the pacing of that, just based on the music.
Um, and it was so big we had to split it between two animators, Miyuki and Chris Lam.
So Miyuki was doing the first half and Chris was doing the second half.
And then we're gonna stitch it back together.
Oh, I like that. That's a good idea.
Crook: Yeah, that was really good.
That's cute.
Richardson: Like, uh, so many characters, and...
and it's kind of a big thing, right?
It's ending, end of the game, so that's kind of exciting, but still goin' like,
"Ooh, that's a lot of things to do." Crook: Maybe not the happy eyes? Lam: No.
Schafer: Yeah, like, the delirious eyes, like yay, he's more like...
Hm.
"You run, I got this." Crook: All right. Schafer: "Save yourself."
Thumb's up.
Crook: Yeah, he got that on film. We might need to...
Schafer: This ping pong ball, his face.
Lam: The parts that I have to do that are kind of those, you know, resolution moments,
they're gonna be a little challenging but-- to get the expressions on the characters right
so that you know that they're thinking, they're not just staring into dead space and stuff like that.
Crook: Think you got enough info there?
Okay. Lam: Yes.
Crook: The plan is to just take it to that, um, shippable stage.
And then, uh, that will allow all the effects and the sound to get put in, um, 'cause all the timing will be locked down.
So the--the plan is that they'll go back to it, uh, to do some polish, um,
after we get all the content in.
Schafer: Is this a good time to look at it?
It would be a good time to look at it, yes.
It doesn't--sometimes it seems like in that whole thing, there's not a shot that shows--
that really shows the entire scene.
Schafer: But, I mean, you know what's left and you know what's right.
Crook: Yeah, like, this is the only shot we have.
Rice: That's the shot that shows most-- Crook: What--uh, I don't know.
I just kept thinking that, like-- You could almost do-- Rice: if it's a flip book,
you could almost--you could have other people that we don't know
that are on the sides from both villages.
Crook: All these people, like here.
Schafer: But where do they come from? Crook: Well, they came from...
Rice: From the monster lands town, like, there's a big battle going on.
They've come to gawk.
Crook: That's fine. I mean, if you're-- But we--but we can't-- we don't want...
-...to animate more people. Stoddard: Yeah, yeah, I know.
Rice: But that's what you're saying. Schafer: It's really important not to add features to the game
at this point Ray.
I like the melting you're adding.
I wouldn't jump to that melting platform.
Crook: Yeah, that's true. She has no shoes.
Camden: She's tough. She's a baker.
Crook: She walks on coals. Schafer: She doesn't use oven mitts anymore.
Oh, that's good. That's perfect.
So I think this would be-- this needs something here.
Inversin: It--it has something, not in this scene, but there is-- I can--I can move it into that scene also if you want.
Schafer: 'Cause it seemed like he was backing up from nothing.
Inversin: So, like, it's in there, too, so I can add it to the other one.
Schafer: I just think it--think it could be, like, half as much?
Crook: That looks really cool.
Schafer: It kind of explains why he jumps now.
That's perfect. I think that's perfect as far as the rain goes.
-Awesome. -Yeah.
-Then we're done. -Yeah.
That was easy.
Boop boop. Yeah, that was really good.
Thanks.
Oh, crying for us.
Crook: Yeah.
[Music] Rice: But we're finally now getting down to-- to final days, I guess.
[Music] Crook: But, yeah, we're all a little on edge, a little stressed out,
but, um, it'll be okay.
Hansen: Anna's here almost constantly, and, you know, I can-- I see the light at the end of the tunnel.
We love these games, but, you know, we all kind of need to take a break.
And people need to get some sleep, too.
It's been a rough few months.
Crook: I mean, we're gonna be pushing to the very end.
[Off screen] Like that guy there. Crook: Oh yeah he is.
I think he didn't go home last night.
But apparently he has, like, a little bed over there.
So I'm just like, that's not a good thing.
Stoddard: I don't want to romanticize it.
I know--I know that Tim wants to show how the sausage gets made,
and this has been-- this has been hard.
Schafer: We're also getting kind of griefed by, um, certain fringe organizations
and attack groups organized, and, uh, that was a bummer.
And then we had the layoffs which were a huge bummer.
And, um, a bunch of bad news.
Rice: There is, like, a group of people that are hoping that we won't succeed for some weird reason,
um, or that are at least heavily scrutinizing us.
And it definitely has been something that's been weighing on a lot of people.
Franzke: The endless thing of, like, people, like, oh, well, maybe they shouldn't have taken the--the money
and only make half the game. Well, you know, all I can say to that is, like,
if you would be, like, we're sitting here, you know, working our asses off to make this game.
Kipnis: And, like, you do, you question yourself.
Like, yeah, maybe we-- what the fuck, maybe we don't know what the--what we're doing.
Who knows?
But you just have to trust and know, like, this is actually-- game development
is not an easy thing.
Schafer: And now we're gonna ship Broken Age, and that's all gonna be great.
So, um, it's a relief to get out of that-- out of that period.
[Offscreen] What's going on right now at this stage of the project?
Romero: So where we are is, we're less than a month out from our first submission,
which is the, um, where you submit to Sony and we release the mastering for the PC,
physical copies that we're doing with Nordic.
So the 20th is the big day where just everything has to sort of be done by that point.
Rice: Uh, yes, I've been working on some Nordic stuff, too, along with Vic. Um... We got the box prints
from them and they just look a little bit dark so we're doing, like, another round on those
before they actually start printing them in bulk.
Uh, but hopefully that'll happen soon.
Schafer: But we don't get a sample before they make a zillion of them?
Rice: No, unfortunately. Schafer: Exciting.
Rice: Yeah. Schafer: That's exciting.
This is just one of Cory's mock-ups of the box.
This is the box.
This is--the disc's not gonna look like that.
I wanted the disc to be the O from Broken Age.
This is gonna be like the O, and that's the box.
And we're first looking at it, we're like, this is cool 'cause it shows the split thing,
but it really overemphasizes Vella over Shay, 'cause Shay's upside down so he's, like, easier to ignore.
It was like, wouldn't it be crazy if we could print Vella and Shay
on a separate clear slipcover, and then you could slide it off
and turn it around and slide it back down and then Shay would be in Vella's world and vice versa,
Which, no spoilers, but that's some foreshadowing there.
And it would be so neat.
It would be like Led Zeppelin.
Rice: We'll nail it. It'll be great.
-Um... Kipnis: Wow.
Romero: So right now the big tasks are-- or the big areas are bugs.
O'Rourke: Yeah, we're in Starship Troopers mode basically, just killing all the bugs.
Schafer: Taking showers together or what are you-- Coull: No. Schafer: I'm sorry, that's...
not the first thing I think about.
O'Rouke: There's the daily shower scene in the audio room.
Kipnis: I'm a little bit concerned about our deadline.
Like, right here it says A and B bugs only.
Like, that's not likely gonna happen, especially since we have brand new cut scenes.
Schafer: Starting now or next week?
Kipnis: Next week.
Uh, that's likely not happening because we have a bunch of new, um, cut scenes coming.
Content is still coming in and we can't actually do that until all content is in the game.
Schafer: What's this selective bug fixing?
Almost sounds more open-ended than A and B 'cause we select to do a C.
Right, that's how that works?
Kipnis: Nope. Rice: I don't think so.
Kipnis: But if you play the game all the way through, um, from Act 1,
that Act 1 is very clean, and we have to make Act 2 look that clean,
and that's a lot of C-bug fixing.
And so, like, we can't suddenly switch to A and Bs only next week.
Like, it's just not-- it's gonna be basically like a, I don't know,
not a very clean game, I guess.
Romero: Uh, Act 2 is interesting because we're not just doing PC, Mac, and Linux digital,
um, we're doing physical, when--and really that goes back to the old school way,
which is you get to the point in the project where you're gonna ship a physical disc,
you have to cut off bug fixing.
You have to be certain that the build you're shipping is the one,
because someone's gonna, in theory, buy the box and get the game,
and that has to have all the, you know, be bug-free as-- as bug-free as possible and as solid as possible,
so they'll just have the disc and the game that's on there.
That's it.
Kipnis: I don't have confidence at the moment that we have--we're really
at the bug count that we are.
Or, like, I--I expect that the bugs will increase tremendously,
or should, because I think they are in there.
Romero: They're still there. Kipnis: Yeah.
Franzke: It's still gonna be good, like, I mean, this game has been out for such a long time, I think
it's gonna be stable and it's gonna be good, but there's always, like,
so much more that we would have liked to do and, like, we're now at a point where
that's just not gonna be possible.
We need to, you know, make sure that the game is stable.
You know, you look-- you look at your bug database and you list some issues that you have in there
and it's, like, a lot, and it's like, how are we gonna be able to--to finish that?
We'll have to probably do some bug triaging next week to just see kind of, okay, well, all of these issues
that are in the bug database right now, which one are we realistically gonna be able to even do now?
And then they have to-- there will have to be some hard decisions.
It's like, okay, well, we can only do one or the other, so which one of these issues,
polish items is more important to you?
And then we're gonna do that but not the other.
And it's just the nature of the beast.
[Music] Hansen: Resources in 12. Schafer: That would be great.
Uh, and yeah, we'll have to re-- and I mean, obviously,
analyze the bugs every day and how they're tracking.
Are all the GPs back from sickness?
Hansen: No, Anna's still out. Stoddard: Two down.
Hansen: But-- Schafer: She's gonna be out today, too?
Hansen: She's trying to get some medicine that'll allow her to work this week,
so she's that bad.
Schafer: Holy cow.
Crook: She was working really late hours.
I think she was probably-- Her immune system was already
pretty vulnerable, and, um, and she--she got whatever, I don't know.
I hope--I don't know, she hasn't said.
She went to the doctor.
Hopefully it's not pneumonia or something, but, um,
hopefully she'll be back with us on Monday.
But--but we know that the most important thing for her is just to get better.
You know, it's just a video game.
You know, she's, you know, her health is the most important thing,
so, um, so that's why it's been great.
Everyone has just jumped in to try and help out, and nobody blames anybody for anything.
-It's just one of those things. Boehle: I'll probably just filter, like, Anna's open or new bugs, like, priority two and higher,
and then if there's anything UI related, I'll just grab those and--
Franzke: Right. Yeah, I think we have to.
I mean, it's just kind of-- sounds like Anna's hit pretty hard.
Hansen: But it's still difficult because, you know, there's a lot of ownership over the code,
so Anna will be able to get something done a lot faster than anybody else just 'cause she's so familiar
with all the inner workings of how this stuff is all hooked up.
That makes it more difficult, for sure, 'cause all the pressure's on her right now.
Rice: I guess at least through the week and then, I just--I guess I wonder when we're gonna get
to other platform work, but for now it's obvious.
It seems like this is until we're locking stuff down.
Franzke: I mean, like, whenever there's an actual pre-cert issue coming in from Sony,
I'm jumping on it right away because I want to get them,
like, fixed as soon as possible.
But so far it's been pretty good.
I think actually not that many bugs been reported from pre-certs.
Rice: So, yeah, whathaveibeenworkingon? We have a couple things.
Today we set up a bug triage meeting with all of the leads.
So, um, producers and leads and Tim, are gonna kind of read through everything in the bug database,
reevaluating where we are with that.
So that'll be happening this afternoon.
Schafer: Hey, everybody, hello. Rice: Hi.
Schafer: This is probably the last meeting of the project, right?
Rice: Um... Probably not.
Schafer: We're so close. Rice: Big one, though.
Rice: It's a big one. Franzke: Apart from the meeting where we get all the royalty checks?
Schafer: Yeah, that's after. That's after.
We have to ship it first, Oliver.
But yeah, so we're gonna look over the bug database and see if we can get rid of some bugs.
Rice: I think the hope is really just trying to get an idea of which ones we definitely need to fix
and which ones might be okay to drop.
And this is specifically for the date in two weeks from now, which is like pressing it to the disc for PC.
So I guess it's, like, what are we gonna not feel comfortable having fixed before that disc is pressed.
And how bad is the situation right now?
'Cause I'm hearing things like the bugs aren't gonna be fixed
by the ship date and all that.
I mean, from Vic's last email, it sounds like we're tracking about half the speed
um, that we would need to be for fixing these 250.
Um, I guess it's just, like, what's the line we can draw where we're comfortable that it's a solid build
that's not gonna crash that gives a good experience.
And, yeah, maybe there's, like, some polish stuff that would have been nice to be in there
but at least it's in versions that get patched.
Hansen: I mean, every game that ships ships with bugs, period.
They're--I mean, it's just unavoidable.
You can keep testing a game forever.
It's just you have to get to the point where you feel like
you found things that are-- you know, that most people are likely to run into
and you've addressed all that stuff.
Rice: Then, like, there's certain cut scenes when you interact with things
in the spinning mode where she'll then just not be spinning
all of a sudden and talking, then it'll go back into
spinning, like-- Schafer: I haven't seen that. Rice: You haven't seen that?
Schafer: Okay, we should find those. Rice: I just saw it, like, last night, so...
Crook: Oh, okay.
Schafer: What stretching arms show?
Crook: When, the wakeup scene? Schafer: Mm-hm.
Crook: The arm--It happens twice, when it grabs him and then you can see at the very top,
you can see, like, the arms are all wacky.
Like they're all stretched out and weird.
Schafer: Is it really ugly? Romero: Is that...?
Rice: I think I've seen it. It's like the top point is off the side and then where they come in.
Schafer: If you were a player, would you say that's the science fiction, uh...
Crook: It's a sliver of, like, pulled out stuff.
Franzke: It is a potentially really risky fix, though, because touching-- Getting that camera to work right in that scene
was--we spent weeks-- Schafer: It's not just reposing the hand?
Franzke: Right. And I really would not feel comfortable messing with the cameras unless we really have to because...
Schafer: Would you fix it with the camera or fix it with the animation?
Crook: We can try and change up the animation-- Schafer: But you can't just straighten up the arm.
Crook: That's a scary scene. Schafer: Hm.
Crook: We are trying to take things that maybe-- small things that we normally might ask
the game play programmers to do, uh, we're trying to fix those things ourselves
just because they're so swamped.
But we're not programmers and we have to be careful.
We don't want to break things.
So I'm kind of learning a lot of things.
Um, I'm learning a few things about game play programming.
Schafer: What if Ben Peck is super miserable at his new job? Has anyone called him lately?
Crook: I saw--I saw him at GDC. He looked a little miserable.
Schafer: Yeah, see what I'm saying? Crook: That was only 'cause Anna was giving him mean looks.
Franzke: I saw him on Friday and he seemed relatively happy.
Schafer: Wait, can we see how many of these we have to go through?
Romero: Uh, so we're at 155.
The bottom goes all the way to 252.
So we're about a hundred away.
Schafer: Oh, my God.
Hansen: We don't have a lot of time in general, so yeah, in aggregate, all that stuff is a lot of work.
'Cause what we're trying to do is, like, get to a point where we've addressed everything we're gonna address
and then have the game sit without anybody working on it.
Just--it's just sitting just in QA for, like, a week.
And that's the hard part 'cause we-- we've already eaten into that week.
And so we're kind of faced with the decision now of, like, do we just work up to the deadline
and just ship what we have?
And there's a huge risk involved with that.
But even, like, the small, minor polish bugs, it's like, you get enough of those
and it does make a huge impact on the quality of the game.
Schafer: Yeah, it looks really bad.
Um, when we print this disc, how would people get the patch?
Franzke: Steam.
Schafer: So that's the only way to get the patch for their disc-based version
of the game is by using Steam?
Franzke: Yeah. Schafer: They can't download it from our website or anything like that?
Franzke: Our infrastructure--like, we would require to have
some kind of login service for people to register accounts.
Schafer: That could be a huge consumer thing of them saying I need to--
in order to get the patch, I need to join Steam, and I don't want to join Steam.
I bought this disc. Franzke: Yeah.
Schafer: So it's not like in the old days, where a patch was just a bunch of LUA files
that you could just unpack into the directory of your game and it would fix it?
Franzke: We could, but we have no infrastructure for that right now.
Schafer: On the server side or in the game?
In the game would have to have that kind of-- Franzke: We right now have no software to create an incremental patch.
Schafer: People are gonna freak out.
Rice: Yeah, well, we don't want to have to support a whole 'nother platform.
And, like, it would mean, like, building ground up an infrastructure
for them to be able to sign in to something.
For us to be able to host something, for us to support a whole 'nother platform.
Schafer: Well, I just think the other stuff is-- like, just 'cause it's hard for us doesn't mean
we're not gonna have to deal with it as a company.
You know what I mean? Like, as a huge community or PR problem.
Rice: This was a red flag waved as soon as we said we were gonna do a box copy.
Franzke: Right, I mean, that's one of the first things we talked about is how the patching would work.
Rice: Yeah, well, we can handle it case-by-case and give them a DRM free code whenever we have to
for GOG or whatever if you think people care that much about DRM.
Schafer: I mean, probably be they wouldn't notice all these things like a flicking shadow or something under the seat.
But it's just that people who buy DRM free copies of games are like, "I'm not signing on to anything.
I don't want to sign on to Steam." Rice: Right. Franzke: They hate--they hate Steam.
Schafer: And they were loud about that until we made the DRM free version of the game,
the first game, so...
And then what happens if we ship late to Nordic?
What does Nordic do if we ship late to them?
Rice: Uh, the disc is late, then all the dates shift.
Schafer: And then what happens?
Rice: Then all the dates shift.
Schafer: And then what happens.
Rice: Tell Sony and Justin's mad, and, yeah.
Rice: Yeah? I'm just trying to balance that out like how bad it would be if-- okay, anyway.
Maybe they wouldn't notice issues.
Rice: This is why we never wanted to sim ship a disc.
This is why we wanted to, like, have the game out there,
have it be patched and finished before we did. So as soon as we signed a contract to sim ship,
we knew it would mean either finishing it all and having this period
or having a build on a disc that wasn't fully patched.
Schafer: Say we slipped the disc date by two weeks.
Does that mean moving that revenue out of the plan for two weeks is Justin's problem
or that there's something bigger with Nordic where they have a truck idling
in the loading dock for two weeks?
Rice: It's that. They want us to right now announce a date.
And Sony wants us to commit to a date.
Everyone wants us to commit to a date.
We've been holding it off because of all these moving pieces.
Schafer: But it sounds like we already are committed to a date if we're saying we can't slip it.
Rice: We haven't totally, but we should and that's what he wants to know.
Schafer: Why don't we just move it two weeks and then commit to it?
Rice: 'Cause I don't know that Justin can.
They've been talking-- so there's, like, million pieces in place.
Schafer: Like, these are all the ones we know about.
I'm talking about there's a bug that we ship on the disc that is, like every--
it's like the elevator, Manny locked in the elevator bug.
Rice: Okay. Schafer: Everyone's posting vines about it all over, it's all over Twitter the next day.
And everyone's like, everyone's freaking out about this bug.
Say I can't this patch 'cause I bought the disc, or I was dumb enough to buy the disc version.
You know, and it's just like we're ripping off everybody and that's the story.
And if it's that on one hand or slipping the date by two weeks, I would slip the date by two weeks.
But I want to know what's the consequence of that?
Rice: Yeah, we'll talk about it after.
Schafer: Yeah.
Romero: Uh, all right, almost to the forest.
Let's see.
Rice: That was the first thing I thought when we had that conversation.
I was like, oh, is there wiggle room in their production schedule
for, uh, the box?
And I looked, and no, their drop dead is, like, the 24th.
And that's why they wanted it on the 20th so they could, like, prepare everything.
Uh, so it would mean pushing the box date out, which I think, since it would be our fault for delivering a build later
that we'd have to push everything.
'Cause I think, like, if we delivered the build on time and they were the reason that the box showed up late,
then we could have shipped and not have it sim shipped.
But, um, yeah, we have to sim ship with them.
Uh, so, yeah, it would mean, um, moving all the other stuff, which is possible.
It just is, like, going back to everybody and making sure that they're okay with it.
And especially since Anna's been out all week, it's made it even trickier.
We've got, like, all the other programmers piling on now to try and help out.
So that's helping, but, yeah, I mean, I guess we're still gonna end up with looking like
at least another week or two of game play bugs.
There's just also this unknown question of, like, is there a big bug that we're missing
that we don't know about?
I think that Tim is a little bit worried about, like, our patching solution on the disc, too,
and even if that's, like, um, gonna be well met by customers.
Yeah, I guess the question is whether we are gonna be okay with
now rolling out to all of our partners and potentially having to move it back a week or two.
Bailey: Yeah, I mean, that's problematic.
We--it's in our best interests to stick to the April 28th date.
Rice: Mm-hm. Bailey: So, um, it's just there's not a whole lot of wiggle room left.
Rice: Yeah. Hansen: Yeah, he's trying to-- he's trying to lay out the whole thing to Justin.
I mean, honestly, what we've got to do is present options for Justin.
You know, there's pros and cons for each one of them, right?
And it's--we need to make a business decision on this.
Bailey: Because it's a double hit for us to, like, take on more expense for Broken Age to go a week longer.
But then also not to have the money that's being brought in, so...
Hansen: You know, Tim's already made his decision, but, you know, Justin needs to weigh in on it also
because there's a lot at stake for this, so...
There's ramifications of all these decisions, but, I mean, we want to push for the one that's gonna give
the highest quality game at the end.
Rice: Yeah, the question is whether we can maybe just push the date back of starting burning all of those discs
and still make the 28th, because the rest of it actually looks like
it's kinda on track for the 28th as far as digital release across all of our other platforms.
So I don't think that really affects the digital dates.
Hansen: One week of bug fixing and then one week of-- you know, nobody's touching the build.
Rice: Yeah, exactly. Hansen: It's just in QA.
Rice: If we can go to them and see if they can move their date for manufacturing back and not touch the final date,
then that seems like it should be good.
Bailey: Okay. I mean hearing this, you know, you're probably right.
Let's just go ahead and, um...
I think it'd be good to maybe just even get a call and just get all the major stakeholders on the line at once
and then we can talk about what the date's looking like and then talk about some stuff
that we can give as well and figure it out.
Hansen: I almost don't want to, like-- the way we phrase this is kind of important 'cause we don't want to, like,
ask them as much as like, we have to do this.
I don't see an alternative, so. Bailey: We're just telling them.
Hansen: About getting them onboard. Bailey: We're like, "Hey, we're in the production, you know,
so we're definitely not gonna make the five weeks that's, you know, ideal for you guys.
Hansen: Yeah.
[Music] Um, so I guess we can start any time,
uh, any time you want.
Bailey: Um, are you guys okay-- we have our camera crew.
They want to film this for the documentary.
So are you guys okay with being on camera, or your voices being on tape?
Nordic Rep: Sure.
Bailey: The bad news is that we had about a five week, um...
On your production schedule, it had five weeks out when we actually gave you guys the build,
like, for us to actually get the build to you, and for you then to be able to get this pressed.
So with the bugs and other things we're running up against now, it looks like--
I don't know if we're gonna need to go right up against that deadline,
but we're gonna need more time than the five weeks we planned for
in that schedule you guys sent over.
Rice: I think the date we know we'd be confident at having a stable build ready for you to press disc
is April third.
So, yeah, I guess that's where the question comes in is if there's a little bit more wiggle room on your guys' side
to try and push back that disc pressing date a little bit.
Nordic Rep: So you're saying April third would be ready to replicate, right?
Rice: Yeah.
Nordic Rep: Well, I mean, that would give us enough time for an April 28th release.
Bailey: Good. Rice: Cool.
That's what we were hoping.
Bailey: Yay. All right.
Rice: Okay. So, yeah, I guess we just didn't know if there was, like, buffer
built into that schedule or not.
Nordic Rep: I mean, it's tight, you know.
Rice: Sounds great. Hansen: That'd be awesome.
Nordic Rep: But let me--you know, if we can--you know, if that's a reliable date,
if April 3 is reliable, you know, then I'm cool with it, you know.
If we actually do have a master going into replication on April 4,
you know, that works for us.
-Okay. -But there's no-- I mean there's absolutely
no buffer in there anymore.
Rice: That's what we figured, but that sounds great.
I mean, I think the team's gonna be excited about that for sure.
Bailey: And having you guys in here as well, you know, this could be probably the biggest launch
I think Double Fine's ever done.
Nordic Rep: Very good. Bailey: Yeah.
Exciting time.
Rice: So April 28th.
Hansen: Yep, April 28th.
Bailey: Awesome. Nordic Rep: All right.
Hansen: Yeah, yeah, it's-- we would-- basically it would be pencils down on the 27th.
Rice: Cool. Hansen: And then we'd just-- it just cooks in QA after that.
Rice: Right. Hansen: That should be really good.
We'll have a really solid build at that point.
Rice: Cool. I mean, it seems like best case scenario.
I didn't think they were gonna be so easy to move.
It's 'cause they had that buffer, waiting.
Bailey: I think the camera helped.
The camera probably did help.
Bailey: Thanks, 2 Player! Hansen: Yeah.
Schafer: Okay.
So I heard that I could add a character.
Yeah, okay. No, that's awesome.
Hansen: Maybe....two characters? Schafer: That's really good news.
I did not want to go into this knowing that we'd have to ship depending on a day one patch for basic stability.
So that's much better. That's awesome. Thank you.
Hansen: So this week's really important. So we need to make sure the team remains focused and we are reviewing the bugs constantly.
Rice: Sweet.
Cool, and Nordic's gonna be putting testers on it, too,
looking at German.
Perfect. Coull: So, um, yeah.
Rice: Awesome. Sounds good.
Almost there, man. Almost there.
-I know.
Hopefully everyone will make one more week...
-...and we'll be, uh... -All right.
She's in. She's in right now.
Yeah, she just got here.
We should go talk to her.
Hi Anna. Kipnis: Hi.
Rice: Are you feeling better?
Kipnis: A little bit.
Rice: But they could turn around in three weeks they said, so --
If it got to where we had to move it to the third, we probably could.
Yeah.
Kipnis: Well...
Rice: Well, I'm glad you're feeling better.
Kipnis: Yeah.
That was the worst week to have missed of work.
I mean, of all the times to get sick.
I would get emails every once in a while where I was like, fuck.
Well, I felt like I was letting the team down, but that the game wasn't gonna go in the toilet
or anything while I was out so...
Yeah, I mean, it's nice to really trust your colleagues.
That's a good feeling that they actually, like, took the time to do it and stuff.
That's, I don't know, that's great, too, so.
Hey, I'm still not a hundred percent right now, but, um, I--I feel confident
that we'll-- you know, we'll make it, especially with the little bit of extra time that we got.
Rice: Sounds good.
Crook: Okay. Rice: Good plan.
Boop, boop, boop.
Yay!
[Music] Crook: Yeah. Yeah, I'm just excited to be done, uh, soon.
Three years.
Kipnis: Yeah, it, uh, it's great.
It feels weird.
It feels weird that it's almost done.
It's the strangest thing.
Franzke: Yeah, it is kind of weird.
It's kind of weird to-- Well, it's kind of weird that it took three years.
I don't think--I don't think we kind of thought in the beginning it would take that long.
[Music] Schafer: Well, you know, three years is not that long for a game.
People will laugh at that, but Brutal was four years.
Grim-- I mean Psychonauts was five years.
Grim was three years, so it's the same amount of time as Grim with a smaller team and less crunch mode.
Grim was really, like, six years if you count all the evenings that we worked.
Um, but it's weird--it's weird to look at the old episodes and just think about how long we've been working on this
and how different it felt in the beginning.
[Music] Look, Broken Age alumni.
We're wrapping it up. We're remembering the old people like Levi.
Ryken: Hi, everybody.
Rice: We miss you.
Schafer: Hello, everybody. Can you remind us, Greg, where we are, what's the schedule, and what will be happening now?
Rice: So the next thing is locking down the build, which is happening at the end of the week.
Franzke: So really, it's not actually all that super glamorous, but essentially what you can see is all these files here
that have the exclamation mark on it.
And what that means is that these files are different from the version of the file that's already in that branch.
So that's the release candidate branch and so I just say accept this and it will say okay.
That means I will overwrite all your files that you have right now
and then just let Perforce do its thing.
Have the little guy walking, which is still my favorite-- one of my favorite icons in terms of tools.
This is really a lot of programming, and especially release engineering
is just sitting around waiting for files to be copied and for certain operations to be performed on files,
which is just kind of weird, like one would expect that, you know, shipping a game is, like,
super exciting kind of stuff.
But really, in the end of a day, it's a lot of copying files from A to B
and sitting around waiting for those files to be copied.
Um, all right. So now we essentially have, like, all the yellow exclamation marks are gone,
which means we now have a list of files, all the files that were changed.
And I'm just gonna say, okay, I want to commit these into the release kind of branch,
so I'm gonna say integration from main.
And this is actually also lock down, so I'm gonna say content lock.
Oh, I actually have to spell it correctly.
And then I say submit, and that's essentially it.
So now we grab all the files from the main line and copy them over into the release candidate branch,
and we lock down the build.
Rice: Right now all the, uh, disc stuff is basically off to Nordic and on their plate,
so that should actually go into manufacturing this week.
And they said they said they're gonna talk with us for photos
and gonna update as they go along.
But this should be tracking towards same day launching the disc as the game digitally.
Schafer: I know what you're saying, why are you wearing luau clothes, Tim?
-Yeah. Rice: Why are you wearing-- -No, it's pretty normal.
Schafer: I am wearing both pants and luau pants because tonight we are going to have a bonfire down at the beach
to celebrate the completion of Broken Age, everybody.
[Applause] Yay!
He's like, son of a-- about fucking time!
Yes, okay.
It's just about done, right, Oliver?
No way it could ever bounce out of cert now?
You only have time to eat now during meetings.
Yeah! Yes!
[Music]