Schafer: Hi, guys. How's it going?
This is the last one of these we'll ever do?
Offscreen: Yeah.
Schafer: Seems like only yesterday I was saying all that stuff, sitting in this chair
that I can't remember now, 'cause it's been so long ago.
Offscreen: Mm-hmm, we talked about that initial budget in that chair.
Schafer: Don't bring that up.
[Laughter] Yeah, it's just-- it's this one,
and then it's, ahh!
[Music] Schafer: Tonight, we are going to have a bonfire down at the beach
to celebrate the completion of "Broken Age," everybody.
[Applause] Yay!
Teamwork!
It started out like a really fun idea, and then it got really hard.
And a bunch of people wussed out, but a lot of people stuck around to the end.
I wanna thank you, thank you to the whole team, and thank you everybody.
We're done!
Like, we went to the beach, we had that party, things got a little out of control.
[Yelling] And it's fun, it's fun 'cause it's, like,
not fixing things right at the last minute.
We kinda had it done in advance a little bit, at least for-- for me and us.
Like, it was, um, wrapped and submitted.
Like, we had to submit for the disc version, and that kind of actually-- it was tough,
but it forced us to have a lot of stuff done before the, um, actual launch date,
'cause we had to have that version burnt to disc.
And so, um...we had to time to kind of, like...
adjust to the thought of it being over.
Um, so, Reds is done and it's awesome.
The end.
Rice: It's done?
Oh my God.
That's kinda sad.
We sent review keys out to press for "Broken Age," so there's already, like, 10 or so folks
that are playing for review.
With the amount of time that it's taken and the amount of things that have happened
in the last three years is, uh, staggering.
And, um, it was nice to see everyone care enough to push for a final product
that could be something we're proud of.
Crook: Um, so yeah, it just, um, it kind of all came together at the end.
Um...so I feel good right now.
Offscreen: You feel good about it? Crook: Yeah.
I think it's beautiful, and something that we should be proud of.
Uh, I think people are gonna really like it.
Russell: Yes, we're finished.
See, I knew it would happen.
And after 13, 14 years here, you know stuff's gonna get done,
and it'll be great in the end.
It'll be all worth it.
Schafer: Rusty. Russell: I'm playin' through and fixin' bugs.
Schafer: Well, thanks for playing.
Russell: Mostly playing. Schafer: Mm-hmm.
Awesome. What do you think so far?
Russell: I got confused, actually.
As much as I played through-- -I was-- Schafer: That's not good!
Rice: It's not a scripted cutscene, so you wouldn't know.
Russell: Yeah, exactly.
Schafer: Excellent, did you figure it out, or did ask for a hint?
Russell: I had to ask Ray.
Schafer: Oh... -Oh...
And also, look, it's running on, uh, iPhone 6.
-Thanks... Rice: Not anymore.
Schafer: Not--b-but--it's a black screen.
Oliver!
Oh, spoilers for "Act 2"!
Okay.
Anyway, it's running.
Franzke: But, yeah.
As you can see, the game is running a little thing-- This one just crashed, but it does work.
I am extremely proud of, you know, the product the way it is right now.
Um...and, yeah, I hope it will stand the test of time.
Schafer: And then we are on the street on April 28th.
It'll be awesome.
Um, and Anna's alive.
Look at that, everybody.
Yay, Anna's alive!
Yay!
Kipnis: It feels--it feels good.
It feels like, uh, we did-- we did something good and worthwhile
and something that hopefully will, you know, uh, have a-- I don't know, a future?
Like, have a legacy of some kind.
Schafer: I really, uh, felt good about the second chapter.
You know, I feel like it answered anyone's critique about the first one,
you know, without changing the game completely, you know.
I think it definitely was, you know, harder and longer, and, um, and amazingly done in less time, so...
Stoddard: I did my first full, full playthrough last weekend, and it is a hard game.
It's really challenging and it's really well-done and it's engaging.
Like, I've worked on this thing for years and I still-- like, the story was still getting me.
It's pretty good.
And when I hit the final scene, like, man, dude,
it's, uh... it's cinematic.
It's like it hits you.
Definitely.
Um...so that felt good.
I just had to have a moment to...
start loving it again.
I mean, like, I had this point in here where, like, the love I have for this just kinda
got knocked out for a few days.
And that was really scary.
That was really scary.
And, um...
It was hard.
Schafer: We're going to our last stand-ups?
Is it last stand-ups?
I believe it is.
Hello, everybody.
Oh, look at the big-- Did we not get bagels for the final stand-ups?
Crook: Ah, I didn't try.
Schafer: Come on! It's our last one.
Get your ass off Bagel.
I brought this for emotional support.
In case I get emotional.
Crook: Just keep hugging it. Schafer: I'm not gonna get emotional.
Crook: Squeezing it, hugging it. Schafer: I doubt it.
I doubt it. We're not done.
Are we? We done?
Crook: This is the last standup.
Schafer: You playing right now?
This game is so addictive.
Cannot put it down for one second.
Um...this might be-- this is our last proper standup for the full team, but, uh...
don't worry, I won't give a speech or anything.
And then you always have this post-project depression, which is, like, you've defined yourself by who you are
by making this game for so long, and then it's over and you're like, "Who am I?
Am I not the person who makes 'Broken Age'?
What am I? What's the point of it all?" Crook: Before, when we were just doing, like, a big game,
it would ship, and then the whole studio didn't have anything to do for a while.
And every--I think every-- the whole-- You could kinda feel that in the air
and it just kind of-- it was just-- it was kind of a downer.
And, uh, because there's multiple projects now, we can all just jump onto things,
and that helps-- helps you, uh, I think helps me, get out of that.
And so that's why there was a need on "Day of the Tentacle."
Um, so now-- now I'm on to that.
Um, I'm--I hear it's really bad for people who are leading the project.
Uh, but Tim doesn't-- I mean, he doesn't show it.
He's pretty good with hiding, I think, his sadness.
But, um...
He's just sad all the time.
No.
Uh, but I'm sure he-- I'm sure it will hit him, you know,
because this is three years, uh, put into this.
Schafer: No, I don't get depressed.
I'm too old to get depressed.
Offscreen: Don't you have any sympathy for all the people that have been insisting the game will never finish?
Schafer: I do--I do feel bad for all the people who have based their identity
on the fact that I'll never finish this game.
'Cause we'll finish it and then they'll have post-project depression.
If I'm not that person who hates Tim Schafer, who am I?
Excellent.
Thank you. Panya's last standup, for sure.
Inversin: Yeah, for sure.
I'm out this week, guys, so it's been a pleasure.
But, uh, uh, yeah.
Crook: Go inside, Victor. You're next.
Schafer: Yeah, nice try, Victor. Crook: There you go.
Romero: Almost. -Schafer: All right, we'll miss you, Panya. Victor!
Crook: Yep. Schafer: Victor.
Romero: I'll miss you, Panya, uh...
Schafer: Oh, shipping games is always tense, and then afterwards there's this moment
where if there's ever gonna be any turnaround in the company,
it usually happens at that moment, 'cause people hang on to the--they want--
everyone wants to finish the project they're on.
That--so that's usually the period where people will come and go,
is--is in that period.
Okay, everyone, thanks for coming to dailies all those times.
It's over. Next project.
Rice: Yay! Crook: That's it.
Stoddard: Man, he's sentimental.
Crook: Yeah.
Coull: So.
Sad panda- I'm leaving.
Um...
What else do you want to know about it.
No, I mean, um, the contract was supposed to come to an end anyway.
The fact that it went on a month after was pretty-- pretty awesome for me.
You know, maybe they'll need me again in the future, but, you know, you can't be certain, I guess.
Schafer: Oliver is still cranking away on the final final versions of it
to get it out the door.
And then Oliver will be moving back to Germany, sadly.
I think some of you know this; we've talked about this.
Oliver is--the-- the--the pull of the fatherland is too strong.
He must go back.
Oliver wants to move.
He's gonna keep working for us, but he's gonna move to Germany.
But he's gonna be working on "Day of the Tentacle." So you don't have to be mean to Oliver.
That's the main point. Usually when someone's leaving, we make sure everyone knows in advance
so that they can be mean to them.
Franzke: So in a few weeks, I'm actually going to move back.
So it will be interesting to see how...
how much German culture has changed since I moved away.
Maybe I'll feel like a complete foreigner for a while.
Who knows? I don't even know.
So, all future interviews will have to be through Skype.
Offscreen: Gonna miss you, Oliver. Franzke: Yeah...
I'm gonna miss you guys too.
It's gonna be weird.
Schafer: I think it's-- it's been a tough time because we haven't, you know,
it's been a while since we've given raises to people, and so there's other companies in the area
that are making a lot of money right now, and so they're able to throw that kind of money around,
and that'll probably cause us to-- Uh, that always happens.
We lose through--when, like, Oculus and Facebook took off, they started throwing money around.
We lost some people to that.
Um, but after "Broken Age" comes out, we'll be able to throw money around, right,
'cause we'll be rich off of, uh, all those point-and-click adventure dollars.
Actually, we don't expect to make a lot of money off of "Broken Age,"
because everyone bought it the first time.
And, um, but the new platforms like, um, PS4 are going to be opening up some new customers.
Bailey: There's a lot banking on it, but--but not everything.
I mean, we diversified to do some of those LucasArts properties
like "Grim Fandango" and, like, uh, "Day of the Tentacle." Uh, so "Grim" sales are really good.
Um, you know...
[Applause] It's, like, $1.7 million gross,
which is good.
So, across all platforms for the last week, um...
Schafer: I'm feelin' kinda gross. Bailey: Yeah.
And, you know, it looks like those are-- are gonna bring in a lot of, uh,
a lot of money for the studio, so...
Schafer: And I hope there's a lot of people out there who were just waiting for the whole thing to be one game
and don't care about crowdfunding and they don't wanna know about
our little transparency efforts.
They just wanna play a game when it's done and, um, hopefully they will buy it.
Please join me in welcoming Mr. James Spafford.
-Yay! -Thank you, guys.
James Spafford.
Uh, would you please stand up so everyone can see you.
This is James, and rotate one time.
No, you don't have to rotate.
Uh, James...
uh, welcome to Double Fine.
So James Spafford used to be one of the two people who ran Mixnmojo, which is an old LucasArts fan site,
and I knew him back then when he visited our offices in 2001, I think, and gave me some Marmite.
And, um...and now I said, "In 10 years, we'll hire you."
Fifteen years? "In 15 years, we'll hire you"-- as our community manager.
-Whoa. -He's not the new Chris Remo.
He will never be the new Chris Remo!
-Yeah. Muir: 'Cause he's not dead.
Schafer: In other news, Chris Remo's dead.
No.
Spafford: I mean, I'm a long-time follower of Double Fine and everything they've been doing.
I'm a backer.
Uh, obviously backed immediately.
Um, followed the documentary series, which I'm now on, which is really weird, uh...
Offscreen: Is he aware of everything that's happened?
Did he know what he was getting himself into?
Schafer: Don't tell him about gamergate.
No, he knows, he knows.
That's--that's the exciting new challenge for him, will be, um, rebuilding all the things.
Spafford: I knew what was going on.
I mean, certainly, lots of people were not happy about the game being split.
Um...so I feel like, yeah, that--that might've been the start of some troubles.
But probably the start of any community troubles was the day that the Kickstarter was made
and, um, $3.5 million was raised and a lot of people's money
was riding on a thing that they had in their head, a vision that they had that this thing was gonna be.
And, you know, it wasn't the way some people wanted it to be.
I never want to give up on people who are like, "You know, I'll try everything."
If people are really mad, a lot of the time you can--
you can--you know, you can bring them around.
There's always some way that you can make them happy again.
Um...yeah, it's just finding out what that is.
Schafer: It's--it's good timing, 'cause we're--as we're wrapping up the game, we're coming out of production
and getting back into all the community-facing stuff, like getting out the last of the backer rewards.
Like, we still have a lot of these little mini portraits that Bagel has to paint.
So, like, it's come to that point where we're kind of, um,
closin' the loop on the story, big story, and so we'll be facin' the backers a lot,
and it's good to have a community manager for that.
Okay, so we're just--are we just talking about the launch plans for the game as far as PR and marketing?
What's--what's your marketing budget on the game?
Rice: Zero...?
Schafer: Okay.
Spafford: One of the big things I wanna talk about is how we talk about "Act 2"
and how we properly do this, like how we bring this thing out.
Schafer: How do we talk about "Act 2"? Spafford: The biggest thing, right.
Schafer: So just, like, the--what's it called?
Spafford: Well, like, no, as in...
how are you getting people to think about it?
You want people to think about it as a whole game, -or as episode two? Rice: Yeah.
Schafer: Like, now that it's done, I would like it to just be just "Broken Age,"
as if we never split it at all.
Rice: So, yeah, I think that the hope was, like, a year from now, the story would be more about just the game as it is,
not that it was split or anything.
Spafford: When it was released, we did-- people did reviews of it and stuff, right?
Like, treated it like it was its own thing.
So I wonder how persuadable people will be to just forget that and move on.
Rice: But I still think we probably have to speak to the people who did already buy it, and--
Schafer: Yeah, because this is a worry that I do have, that people are like, "When's 'Act 2' coming out?"
And that they don't see that announcement, -"'Act 2' is out"-- Rice: Yeah.
Schafer: Like, the answer to that question, they might miss the fact that it came out.
Rice: Yeah.
Yeah, so I think we still need to be saying that, like, for people who purchased "Act 1,"
they're getting the full game now, updated with "Act 2" content.
Spafford: Yep. Rice: But...
Spafford: The PS4 and iOS is definitely a really good chance to just talk about the whole game.
So we've been trying to get people to play the PS4 version,
which is a new platform, um, and doesn't have that distinction.
Like, it's just one game on that platform.
So the more people we can get to look at that and talk about that,
the more-- the more hopeful we are that that can be a thing.
Rice: Not--not speaking to just, like, what's gonna happen in "Act 2," you know,
'cause that's how we've all been thinking about it for a long time, but speaking of, like,
what is this game?
Spafford: Looking at the full-- the full picture now it's done.
Other than that, we're just trying to, you know, beg, borrow, and steal every bit of coverage we can.
Rice: We were able to get a European press tour on zero dollars.
Schafer: I...w-well... Rice: So that's good.
Schafer: We're not paying anything for that?
Rice: Um, we are paying for three days of a B&B, but they're paying for all of our flights
and our B&B while we're there, so...
Um, I think it's all pretty set now.
So, um, flights and hotels and everything is in there.
There'll be-- basically we get to UK first for the first weekend,
and then the Monday after that we're doing, like, a bunch of press at Media Molecule.
Um, and we'll have Eurogamer, Edge, and The Guardian, uh, all that day in their offices.
And then, yeah, we have the talk in Vyborg with Peter and Ray.
[Music] Spafford: We should pick a day for having press around as well,
and then we can start organizing them.
[Music] Schafer: So what do you think so far, Marty?
Sliva: I think it's awesome.
Schafer: Give us your, um, full review now.
Sliva: Just verbatim, and then you guys can write it down.
Schafer: We need to know the score before we decide whether -you're leaving the room. Sliva: Yeah, okay.
Schafer: That's just a common-- Sliva: That's--that's happened-- That's happened before with other publishers, so--
Schafer: Really? They're, like... Rice: Oh, God.
Sliva: I think it's mostly like, like, "You can do an exclusive, but what's the score,"
you know what I mean? It's like, well, I'm not gonna do that, then.
Uh, everyone always says, like, "Oh, this is gonna be the adventure game
that gets people to play adventure games who haven't played adventure games."
Like, you--is that bullshit to you?
Like, is that-- is that necessary?
Do you think adventure games need that, -or do you think it's-- Schafer: I've always been--
I've always been interested in it, because it always seemed like
with adventure games that we were trying to get beyond the-- the limited audience
of people currently playing--playing games.
Not that they're limited, but there-- there was a, back in the '90s,
a small group of the culture at large that was playing games at all.
And it seemed like there are all these people who weren't playing games and they're like, hey,
I think you would like a game that, well, it's about story, where you don't have to worry about getting shot in the head,
and, like, you could play at your own pace and it involved themes that weren't
being covered in games, you know.
So we always, you know, we always, you know...
People would tell us, like, "This is the only game that my girlfriend will play with me."
And it was--that was always the story.
Like, there's all these people out there who, you know, why aren't they playing games?
And I think this is the game they would like.
But, um, you know, it's always been hard to reach those people, and, um, and make them feel like they would like--
You know, they think of themselves as someone who would not play video games.
It's hard to get past that identity problem, almost.
Sliva: Totally. Schafer: So I do think about it, but I don't think it's necessary.
Like, I think it's good enough to make a game that people--
and that's what this Kickstarter is all about.
Like, there are these people who said, "We like adventure games just the way they are."
And they don't need to completely revolutionize with--with how they interact.
They don't need to be a different genre.
They just, "We like the old adventure games and we wanna play another one."
And knowing they were out there and we were making the game for them, uh,
is what made it special this time around.
Rice: There's always been, like, conversation coming up here and there about how we're gonna give backers the codes,
or if we're gonna give them early access to the game or anything like that.
And I feel like it's never been, like, fully talked about and decided upon.
Schafer: I was--I wanted to give it just the--the day before, -the 24 hours before. Rice: Yeah.
Spafford: Yeah, if it's possible without too much mess, then I think that people will really appreciate it.
And in fact, we've set the embargo for press for the same time
as the backers getting their keys so that, you know, everyone's getting
their thing at the same time.
Offscreen: Yeah, 'cause the embargo thing was such an issue last time.
Spafford: I think there is all kinds of emotions about that.
Rice: Tim, did you hear that? Schafer: What?
Rice: "Digital Trends" posted an article, "Why We're Breaking the 'Broken Age' Embargo."
Schafer: Tell 'em maybe he didn't agree to anything, but he knows he's bein' a shit.
Bailey: I was looking over all of our news broadcasts, and basically all the exposure went out
when the backers got it, like, two weeks ago.
Spafford: I think that whole situation probably should have been done a bit differently.
I think we learned a lot from that, by the sounds of things, or at least I hope so.
And I've certainly watched that episode and--and thought, "Okay, we need to not do that."
Yeah, so, it--today is Friday.
Uh, on Sunday night, we're gonna send out backer keys to people, which is pretty exciting.
Um, 24 hours later, the game will unlock on Steam and be pushed out, uh, around the world
onto however many millions of platforms that we're doing.
Um, so by Tuesday, uh, morning when we all come into the office,
the game will be out, everyone will be playing, no one will have any problems, everything will be fine,
and everyone will be having a good time.
That's--that's the gist of it.
Hansen: Flawless. Franzke: What could go wrong, right?
Hansen: Yeah, don't say that.
Rice: It's all gonna be perfect.
Hansen: It--it may not be perfect.
Rice: Um, all right.
All right.
Let's put out the Kickstarter update?
Spafford: Let's do it.
Schafer: Yo, yo, yo, yo, yo.
Yo, yo, yo, yo, yo.
Hi, everybody.
Hello, hello, thank you for waiting.
Thanks for-- sorry about the delay.
It's still so interesting, Melina just magically appears there.
Hello, Melina, nice to see you.
Awesome, awesome.
Okay. Hi, everybody.
Uh, today I've been very preoccupied 'cause "Broken Age" is in the hands of our backers
and people are playing it, which is amazing!
Yeah!
Offscreen: Do you wanna look at the forum right now?
Schafer: Okay.
Let's go to the forum, shall we?
"Spoiler: Need hint urgently." Ah! Ah!
Take that, right?
Right?
Where's the general...
"Let's talk about how much we love the game" thread?
Let's see.
Discussion and feedback.
"I finished this morning.
What an incredible game!" That's all I'm gonna read.
That's it.
"Everything about 'Act 2' has improved the game dramatically.
The puzzles are a lot more detailed.
Required me to pull out a notepad." Yay.
That's nice. I'm glad it makes-- I get excited when I pull out a notepad.
"I liked 'Act 1,' but it was a little linear.
'Act 2' is perfect.
And to Tim and everyone at Double Fine, I really appreciate you and what you've done so much."
Well, that's nice.
Ah! The game's out.
I mean, it really comes out tomorrow, or midnight tonight.
But it's out, the review embargo is lifted, we got a 9.2 from "Game Informer,"
and it should be good for launch, official launch day tomorrow,
where it'll be out on all platforms and everywhere.
Um, so now we just sit around and read reviews and pretend we don't care about 'em.
That's the...regular thing.
I'm gonna sit there, like, all night just waiting for them to come in.
You see one, you're like, "Oh, that-- that was awesome! I'm gonna read one more!
Oh, that was bad, I'm not gonna-- not gonna read any m--
Oh, that one was nice!" And then it all evens out.
I just was reading, like, two different reviews, one talking about being too hard
and one being, it's too easy.
And, uh, you know, that just seems to be the way with those games.
They're just, like, um...
people--people react strongly and very subjectively and, um...I don't know.
Like, I feel like it takes years, almost, for people to really decide
how they feel about these games.
So 10 years from now we'll find out if it was any good.
Offscreen: It seems a bit strange that there's review scores for "Act 1," "Act 2--"
And the whole thing.
Schafer: Yeah, it's a mess... it's a mess.
Never split your game in half.
Rice: By the way, there's a lot of people talking about it, so that's good.
Um, and tomorrow we're partying, and I think I sent an invite out to everybody.
So, bar crawl, I think we're just starting at Victory Hall, 'cause it's close and we can walk there,
and then we're gonna go-- Schafer: And then the hardcore. Rice: Chinatown.
Schafer: To people who care about history and wanna relive history through the bars of Chinatown and beyond.
Rice: So, tonight at 9:00 our time, midnight Eastern, is when all the other platforms will go up.
Bottle Opener: In the name of Lars Halford, open up!
Franzke: Okay, so we've got Ouya lined up.
I guess we just need to press that button.
Rice: The button?
Uh, Spaff figured out some way to wire this weird Divekick button...
Spafford: It's not that weird! Rice: ...to launching the game.
-Cheers. Franzke: Well, cheers to you guys.
Spafford: It's okay, we're toasting the five-- four-minute countdown
to pressing the blue button.
Do you want the blue pill, or the yellow pill?
Rice: Oh my God, everything explodes.
Franzke: The game gets deleted, obliterated from the server, so don't press the yellow button.
Spafford: All the money is refunded.
Franzke: The code gets unwritten, the art unmade.
Rice: Yep.
Spafford: What are we gonna do for four minutes, you guys?
We could read Twitter for a bit.
Spafford: People are really happy. Rice: The reviews have been -really good. Spafford: Yep.
Rice: Just, like, the way they describe the puzzles and the writing,
it makes it-- makes it feel like people actually really got it,
-which is nice. Spafford: We should get ready, because we're about to--to go into...
Rice: Let's do it, you guys.
Spafford: You should. Franzke: Okay, Greg, It's hovering over the button.
Rice: You do this one. Franzke: I do this one?
This is Steam; this is the big one.
Rice: I know. You do this one. Franzke: All right.
Spafford: Press the "Okay" button!
Franzke: All right, here it goes!
It's live on Steam.
Rice: Yay. Spafford: Oh, my God.
Rice: Okay. Spafford: All right, next one.
Franzke: Okay, here's iOS.
Spafford: Oh my God, oh my God, oh my God.
Rice: Oh, man...
Franzke: All right, here, Spaff.
Franzke: Spaff, you do the OS X App Store.
Spafford: Release this version.
Franzke: Release!
I'll do Ouya.
Rice: Yep, there you go.
You're in that one.
Spafford: Ouya's live?
Franzke: Waiting--yep. Spafford: Okay.
Franzke: Just Google Play.
Rice: Okay, wait, is this the last one?
Franzke: Yeah. Rice: Let's all do this one.
Franzke: Okay. Ready?
Rice: Final build, one, two, three, go.
[Music] Franzke: But, yes, this is my last, I guess,
full day in the office, one could say.
Not that I'm actually gonna do any work, but, um...
Today is "Broken Age" launch day, officially.
Uh, so lots of parties lined up.
I am just gonna pretend they're all for me, for my leave--for one of my leaving parties.
Uh...but yeah, it's--it's weird.
It's weird. What is that? Oh.
Oh, because we don't actually need this anymore?
That's true, I guess I don't need to talk while-- Brr!
There's that.
All right?
Rice: We just put out the new trailer, so we're trying to, like, spread those around, um...
Offscreen: Elijah Wood? Rice: I did see that.
So Elijah just tweeted, like, thirty minutes ago about the game.
Right there, see? Boom.
Yay, Elijah.
Like you see right now, we're at, like, twenty-five or so on the list.
Um...and then the hope is that that'll start going up, so, by a couple things.
One is, we can check and see now if it's getting featured.
Okay, so there it is.
Yay. So this showed up.
So this'll help, especially since it's on sale.
Um, that's always nice.
On Steam people see that sale number.
We do get daily Android and iOS sales.
PS4 probably won't, uh, give us any kinda inclination for, like, a week or so, maybe, um, maybe more.
Spafford: They're the most interesting ones, I think.
Rice: Yeah, that'll be interesting, 'cause it's new.
Um...brand-new sales and it's reviewing well there and everything.
So, uh, I think we'll have a better idea in, like, a couple weeks across all platforms,
but we'll at least have an inkling of what to expect, um, from the ones that we can see soon.
It's just, those are the ones that we've already been out and being sold on for a while now,
so it's hard to say.
That's it.
Congrats.
Schafer: Uh...
Yeah, yeah.
Rice: You're so excited.
Schafer: Yep.
Phone voice: Press one.
To send a voicemail, press two.
Schafer: I don't know what hap-- why it did that there.
Phone voice: Home screen.
Schafer: Oh, man. Rice: Okay, all you'll do is say "Green," and then "Okay." Kipnis: Green and then--
Schafer: You press "Send" to accept the call.
Rice: Yeah, this is an old phone, old-school phone.
Kipnis: This is a really old phone, yeah.
It's--it's a burner we got?
Greg: Yeah. Kipnis: Is this what drug dealers use?
Rice: Yes, it's a drug dealer-- Schafer: Oh, I got a voicemail.
Okay, okay.
Phone voice: Home screen.
Kipnis: I love that it announces. Rice: All right, can we start?
Schafer: A hint line--we're talking about doing a hint line, getting a burner phone and just making it a number
that people can call for hints.
You're supposed to say, "Action." Maybe talking to me...
Hm.
I'll probably just be getting people angry, people calling to chew me out about "Spacebase."
Here's a hint: Go buy someone else's games.
Hi, and welcome to the Double Fine Hint Line, which we have had for a long time,
but no one's ever called, it's weird.
Uh, but we're answering calls today for "Broken Age," 'cause today is the launch of "Broken Age"!
Phone voice: Call one. Schafer: Oh, we got a call!
Hold on, everybody.
Hello, Double Fine Hint Line, can I help you?
Phone: Uh, hello, is this Tim?
Schafer: This is Tim.
How are you doing?
Phone: Oh m--oh, my God.
Hello, my name is, uh, Steve Kaufman, and I just wanna say, you are the greatest developers
in--in history, basically.
Schafer: Oh, that's so nice of you to say!
-Oh, that's lovely! Kipnis: Wow.
Phone: Uh, I was really happy as a backer to see it all come together.
Schafer: Aw, thanks for backing. Phone: So, I love it.
Yeah, um, and I actually have a legit-- like, I need a legit tip.
Schafer: Okay, all right, that's why we're here.
Kipnis: Wow, this is really working well.
Rice: There's a lot of people-- Schafer: Hello, Double Fine Hint Line, can I help you?
Kipnis: Maybe some--some asshole would call in and just say really mean things to us, live on the stream.
But it was, like, the opposite.
It just, like, it completely blew our expectations, in the similar way that seeing the game get funded did
on that first day.
It made you feel like the world is a much better place than you thought it was.
Schafer: Bye. Phone: Goodbye.
Schafer: What a lovely fellow. Lovely fellow.
-That was spoiler-free. -Yeah. There we go.
Spoilers: Uh, our backers are great.
Phone: This is Emory Biloski from, uh, Israel calling, actually.
Schafer: You're calling from Israel?
What time-- what time is it there?
-Isn't it super late there? Kipnis: Shalom.
Phone: It's, uh, it's like 1:30 in the morning.
Schafer: Shalom.
Hello, Double Fine Hint Line, can I help you?
Double Fine Hint Line, can I help you?
Rice: Blowin' up, blowin' up.
Schafer: Hello, Double Fine Hint Line, can I help you?
Phone: Oh, shit.
Uh, hi.
Schafer: Language!
Kipnis: Yeah, it was just-- it was a really pleasant surprise,
like, just how lovely everyone was and, like, how fun that whole day--
that whole day was really amazing.
Spafford: That's it. We're done.
Kipnis: Yay. That was-- that was a great last call.
Rice: Well, we might turn the phone back on later.
Kipnis: Really? Rice: So, you never know.
Schafer: While we're hangin' out, just out in the bar later?
All right, let's get this good time over with.
Woo!
Nothing seems to happen until I stand up and get everyone's attention
and then say thank you to everybody.
I've made so many toasts.
Peter McConnell's here, everybody.
Peter McConnell. Nice to see you.
Thank you for all the excellent music in the game.
McConnell: Well, thank you.
When you've worked on something for--for a good long time,
you know, over two years, you know, two and a half for me, three I think for the--
for--for the--the team at large, um, uh, it's hard not to be, you know,
a little misty-eyed about it.
It's-it's like getting to the end of the game, when you play the game, um,
where--where you have to, um, say, oh, well, you know, these characters
have become my friends and--and now I have to say, you know, goodbye to the story
and goodbye to the characters.
And so there's a certain amount of sadness, I guess.
And--and, uh, certainly, um, you know, there's a little relief.
It's always nice to be-- actually to say, oh, finally, you know?
Um, you know, but there's also that, oh, well, you know...
I mean, that's...
that's like, uh...um...
It's, uh, an--an era, you know?
A really big project like that, you love like--like a-- like a child.
And, uh, letting it go out into the world is a--is a-- is an emotional moment.
Schafer: Call me if you need any hints.
If you need any hints, give me a call.
All right.
Now, then...
[Gasps] Agh!
[Laughter] That's what you get for being cute!
TV: Oliver, safe travels and best of luck for the future.
And everybody else, stay awesome, stay strong, and find joy in the things that you do.
-Bye. Schafer: Bye!
Kipnis: Aw...
Wow.
Schafer: Awww.
TV: "Broken Age" got released...
Kipnis: Oh!
Schafer: Majus!
TV: I'm so happy for all of you.
Congratulations.
You finished this work of art, and now everybody can see and play it
and it's wonderful!
[Laughter] Struggled with problems and obstacles.
Ups and downs are a normal part
of the whole project.
And you should embrace that.
It's part of it.
"Broken Age" is made out of the ups and downs.
I am really emotional right now.
I wish I could talk to you for real right now.
And hope I see you again soon in the future.
And, uh, let's make more games.
Let's show the world how the sausage gets made.
And, um, yeah.
I love you guys.
Crowd: Aw!
TV: And...yeah.
Let's, uh, let's--we--we'll-- we'll talk in person, so let's not do this.
[Laughter] Schafer: Let's not let this get weird.
TV: Bye. Bye.
I love you.
Crowd: Bye, Majus!
Schafer: I mean, crowdfunding was so great, and is so great in a lot of ways.
Like, it's--the--the, um, the relationship you have with the community
and the-- and the nature of the money is so, um, perfect for what you wanna do,
do something creative and--and community focused without worrying about ties to people
who might wanna try to influence your game because they gave you money.
Um...it's--it's weird because it just happened to time out--
it happened to coincide with a weird phase of the Internet where everyone's super angry all the time and it just, like--
it was hard to be that open and transparent and give everybody--
It's like we opened up a little tray of, you know, bludgeoning instruments so that--
for people could beat us up with.
And then people picked 'em up and just beat us up with them.
And we're like, huh, that was an interesting experiment.
We probably shouldn't have given all those weapons to all the people who are mad.
But, um, if that had not erupted at that moment, you know, maybe I would've thought--
'Cause at the beginning, the transparency was nothing but, like,
um, hugs and, uh, high-fives all around.
Like, everybody at our-- you know, our PAX meetups, like, that was our community experience,
was everyone just telling us how much they were excited about the game
and how much they loved us and everything.
And then when we announced the change in the schedule, just all that-- just people just--
it seemed like there was a big crowd of people just ready to-- just really super mad.
And if you Google, like, um, "'Broken Age,' broken promises" on the Internet-- which I do every night--
if you Google that, you'll see all these angry articles.
Not just from, like, random people on Twitter, but, like, these journalists who are like,
"They really let everybody down with this and they should really be sorry."
And, um...
and here we are at the end and we're shipping the game and it took a long time,
but it's everything we said we were gonna do.
Uh...and I want to mail all those people individually and be like,
"It's time for you to apologize about that article." But I don't think they feel like they were wrong.
I think they feel like-- that we still really messed up.
But, um, I don't.
I feel like...
I feel--isn't it great to know I've learned nothing?
But I feel like...
[Laughter] I feel, like, officially that--
I feel like I just need to make an official announcement that I don't apologize for anything,
because I feel really good about it.
And if we had shipped one day earlier, the game would've been one day buggier.
And, um, if we had shipped the game that the original $3.3 million paid for,
it would've been small.
And I like the game that we made instead, and we put a lot of our own money into it,
and I think I'm really, really happy.
This is the game, this is what the game kinda said that it wanted to be, about this size,
and we did a really good version of it.
And so I don't apologize for anything.
[Music] Raz: He makes me laugh.
"And that's why it's called a game." Schafer: Yay!
[Applause] That's awesome.
Uh, even though you like basketball...
Burbank: We all have our faults.
Schafer: That's awesome. Well, yes.
Well, that's awesome.
Now, uh, congratulations, Gabe.
No speech?
Gabe: No. Schafer: Okay.
Oh...one more thing.
We have boxes of "Broken Age," actual boxes of "Broken Age,"
and we have enough for everyone here to get one!
Ryken: It's under our seat?
Schafer: What?
Look under your seat...
and that'll give me time to open this box.
Offscreen: Now that this is wrapping up, like, how do you feel about the whole experience?
Schafer: I wish I really knew right now if I could say 100% what I learned from all that.
'Cause some of it's still, you know, uh, too soon.
Like, uh, 'cause there's this part of me that's like, I just wanna not tell anybody
about what we're working on right now.
Like, I feel just kinda, like, so exposed that I just wanna be--
I just wanna have some secrets for a little while, just as a kinda break from that.
I had a pleasant trip down memory lane making an adventure game, but I remembered
how hard they are to make.
And, um, I don't think my next game will be an adventure game.
I wouldn't say I'd never make one again.
But in the end, I really-- I really think the team put together a beautiful game,
and that's what I'm most happy with.
'Kay.
Now, this is gonna be awkward in case this came out wrong.
This is a little light.
That's a different game.
What?
Whoa, -look at that. -Beautiful.
It looks beautiful, okay wait.
I don't believe it.
The design of this was supposed to have Vella on the bottom,
'cause her hair is touching the logo.
Not that I'm gonna complain, 'cause it's really awesome.
Okay.
I--I just have to demonstrate before you leave.
This is fantastic.
Let's see if it works; I've never tested this before.
Gah, no, it doesn't work.
Gah! Nope.
Let's see, how does it actually--?
Okay, get rid of this.
Whoa...
Very cool.
And that, and that?
See?
And then, oh...
I want everyone to do that when you get your copy and fix it, okay?
[Applause] That is kinda funny, we did Kickstart this thing
and now it's actually a box in my hand.
Well, that pretty much ends this documentary.
And...scene.
I really hoped when it came out people wouldn't forget about
how it was funded and just kinda talk about the game.
But it seemed like every review had to talk about the development story,
and so that was part of the lore for a long time, still.
So I hope, um, five years from now when people talk about adventure games,
they can look at it as just an adventure game.
And so I think it'll be remembered well, and people can just kinda get over
the crowdfunding part of it.
Kipnis: I--to be honest with you, I'm not really sure how this whole thing is gonna be looked at in the end.
Um...
I--I guess, like, everyone has hopes for, like, a game when it comes out,
and I had certain hopes that, um...
maybe were not fulfilled, necessarily.
And, uh, and it has more to do with just, like, I really hoped people would love the game.
Um, and it's not to say that they didn't, but I kinda just, um--
I think there--there was a lot of controversy surrounding the game and the company
that I wish hadn't been there.
Like, I just wish it was...
I don't know.
Annable: It was a long, hard road, and it was very public,
and I feel like there were a lot of things that changed.
Um, and they weren't necessarily just because of "Broken Age" and its visibility.
I think the company is a different company now than it was three years ago,
and I'm trying to still figure out, why?
I don't know, are we just older?
Offscreen: Do you have any expectation of "Broken Age's" performance?
Annable: I don't know.
Bailey: And then...uh, talking about sales of "Broken Age,"
so, uh, sales on Steam, we had a feature spot.
Um, it acted more like an update than, like, a--a new push.
Um, however, we got a feature on Apple, which is doing really well; about $25,000 a day.
Um, and then we also have, um, sales for, uh, Sony.
PS4, we had, like, $100,000 worth of sales, uh, over the weekend.
And it just got featured, so, uh, that's cool.
Schafer: My expectation-- my expectation of "Broken Age" in the end
would just be to break even.
I know it was kind of always like a Kickstarter, like, you plan on it--
Like, it's--the risk is gone of losing money on it, so you know you've broken even if you just make the game
to that amount of money.
But we made it, like, twice as much, almost, as we got in, or more.
And so, um, we will just about make that back.
And the biggest change is that we don't need the publishers anymore, 100%.
You know, it used to be, like, there was no money in the world outside of publishers.
And I think crowdfunding's here to stay.
I think it's, um, hopefully gonna grow.
And in my dream-- my dream world, it would be big enough to fund AAA games
and it would be the way that we fund all games going forward.
So now when we're talking to a publisher, the deals are better.
We're asking for less money, but we're also not entirely dependent on them
to make payroll next week.
We're not like, "Please, we just--sign us.
We'll--we'll sign anything, we just gotta make payroll." It's like, okay, you gotta kick us in the teeth
once a month and all this stuff.
And now we only have to take good deals with people we like.
So we still work with publishers, but, um, it's different.
Because we're 100% in control.
Annable: Yeah, we're not...
we're not rollin' in millions of dollars.
I--I don't know if that would necessarily make us happier, though.
Schafer: You guys are the best.
Thank you for all your lovely audio.
And thanks for your beard.
Stoddard: It's kind of a milestone.
I think there's a-- there's a few things in general around gaming that "Broken Age," like,
really kinda did a push towards a new area.
And I like that.
Um, there's a whole bunch of stuff, like, we could've done differently
and, like, we definitely fell down in some areas.
But, like, so what?
Like, that's how you-- that's how you go forward.
Like, if you never fail, then you just aren't learning anything.
You're just... being boring, really.
Franzke: I think it was a huge success.
Without this project, who knows?
Maybe Kickstarter would have never been the prime platform for, you know, crowdfunded games.
I think it made it possible for a lot of other people to--to work on their dream projects,
so that's--that's pretty cool, yeah.
So overall, you know, I couldn't be happier, I really couldn't.
And, you know, the other day, um, the other day I went to just a random technology store
here in Germany, and--and we just, um...
walked by this little thing.
So, just have--to see this physical manifestation of all the work that, you know,
went into--into this game is, like, super awesome.
Schafer: Hey, Ray! Good job. Crook: Has the soundtrack in there.
Schafer: Oh, I forgot to mention, it has the soundtrack in there.
Crook: I mean, I guess we did accomplish what we wanted to, which was to do this game.
And we--and we did that, and we--and we finished it.
I think what we did do that was the-- that I think was the most beneficial to everybody
was that we kind of cracked things open and we let people look inside of how things work.
And this maybe will help them to see how things-- uh, how difficult, uh, it is,
and how we're kinda lucky that anything even comes out.
Like, that any video games actually get finished, um, is kind of a miracle.
And--and so that's good.
I hope that-- that helps...
I--I hope that helps people who are fans of video games and like playing video games,
it just helps them understand and have a little bit of empathy towards, uh,
those of us who are in this industry.
Um...you know, we're lucky to be in it, and I--you know, I'm grateful to be in it, um,
but it's not always easy, and--and it's-- and I'm glad that
we were able to show that to people in--in an honest way, so it's kinda neat.
I mean, if Double Fine's not around in 10 years, let's just, say, um-- it'll always be rem--
like, it's out there now forever, right?
Once it's on the Internet, um, it'll always be there.
And so...so...
Double Fine will always be...
...around.
[Music] Stoddard: I think it was very positive.
I think there was a lot of stuff that we really did contribute
to the games industry.
And...uh, and there's a lot of stuff that we sidestepped and, like, misstepped.
And we're trying to learn from that, too.
So, um, considering all that, I--going back and playing the actual game,
I actually think we did really solid work.
And I actually think it's, um...
I think it's a really good game.
I haven't really seen many reactions that are just blas.
Like, it--it's usually a strong reaction, one way or the other.
And to me, in any art form, that's great.
Like, that means that it's provoking something.
And I think that's what this is about.
If, like, we did three years of work and there was all these trials and tribulations
and at the end somebody just went, "Meh," like, that would be crushing!
But it hasn't been like that; it's been the opposite.
Like, it's either really, really good or really, really awful or, you know,
very, very vocal, no matter what.
Great.
Then we did our job.
[Music]